<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Towards Interoperability of ISO Standards for Language Resource Management *</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kiyong</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
							<email>klee@korea.ac.kr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Korea University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
							<email>laurent.romary@loria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Max-Planck Digital Library</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Towards Interoperability of ISO Standards for Language Resource Management *</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9D546272D0C3B5EE35DE0EDA383F95FB</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper reviews and evaluates some of the ISO documents for language resource management. Being developed under ISO/TC 37/SC 4, these documents are at the last stage of approval and publication as international standards. They provide specification languages for the annotation of primary linguistic data and also for the representation of annotated data. The paper makes some technical recommendations to make these specification languages interoperable at the level of both annotation and representation, thus making the use of the resulting language resources sustainable in various areas of language technology applications. * 1 Jointly developed with the TEI Consortium and Chapter 5 XML representation of feature structures in FSR is contained in TEI P5.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>1 Introduction: Purpose and Focus ISO/TC 37/SC 4 was established in May 2002 to develop ISO documents for language resource management (LRM) that can be accepted as international standards. These documents are designed to provide specification languages for the annotation of primary linguistic data of various types and sources and also for the representation of annotated data in a markup language such as XML. The purpose of this paper is to review some of these ISO documents for their interoperability at the level of both annotation and representation and then to make some specific recommendations for their convergence in a pivotal format for the sustainable use of language resources A preliminary version of this work was presented by the first author at a research seminar organized by CTL, City University of Hong Kong, 2009-12-10.   thus produced. It will, however, focus on the representation schemes of those specification languages for LRM, developed under the Working Group 2 of ISO/TC 37/SC 4.</p><p>The paper is organized as follows: section 2 review of some ISO standards for LRM, section 3 Segmentation of primary data, section 4 Identification and reference, section 5 Annotating different layers of linguistic descriptions, section 6 Summary of proposals, and section 7 Concluding remarks.</p><p>2 Review of ISO Standards for LRM ISO/TC 37/SC 4 consists of five working groups (WG's) each with a specific objective. WG 1 aims at working on basic descriptors and mechanisms for language resources, WG 2 on annotation and representation schemes, WG 3 on multilingual text representation, WG 4 on lexical resources, and WG 5 on the workflow of LRM. Except for WG 5, the other four WGs have been activated with a dozen of work items that are now at various stages of development. WG 1 and WG 4 have succeeded in publishing one ISO document each as an international standard: ISO 24610-1:2006 Feature Structure Representation (FSR) 1 and ISO 24613:2008 Lexical Markup Framework (LMF).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Basic Descriptors and Mechanisms</head><p>Two of the documents produced by WG 1 lay the basis of developing other LRM-related standards. One is ISO DIS 24612 Linguistic Annotation Framework (LAF) and another FSR. They are basic descriptors and mechanisms for language resource management. LAF makes at least the following three proposals for: (1) the adoption of standoff annotation, opposed to inline annotation, (2) a data model of a double-deck structure that clearly demarcates between referential and content structures, and (3) the representation of content structures in feature structures. FSR then adopts XML as a markup language and lays out details for the use of XML for representing feature structures. Based on these standards, all of other LRM standards are thus required to follow each of these proposals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Representation Schemes</head><p>With its aim on LRM representation schemes, WG 2 has been most productive. Four of its documents are at the penultimate stage of approval and publication by ISO as international standards and two other documents are at the stage of committee-internal review. Five new work item proposals have also been made this year alone.</p><p>WG documents treat various layers of linguistic descriptions. Two of the documents, ISO DIS 24611 Morphosyntactic Annotation Framework (MAF) and ISO DIS 24615 Syntactic Annotation Framework (SynAF) treat morphosyntax and syntax, respectively, while ISO DIS 24614 Word Segmentation of Text (WordSeg) specifies how a text, say written in Chinese characters, is segmented into words or other segmentation units. The other two are parts of ISO 24617 Semantic Annotation Framework (SemAF) on semantic annotation: one treats the annotation of temporal and event-referring expressions in a text with a specification language called ISO-TimeML and the other part works on the annotation of dialogue acts and other related pragmatic features in dialogues with dialML.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">2</ref> WG 2 has also been preparing other parts of SemAF: Part 3 named entities, Part 4 space, Part 5 semantic roles, and Part 6 discourse relations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Operational Issues for Interoperability</head><p>Naively understood, interoperability means operational consistency. When it applies to a system or a set of schemes, each system or set of schemes must not result in internal inconsistencies nor in incompatibility with other systems or other sets of schemes. By interoperability defined operationally as such, some morphosyntactic descriptions as necessitated in one standard (e.g. WordSeg or Se-mAF) thus needs to conform to another standard (e.g. MAF), which provides such descriptions. These standards are also require to meet the condition of interoperability with other accepted guidelines and recommendations such as TEI guidelines or W3C recommendations. Interoperability is enforced especially when all these layers of linguistic descriptions, each stored in a separate file in standoff manner, converge into one pivotal format to generate one coherent system of information.</p><p>Applied to LRM, interoperability operates at three different levels: annotation, representation, and applications. Our work presented here focuses on the interoperability of ISO specifications for LRM at the level of representation schemes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Segmentation of Primary Data</head><p>Annotation means adding some notes to some parts of a text or some other types of data. For this purpose, the data is segmented into parts so that some relevant parts, called markables, are uniquely identified each with a unique ID and then these parts are referred to in an explicit way.</p><p>A text can be segmented into parts of different sizes. LAF proposes base segmentation that segments primary data into character units. MAF introduces two segmentation units, token and wordForm, while SynAF introduces four more grammatical units, chunk, phrase, clause, and sentence. WordSeg then defines the term word segmentation unit (WSU) as a technical term that may refer to other units than word forms. SemAF-2 introduces the concept of functional segment that allows the segmentation of a single utterance into more than one functional segments each with a distinct communicative function.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Base Segmentation</head><p>In LAF, primary data is segmented into characters that are understood as contiguous byte sequences of a specified length. Each annotated data is then associated with a unique base segmentation of primary data that defines edges between virtual nodes located between each character in the data. For text, the default is one UTF-8 character. Location indexes are considered to fall between characters, starting at 0. For example, consider the text:</p><p>(1) a. Text: Mia's looked me up.</p><p>b. Base segmentation: <ref type="table">0 1 2 3 45 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8</ref>  The location indexes for each token are referenced to as spans with start and end.</p><p>(2) Location Indexes as Spans:</p><p>Mia: from="0" to="3" 's: from="3" to="5" looked: from="6" to="12" me: from="13" to="15" up:from="16" to="18" .: from="18" to="19"</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Token and Word Form</head><p>In segmenting text or other type of linguistic data into morphosyntactic units, MAF introduces two concepts, token and word form, that are well-known in NLP communities. It then shows ways of representing annotated data in XML with two elements, &lt;token&gt; and &lt;wordForm&gt;, corresponding to these two concepts.</p><p>The tokenization of sample text (1a) given earlier is represented in MAF, as below:<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">3</ref> </p><p>(3) Tokenization:</p><p>&lt;token id="t1" from="0" to="3"&gt; Mia&lt;/token&gt; &lt;token id="t2" from="3" to="5"&gt; 's&lt;/token&gt; &lt;token id="t3" from="6" to="12"&gt; looked&lt;/token&gt; &lt;token id="t4" from="13" to="15"&gt; me&lt;/token&gt; &lt;token id="t5" from="16" to="18"&gt; up&lt;/token&gt; &lt;token id="t6" from"18" to="19"&gt; .&lt;/token&gt;</p><p>With this, MAF can now show in standoff notation how the sample text is segmented into word forms.</p><p>Here two discontiguous tokens t3 and t5 are shown to form a single complex word "looked ... up". 4</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Word Segmentation (WordSeg)</head><p>WordSeg consists of two parts: Part 1 treats some basic concepts and general principles of word segmentation of text and Part 2 specific details of word segmentation of Chinese, Japanese and Korean text. This standard is particularly needed to treat written text of Chinese and some other languages in which each character may be treated as a word.</p><p>Consider the following fragment of Chinese text:</p><p>(5) Chinese Text: 白菜和猪肉 This fragment consists of five characters, each of which can be segmented as words, as a whole meaning "white vegetables accord pig meat". Its normal interpretation, however, is "lettuce goes well with pork". The first two characters "白菜" together are ordinarily treated as a single word that refers to a a particular type of vegetable independent of its color just like the word "blackboard" in English. The last two characters "猪肉" are also understood in the same manner, referring to pork as a one word consisting of two characters.</p><p>Such segmentations can be represented in MAF. First, each of the five characters is marked up as a token.</p><p>(6) Tokenization for Chinese: &lt;token xml:id="t1" from="0" to="1"/&gt; &lt;token xml:id="t2" from="1" to="2"/&gt; &lt;token xml:id="t3" from="2" to="3"/&gt; &lt;token xml:id="t4" from="3" to="4"/&gt; &lt;token xml:id="t5" from="4" to="5"/&gt; Then we have:</p><p>(7) Word Segmentation: <ref type="bibr">4</ref> As will be discussed presently, the attribute names @id and @tokens need to be replaced by @xml:id and @target, respectively, in order to be compliant to TEI P5. &lt;wordForm lemma="白菜" target="#t1 #t2"/&gt; &lt;wordForm lemma="和" target="#t3"/&gt; &lt;wordForm lemma="猪肉" target="#t4 #t5"/&gt; The word form "猪肉" can further be segmented into two word segmentation units, "猪" and "肉". This granularity can be treated by introducing two elements &lt;wfAlt&gt; and &lt;wfColl&gt;, corresponding to &lt;vAlt&gt; and &lt;vColl&gt; in the XML representation of feature structures, and also an attribute @org with a possible value "list" associated with &lt;wfColl&gt;.</p><p>(8) Granularity of Word Segmentation &lt;wordForm lemma="白菜" target="#t1#t2"/&gt; &lt;wordForm lemma="和" target="#t3"/&gt; &lt;wfAlt&gt; &lt;wordForm lemma="猪肉"target="#t4#t5"/&gt; &lt;wfColl org="list"/&gt; &lt;wordForm lemma="猪" target="#t4"/&gt; &lt;wordForm lemma="肉" target="#t5"/&gt; &lt;/wfColl&gt; &lt;/wfAlt&gt;}</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Syntactic Units</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ISO DIS 24615 Syntactic Annotation Framework</head><p>applies to segments of a text that are analyzed as sentences, dealing with their constituency and the dependency among the sentential constituents. In addition to the concept of sentence, SynAF introduces the following concepts: word, chunk, phrase, and clause.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">5</ref> These concepts need to be incorporated into the syntactic annotation of linguistic data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Generalization of Various Types of Segmentation</head><p>Various types of segmentation can be generalized with an element &lt;seg&gt; with an attribute @type that has a list of appropriate values that includes characterBased, token, wordForm, word, chunk, phrase, clause, sentence, etc. By this generalization, the element &lt;token&gt;, for instance, is understood as an alternative representation of &lt;seg type="token"/&gt;. This also makes it easier to accommodate any new type of segmentation such as funcSeg for functional segment that is introduced in Part 2 of SemAF for dialogue acts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Identification and Reference</head><p>Base segmentation locates characters in primary data, while tokens are each identified with a unique span in which an associated sequence of characters is located. These tokens with unique id's are then referred to for the unique identification of word forms or larger segments of a text.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Identifying Segments</head><p>In MAF and a few other LRM documents, the @id attribute uniquely assigns an ID to a token or other linguistic segments of primary data so that they can be uniquely identified. Then these segments are referred to with their unique ID's for identifying other segments.</p><p>Here is an example from MAF:</p><p>(9) Older Version &lt;wordForm id= "w3" tokens="t4 t5"/&gt;</p><p>This fails to conform to the following conventions in TEI Guidelines P5: (a) Prefixing of xml: to @id, (b) Introducing @target which lists the value of each @id attribute that is referred to, and (c) Prefixing of # to each attribute-value that is referred to. These conventions are very simple, but are needed to clearly distinguish what is identified from what is referred to.</p><p>MAF can now be easily modified to accommodate these conventions:</p><p>(10) Revised: &lt;wordForm xml:id="w3"target="#t4 #t5"/&gt; Or &lt;seg type="wordForm"xml:id="w3" target="#t4#t5"/&gt;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Reference in Linking Structures</head><p>In addition to the two elements &lt;EVENT&gt; and &lt;TIMEX3&gt;, the following three elements are introduced in ISO-TimeML for linking structures: &lt;TLINK&gt;, &lt;SLINK&gt; and &lt;ALINK&gt;. Here is an example for the use of &lt;TLINK&gt;, which anchors an event to a time here:</p><p>(11) Mia looked me up yesterday.</p><p>(12) Temporal Linking:</p><p>&lt;EVENT xml:id="e1" pred="LOOK_UP" target="#token2 #token4" tense="PAST"/&gt; &lt;TIMEX3 xml:id="t1" type="DATE" value="2009-12-10"/&gt; &lt;TLINK target="#e1#t1"relType="DURING"/&gt; Here, the two values #e1 and #t1 for the @target attribute in &lt;TLINK&gt; refer to the value e1 of the xml:id attribute in the &lt;EVENT&gt; element and the value t1 of the xml:id attribute in the &lt;TIMEX3&gt; element, respectively. Such a specification of the target attribute in &lt;TLINK&gt; is then understood as relating e1 to t1 with the relation type DURING. For this representation, ISO-TimeML is again modified to be conformant to the TEI P5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Annotating Different Layers of Linguistic Descriptions</head><p>There are several standards that are being developed under ISO/TC 37/SC 4/WG 2, each of which provides a different representation scheme for annotating a different layer of linguistic descriptions. MAF treats morphosyntactic descriptions, SynAF syntactic descriptions, each part of SemAF a specified subarea of semantic descriptions, while WordSeg deals with segmentation issues only. All these linguistic descriptions need to converge on a unified structure of linguistic information. For illustration, we show how MAF and SemAF-Time provide different types of linguistic content and how they can merge into a single unified structure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Morphosyntactic Descriptions (MAF)</head><p>After identifying each word form the &lt;wordForm&gt; element, MAF adds morphosyntactic information content to it in feature structures, as is required of a data model by LAF.</p><p>(13) Morpho-syntactic Description:</p><p>&lt;MAF&gt; &lt;wordForm xml:id="w1" target="#t1"&gt; &lt;fs type="morpho-syntax"&gt; &lt;f name="lemma"&gt; &lt;string&gt;Mia&lt;/string&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="pos"&gt; &lt;symbol value="noun"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="person"&gt; &lt;symbol value="third"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="number"&gt; &lt;symbol value="singular"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="gender"&gt; &lt;symbol value="feminine"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;/fs&gt; &lt;/wordForm&gt; &lt;/MAF&gt;</p><p>The feature structure represented here in XML is conformant to FSR as well as to TEI P5. It introduces the element &lt;symbol&gt; to specify values of some particular features like grammatical ones that constitute a very restricted set of symbols. The feature name person, for instance, has only three values: first, second, and third.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">6</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Semantic Annotation (SemAF)</head><p>SemAF-Time specifies how to annotate temporal and event-related information in a text. Here is an example repeated here:</p><p>(14) Primary data:</p><p>Mia looked me up yesterday.</p><p>(15) Annotation:</p><p>&lt;EVENT xml:id="e1" pred="LOOK_UP" target="#token2 #token4" pos="VERB" tense="PAST"/&gt; &lt;TIMEX3 xml:id="t1" target="#token5" type="DATE" value="2009-11-30"/&gt; &lt;TLINK target="#e1#t1"relType="DURING"/&gt; This representation conforms to TEI P5, but fails to conform to LAF at least on two scores. First, it fails to separate referential structures from content structures. Second, it fails to represent content structures in feature structures. Furthermore, it fails to separate morphosyntactic information from semantic information.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">7</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Resolving Interoperability</head><p>In order to resolve this incongruence, we first construct the &lt;MAF&gt; structure and the &lt;isoTimeML&gt; structure separately, with their appropriate name spaces specified, and then merge them into a single &lt;semAF&gt; structure.</p><p>(16) Merging MAF and isoTimeML: &lt;semAF xmlns:iso="http//www.iso.org/semAF&gt; &lt;MAF xmlns:iso="http://www.iso.org/maf"&gt; &lt;wordForm xml:id="w2" target="#token2 #token4"&gt; &lt;fs type="morpho-syntax"&gt; &lt;f name="lemma"&gt; &lt;string&gt;look up&lt;/string&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="POS"&gt; &lt;symbol value="VERB"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;/fs&gt; &lt;/wordForm&gt; &lt;wordForm xml:id="w4"target="#token5"&gt; &lt;fs type="morpho-syntax"&gt; &lt;f name="lemma"&gt; &lt;string&gt;yesterday&lt;/string&gt; &lt;f name="POS"&gt; &lt;symbol value="ADVERB"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;/fs&gt; &lt;/wordForm&gt; &lt;/MAF&gt; &lt;isoTimeML xmlns:iso="http:// www.iso.org/semAF/isoTimeML"&gt; &lt;EVENT xml:id="e1" target="#w2"&gt; &lt;fs type="OCCURRENCE"&gt; &lt;f name="PRED"&gt; &lt;string&gt;LOOK_UP&lt;/string&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="TENSE"&gt; &lt;symbol value="PAST"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;/fs&gt; &lt;/EVENT&gt; &lt;TIMEX3 xml:id="t1" target="#w4"&gt; &lt;fs type="temporal annotation"&gt; &lt;f name="DATE"&gt; &lt;string&gt;2009-11-30&lt;/string&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;/fs&gt; &lt;/TIMEX3&gt; &lt;TLINK xml:id="tL1"target="#e1 #t1"&gt; &lt;fs type="temporal anchoring"&gt; &lt;f name="relType"&gt; &lt;symbol value="DURING"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;/fs&gt; &lt;/TLINK&gt; &lt;/isoTimeML&gt; &lt;/semAF&gt; Suppose the given data is part of a dialogue like the following:</p><p>(17) Primary data: Dialogue 1 (Gio,fs1): Mia looked me up yesterday. (Gia,fs2): Did she?</p><p>SemAF-Dacts can add more information to the annotation given above by inserting the following annotation into the &lt;semAF&gt; structure. <ref type="bibr">8</ref> Here we have assumed that the dialogue material is identifed as consisting of two utterances u1 and u2 in a preprocessed text segmentation, which constitute functional segments fs1 and fs2, respectively, each with a distinct communicative function.</p><p>(18) Dialgoue Annotation: &lt;diaml xmlns="http://www.iso.org/diaml/"&gt; &lt;maf xmlns="http://www.iso.org/maf/"&gt; &lt;text xml:id="dialogue1" target="#string-range(#text,0,35)"&gt; &lt;seg type="token" xml:id="token1" target="#string-range(#text,0,3)"&gt; ... &lt;seg type="token" xml:id="token9" target="#string-range(#text,34,35)"&gt; &lt;/text&gt; &lt;/maf&gt; &lt;text xml:id="dialogue1" target="#token1...#token9"&gt; &lt;seg type="funcSeg" xml:id="fs1" target="#token1...#token6"/&gt; &lt;seg type="funcSeg" xml:id="fs2" target="#token7...#token9"/&gt; &lt;/text&gt; &lt;comment xml:id="dialogue1" target="#fs1 #fs2"&gt; &lt;fs type="dialogue"&gt; &lt;f name="participants"&gt; &lt;vColl org="list"&gt; &lt;string&gt;Gio&lt;/string&gt; &lt;string&gt;Gia&lt;/string&gt; &lt;/vColl&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;/fs&gt; &lt;/comment&gt; &lt;dialActs xml:id="da1" target="#fs1"&gt; &lt;fs type="dialogue act"&gt; &lt;f name="sender"&gt; &lt;fVal target="#Gio/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="addressee"&gt; &lt;fVal target="#Gia"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="communicativeFunction"&gt; &lt;symbol value="inform"/&gt; &lt;/fs&gt; &lt;/dialActs&gt; &lt;dialActs xml:id="da2" target="#fs2"&gt; &lt;fs type="dialogue act"&gt; &lt;f name="sender"&gt; &lt;fVal target="#Gia/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="addressee"&gt; &lt;fVal target="#Gio"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="communicativeFunction"&gt; &lt;symbol value="checkQuestion"/&gt; &lt;/fs&gt; &lt;/dialActs&gt; &lt;/dialml&gt;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Proposals for Representational Interoperability</head><p>A list of proposals is given here to show how some of the key requirements of TEI, LAF, and FSR can be met for the interoperability of representing lingustic annotations. First, we discuss a set of TEI requirements that are laid out in TEI P5 for segmentation, identification and reference. Then we make proposals following the three key requirements laid out by LAF:</p><p>(1) Standoff annotation opposed to inline annotation, (2) demarcation of referencing and content structures, and (3) representation of content structures in feature structures. These requirements need to be met for the operation of a pivotal format that allows the merging, extension, and exchange of different types of annotation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Segmentation of Primary Data</head><p>For the segmentation of text or any data in general, TEI introduces the &lt;seg&gt; element with a list of appropriate types. We list these types as follows:</p><p>(19) Proposal 1: Introduce the &lt;seg&gt; element, with the following @type attribute and with a list of appropriate vavlues baseSeg, token, wordForm, chunk, phrase, clause, sent and funcSeg:</p><p>(20) Segmentation:</p><p>a. &lt;seg type="token"/&gt; b. &lt;seg type="wordForm"/&gt; c. &lt;seg type="funcSeg"/&gt;</p><p>We may, however, adopt an alternative representation as allowed in TEI.</p><p>(21) Convention 1: Interpret &lt;token&gt;, &lt;word Form&gt;, etc. as alternatives (or syntactic sugar) to: &lt;seg type="token"&gt;, &lt;seg type="wordForm"&gt;, etc., respectively.</p><p>This convention allows elements such as &lt;token&gt;, &lt;wordForm&gt;, etc. corresponding to the values of the @type attribute, as listed in Proposal 1. The &lt;token&gt; element is then understood as standing for &lt;seg type="token"&gt;.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Identication and Reference</head><p>Following TEI again, we adopt the following:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(22) Proposal 2</formula><p>a. The @xml:id should be systematically used and references to element identifier made through URIs. b. Introduce the @target attribute with a sequence of URIs as value.</p><p>(23) Illustration for Prop 2:</p><p>&lt;seg type="wordForm" xml:id="word2" target="#token2 #token4"/&gt;</p><p>The reference mechanism may extend to linking structures, as illustrated below:</p><p>(24) Reference for Linking:</p><p>&lt;TLINK type="temporal" target="#e1 #t1"&gt; &lt;fs type="temporal anchoring"&gt; &lt;f name="relType"&gt; &lt;symbol value="DURING"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;/fs&gt; &lt;/TLINK&gt; Here the &lt;TLINK&gt; is understood as &lt;link type="temporal"&gt;.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Standoff Annotation</head><p>Now following LAF, we propose the following: Proposal 3: Adopt standoff annotation.</p><p>The following annotation exemplifies how one should adopt a syntax that is continuous to the URI reference. It adopts the string-range() XPointer scheme (with the hypothesis that an xml:base has been defined in the parent element):<ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">9</ref> (25) Illustration for Prop 3: a. Inline: &lt;seg type="token" xml:id="token1" target="#string-range(#text,0,3)"&gt; Mia&lt;/seg&gt; b. Standoff:</p><p>&lt;seg type="token" xml:id="token1" target="#string-range(#text,0,3)" form="Mia"/&gt; target="#token2 #token4"&gt; &lt;fs type="morpho-syntax"&gt; &lt;f name="LEMMA"&gt; &lt;string&gt;look up&lt;/strng&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="POS"&gt; &lt;symbol value="VERB"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;/wordForm&gt; &lt;/MAF:MAF&gt; &lt;TimeML:isoTimeML xmlns:TimeML= "http://www.iso.org/semAF/isoTimeML"&gt; &lt;TimeML:EVENT xml:id="e1" target="#w2"&gt; &lt;fs type="OCCURRENCE"&gt; &lt;f name="PRED"&gt; Each of the elemnts &lt;annLRM&gt;, &lt;MAF&gt; and isoTimeML provide their respective namespaces, while the elements &lt;wordForm&gt; and &lt;EVENT&gt; each represent their respective referential structure.</p><p>To each of these referential structures a feature structure is embedded.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Concluding Remarks</head><p>For ISO, standards are documents. Applicable to the standardization of LRM, the number of the documents has amounted to more than a dozen, including six newly proposed work items. For the interoperability of these standards, their representation schemes have been examined especially with respect to some of the requirements laid out by TEI, LAF, and FSR. All the issues discussed are technical in the sense that their resolutions are basically constrained by the very conventional nature of the representation language, namely XML, adopted for the annotation of language resources. It is hoped in further study that our proposals be elaborated with details and incorporated into one of the ISO documents that deals with basic representational requirements.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>9 |M|i|a|'s| |l|o|o|k|e|d| |m|e| |u|p|.|</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Proposal 4: a. Construct each data model as a double-deck structure, consisting of (1) referential structure and (2) annotation content structure. b. Specify the attributes @xml:id and target with appropriate values in each referential structure. c. Represent each annotation content structure in feature structures.</figDesc><table><row><cell>6.4 Data Model: Referential Structure and</cell></row><row><cell>Annotation Content Structure</cell></row><row><cell>Being conformant to LAF, we prose the following:</cell></row><row><cell>(26) (27) Illustration for Prop 4:</cell></row><row><cell>a. Mia looked me up.</cell></row><row><cell>b. &lt;LRM:annLRM</cell></row><row><cell>xmlns="http://www.iso.org/LRM</cell></row><row><cell>xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;MAF:MAF</cell></row><row><cell>xmlns:MAF="http://www.iso.org/maf&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;MAF:wordForm xml:id="w2"</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>This document is at the stage of committee-internal review.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_1"><p>The following representation is in inline notation, but needs to be changed to standoff notation, as is required by LAF. See section 2.1.(4) Word Forms: &lt;wordForm lemma= "Mia" tokens="t1"/&gt; &lt;wordForm lemma= "have" tokens="t2"/&gt; &lt;wordForm lemma= "look up" tokens="t3 t5"/&gt; &lt;wordForm lemma= "I" tokens="t4"/&gt;</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Applied to non-inflectional languages like Chinese, note that the concepts word and word forms are identical.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_3"><p>Open ANC does not follow such details of FSR on the use of XML for representing feature structures, although it uses FSR for representing linguistic annotation content.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_4"><p>The third point has been indicated by HarryBunt (personal  communication).</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_5"><p>The annotation given below is slightly modified from the one proposed in<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Harry et al. (2009)</ref> and also from Part 2 of se-mAF for dialogue acts. Furthermore, the two attributes @to and from that specifies a span with start and end in base segmentation are replaced by a sing attribute @target with its values specified with #string-range(#text,i,j), where i stands for start and j for end.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="9" xml:id="foot_6"><p>Briefly discussed in section 5.3, footnote 8. &lt;string&gt;LOOK_UP&lt;/string&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;f name="tense"&gt; &lt;symbol value="PAST"/&gt; &lt;/f&gt; &lt;/fs&gt; &lt;/TimeML:EVENT&gt; &lt;/TimeML:isoTimeML&gt; &lt;/LRM:annLRM&gt;</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgment</head><p>The first author wishes to thank Prof. Jonathan Webster, Dr. Alex Fang, and other faculty and staff members of Department of Chinese, Translation and Linguistics, City University of Hong Kong, for their invitation that enabled him to stay at this department as visiting professor and to complete the drafting of the paper and also to all the members of the Dialogue Systems Group of City University for their support and comments.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards an ISO standard for dialogue act annotation. Unpublished. Nancy Ide and Laurent Romary</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Harry</forename><surname>Bunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Alexandersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jean</forename><surname>Carletta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jae-Woong</forename><surname>Choe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alex</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Koiti</forename><surname>Hasida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Volha</forename><surname>Petukhova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrei</forename><surname>Popescu-Belis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claudia</forename><surname>Soria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Traum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kiyong</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Naturaql Language Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="225" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2009. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>International standard for a linguistic annotation framework</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards international standards for language resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nancy</forename><surname>Ide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Evaluation of Text and Speech Systems</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dybkjaer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hemsen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Minker</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="284" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kiyong</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lou</forename><surname>Burnard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><surname>De La Clergerie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thierry</forename><surname>Declerck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Syd</forename><surname>Bauman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Harry</forename><surname>Bunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lionel</forename><surname>Clement</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tomaz</forename><surname>Erjavec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Azim</forename><surname>Roussanaly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claude</forename><surname>Roux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Towards an international standard on feature structure representation. Workshop Proceedings of The Fourth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2004)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lisbon</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ISO DIS 24614-1 Language Resource Management -Word Segmentation of Text -Part 1: Basic Concepts and General Principles (WordSeg-1). ISO/TC 37/SC 4/WG 2. International Organization for Standardization (ISO)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kiyong</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Pustejovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Branimir</forename><surname>Boguraev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ISO/TC 37/SC 4/WG 1</idno>
		<ptr target="ISO/TC37/SC4/WG2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Towards an international standard for annotating temporal information. The Third International Conference on Terminology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Japanese</forename><surname>Chinese</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Korean</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>SemAF-Time; SemAF-NE</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Space (ISO-Space</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006. 2006. 2006. 2008. 2008. 2008. 2009. 2009. 2009. 2009. 2009. 2009. 2009. 2009. 2009. 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24613</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24610" to="24611" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Standardization and Technology Transfer, Beijing. International Organization for Standardization</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Dialgoue Acts (SemAF-Dacts). ISO/TC 37/SC 4/WG 2. International Organization of Standardization. 2009. ISO PWI 24617-3 Language Resource Management -Semantic Annotation Framework -Part 3: Named Entities</note>
	<note>Language Resource Management -Persistent Identification and Access for Language Technology Applications (PID). International Organization for Standardization (ISO). 2009. ISO PWI 24620-1 Simplified Natural Language -Part 1: Basic Concepts and General Principles (simppL-1). ISO/TC 37/SC 4/WG X and Object Management Group (OMG</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ISO PWI 24621 Language Resource Management -Date-Timne Vocabulary (tempVoc)</title>
		<idno>ISO/TC 37/SC 4/WG 2</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>International Organization for Standardization</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Object Management Group (OMG)</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Language of Time: A Reader</title>
		<editor>Interjeet Mani, James Pustejovsky, and Rob Gaizauskas</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The specification language TimeML</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Pustejovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Ingria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Roser</forename><surname>Sauri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jose</forename><surname>Gastano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jessica</forename><surname>Littman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rob</forename><surname>Gaizauskas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Setzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Graham</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><surname>Habel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Mani et al.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Pustejovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kiyong</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Harry</forename><surname>Bunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">ISO-TimeML: an International Standard for Semantic Annotation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Unpublished</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
