<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">212140906FF5318010D92307B9077C7C</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The TEI at a glance    -Based on a hierarchical abstract model (cristals)</p><p>• &lt;form&gt;: for characterising the othographic or phonetic form of the word -&lt;orth&gt;, &lt;pron&gt;, etc.</p><p>• &lt;gramGrp&gt;: grammatical features -May also appear in &lt;form&gt; Overall picture tei.gramInfo &lt;pos&gt; &lt;gramGrp&gt; Declaring the class: tei.gramInfo &lt;classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="dictionaries-decl" id="GRAMINFO" type="model" ident="tei.gramInfo"&gt; &lt;gloss&gt;grammatical information&lt;/gloss&gt; &lt;desc&gt;groups those elements allowed within a &lt;gi&gt;gramGrp&lt;/gi&gt; element in a dictionary.&lt;/desc&gt; &lt;/classSpec&gt; &lt;pos&gt; belongs to tei.gramInfo &lt;elementSpec module="dictionaries" id="POS" ident="pos"&gt; &lt;gloss&gt;part of speech&lt;/gloss&gt; &lt;desc&gt;indicates the part of speech assigned to a dictionary headword (noun, verb, adjective, etc.)&lt;/desc&gt; &lt;classes&gt; &lt;memberOf key="tei.dictionaryParts"/&gt; &lt;memberOf key="tei.gramInfo"/&gt; &lt;memberOf key="tei.dictionaries"/&gt; &lt;/classes&gt; &lt;content&gt; … &lt;/content&gt; &lt;exemplum&gt; … &lt;/exemplum&gt; &lt;/elementSpec&gt;  • LMF serialization seen as -A subset of the TEI when equivalent construct exist -An extension of the TEI for missing constructs (e.g. syntax)</p><p>• Some concrete work on the table… -Aside activities: specifying LL-LIF in ODD</p><p>• Reference -L. Romary, "Standardization of the formal representation of lexical information for NLP" -http://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00436328/fr/</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>-•</head><label></label><figDesc>ISO standard 24613 (published Oct. 2008) -Edited within ISO committee TC 37/SC 4• Technical content -Focus on provided a core meta-model with extensions -Potentially agnostic with regards serialisation • Isomorphism =&gt; interoperability -Default syntax to exemplify its possible use, room for improvement… • Can the TEI be seen as a Basic structure already defined • Provision of additional tags -Surface annotation (e.g. names, dates, abbreviations, alternatives) -Cf&lt;equiv&gt; equivalences to ISOCat when needed • Integration of lexical data in a textual macro-structure -Creating an edited version of a lexica -Grammar books, teaching material, scientific papers • Interoperability with other lexical sources -Community of users: sharing a common culture of TEI tags rather than constantly worrying about mappings -Sharing tools: e.g. stylesheets, editors, etc. (cf. Roma) -Note: continuity between dictionary and lexical sources &lt;hyph&gt; ) /syllabification/ (&lt;syll&gt;) /stress pattern/ (&lt;stress&gt; ) /part of speech/ (&lt;pos&gt;) /inflexional class/ (&lt;itype&gt;) /gender/ (&lt;gen&gt;) /number/ (&lt;number&gt;) /case/ (&lt;case&gt;) /person/ (&lt;per&gt;) /tense/ (&lt;tns&gt;) /mood/ (&lt;mood&gt;) /definition/ (&lt;def&gt;) /example/ (&lt;eg&gt;) /usage/ (&lt;usg&gt;) /etymology/ (&lt;etym&gt;) Customizing the TEI lexical model • Constraining the TEI model -Sub-setting the TEI default dictionary module -Providing additional rules (XSLT, Schematron) -Constraining possible values• Complementing the TEI model -Defining additional data categories -Defining missing LMF extensions as TEI components • Make use of the class mechanisms • A natural implementation of the LMF extension mechanisms Towards a joint ISO-TEI activity • Contributing to convergence, with a pragmatic prespective • Benefiting from advantages of both sides -TEI reactivity and community support -ISO stability and international validation</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
