<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Contrastive Indexing Method and its Integration in Aquarelle Folders</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bonhomme</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">CRIN/CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INRIA Lorraine</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">FRANCE</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">CRIN/CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INRIA Lorraine</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">FRANCE</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Contrastive Indexing Method and its Integration in Aquarelle Folders</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">714592C03BD99CDF8299EEAE5EE0C7D2</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:02+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The Aquarelle 1 architecture is designed and built in a user oriented perspective. Folder archiving, indexing and retrieval must thus be designed for data access through «user friendly», yet expeditious, methods. This is a major challenge to the Information Systems in the Aquarelle organisation. This document addresses the role of advanced full text indexing in delivering data access and archiving applications. Our aim is to investigate the effective use of structured folders using automatic or assisted indexing in a multimedia and multilingual environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.0">General Presentation</head><p>One of the main objectives of the Aquarelle Project is to provide a user with the technical facilities supporting information retrieval by querying. And our specific task at the CRIN-CNRS &amp; INRIA Lorraine (within Work Package 6 [6]) is to design a Full Text Retrieval System, including mechanisms for automatic indexing of documents using the information available within texts dealing with these documents. The prototype we are developing, based upon a new method we called Contrastive Full Text Indexing, has been integrated within the Grif SGML Editor and tested on two different protocols:</p><p>• Blind (or free indexing), that is with no reference to a given thesaurus. This has the advantage of providing non technical words which a user could employ within his request.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>• Oriented (or controlled) indexing, with an existing thesaurus containing words close to the artwork being indexed. This collocation word method is a ˝contrastive˝ indexing method <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. This task is a collaboration between INRIA, GRIF and FORTH/ICS In addition, since Aquarelle is to support Multilingual or Crosslingual Information Retrieval, it is important, and crucial for perpetuating the Aquarelle Project, to supply the users with multilingual thesauri if they exist or to contribute to the translation of the thesaurus. We achieve a tool which automatically aligns a text and its translation <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1]</ref>. This tool will assist the translation of thesauri resources across language. This task is a collaboration between INRIA, FORTH and ILSP</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.0">Full Text Indexing and Contrastive Method</head><p>Our aim is to facilitate the effective use of structured folders using automatic or assisted indexing of SGML document.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">General Method for an Indexing System</head><p>We want to provide a key word extraction to index the textual content of the different documents of a given collection or the sub-documents (from an SGML point of view) of a single document. The following indexing method is based on the number of occurrences of tokens in the documents of a collection:</p><p>1. Use of the SGML structure for each document (or sub-document) to locate textual data. Where appropriate content identifiers (tokens/terms) might be found? -text, description,...</p><p>-titles, abstracts,... 3. Assignment of term weights depending on term importance using:</p><p>• The Inverted Document Frequency (IDF) weights</p><p>• The Reduced Deviation (RD) method to supply user with indications about words occurring more than the mean around a given hub word-type, token or term. This probabilistic method is used in corpus linguistic studies, collocation word extraction and more generally in semantics and lexicology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Contrastive</head><p>Full Text Indexing Method (CFTI)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">General Framework</head><p>The Aquarelle users are supposed to be museum curators, urban planners, commercial publishers and researchers. All users should be able to collect the information relevant to their need or answering their curiosity, wherever the information components are located with the aim of organising exhibitions and producing such information products as books or CD-ROM. The amount of information increase the need, for a professional user, in information retrieval and extraction and in content analysis. It is necessary to get rid of the non relevant information by either filtering with a thesaurus and some authority file supports or with a semantic access to the plain text.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">Specification for a Contrastive Approach</head><p>The meaning of a word is decidable with its linguistic and/or situational context. We use the test of statistical significance to filter the context and to reveal a set of words occurring around a specified word (a hub-word) within a short span in a text (a window). Words co-occurring around a hub-word share some recurring semes organized in structures. We observed that the test of Reduced Deviation could assist the thematic retrieval within a collection of documents or within parts of a document. The main principle of a contrastive approach is to compare (or to contrast) a reference collection of texts with a working collection of textual data. The working collection extracted from the reference collection, is a subset of the whole reference collection. The extraction of the working collection can result from:</p><p>• A text windowing procedure,</p><p>• A selection of some SGML elements (and their content).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reference Collection</head><p>Working Collection text windows (+/-tokens)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3">Theoretical Principle</head><p>The goal of this method is to supply user with indications about words occurring more than the mean around a given hub-word or term. It is left to the user to decide which among those words are semantically linked with the given hub-word. In this case information uniformly distributed (empty words, more frequently words,...) will not appear in the result of a Reduced Deviation procedure. This kind of non information is of course non relevant for the document and is also language independent. The remaining words will be more relevant compared with other documents (or other parts in the same document).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.4">Probabilist Principle</head><p>Our model is based on a probabilistic indexing method which is a statistical assumption about distribution of words in a document. Our hypothesis is that a hub-word (can be a term) has an influence on a given word or another term (a target word). We would be able to determine if a given word (target) co-occur more than the mean around the hub-word. To accept or to reject this hypothesis implies that we take a risk corresponding to the possibility that the target word is not linked to the central word and that its frequent occurrence around the central word is not due to a coincidence. We calculate, to evaluate the risk, what we call: a reduced deviation. We assume, according to our hypothesis, that words occurring around the central word have the same distribution than the whole text. We introduced a normal approximation of the distribution: N(0,1). We calculate the reduced deviation rank r of a word m:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(EQ 1)</formula><p>with: (EQ 2)</p><p>The more important the value (absolute) of the reduced deviation is, the more important the likelihood of the given word will correspond to a semantic link with the hub-word.</p><p>Given this, we can provide a contrastive indexing in comparison to other documents in the collection or to subdocument (part) in the document.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Controlled Indexing</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1">Using a Thesaurus or Authority List</head><p>A hub word can result from an IDF processing or come from a relative thesaurus. Thesaurus can be used to broaden the indexing term by replacing them with the corresponding thesaurus class identifiers or by adding to them the thesaurus class identifiers:</p><p>• choose broader, related or narrowed terms,</p><p>• term associations, term classification,</p><p>• facets or/and hierarchies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2">Expert-user refinement by hand</head><p>It is important for the user, to have the possibility to drive his own indexing procedure, by changing the parameters of the system:</p><p>1. Statistic parameters (size of the windows, threshold, working and reference corpus,...) r Freq observed Freq theor - <ref type="figure">---------------------------------------------------------------=</ref> p m frequency of the word m in the reference collection Freq theor <ref type="figure">---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------=</ref> 2. Linguistic and document parameters (lemmatization or not, stemming words, list of words, definable SGML data structure, working corpus/document, reference corpus/document,...).</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Freq theor 1 p m - () × -</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">An experiment</head><p>A series of experiments are conducted to study the design issues of the Contrastive Indexing system within the Grif SGML Editor. The objectives of this experiment were:</p><p>• To implement two different and complementary indexing methods, a global method (IDF) and a local term method (RD);</p><p>• To fit statistical thresholds and their influences on results indexing;</p><p>• To find the optimum numbers of document and size of documents in number of characters, words, lines,...</p><p>• To establish stop list to remove fluff words or use IDF to remove high-frequency terms non relevant for indexing.</p><p>This experiment have been tested on:</p><p>• A set of 30 folders 1 in SGML format (description of the city of Cognac),</p><p>• A set of documents extracted from the Mérimée data base 2 and converted from HTML into SGML/TEI. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.0">Integration in Aquarelle Folders</head><p>The access to the Aquarelle System is gained by means of a User Client. The Aquarelle User Client offers a document authoring environment for professional usage. It provides two kinds of connection to the Aquarelle System:</p><p>1. A full access through the Aquarelle Access Server on which the user is registered;</p><p>2. A more restricted access through a WWW client.</p><p>In the User Client, a user can have access to details of the informations that is available (in his language or not), using query composition and submission facilities, SGML editing and obviously access to Archive and Folder Servers. It's important for a user to have an interface with the Access Server to retrieve what resources are available and what resources are relevant to work on them. In that aim, the User Client provides query and retrieval utilities to specify queries that identify such relevant documents.</p><p>Within Aquarelle, a folder is considered as an SGML document. In his User Client environment, a user has an Authority Editor System for creating, editing and modifying their structured documents or folders. The Grif SGML Editor is used for folder editing using some specific DTDs and the material for composing a folder being edited is stored into the Client workspace. At the publishing time, to made available the folder in the Folder Server by the Access Server, workspace folder, sub-folders and links are turned into Aquarelle folders and links. At that time, user has the possibility directly from the SGML Editor to launch a keyword extraction procedure on his folder. The result will be stored in the folder profile itself.</p><p>We used the Grif Application Toolkit Environment (GATE) to develop the CFTI system. The GATE API enables:</p><p>• To create of integrated SGML authoring environments,</p><p>• To customize Grif SGML Editor with new menus and functions,</p><p>• To develop Document Oriented Interfaces.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.0">Multilingual Resources Features and Limitations</head><p>Using and producing language resources to support querying and retrieval is a crucial point in the Aquarelle multilingual environments. It includes the use of both trends in language engineering: 2. http://www.culture.fr/cgi-bin/mistral/merimee 1. the statistical trend: allowing for higher precision, it can be used as an automatic start-up in language processing and can be improve by an expert-user refinement.</p><p>2. the semantic trend: allowing for a broader coverage using knowledge bases <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, thesaurus and overriding the initial automatic results when needed.</p><p>To implement multilingual querying using one of this approach (or both), it is necessary to give the corresponding translation of each thesaural term for each new language recognized. But two main problems remain since:</p><p>• concepts expressed by one single term in one language sometime are expressed by distinct terms in another,</p><p>• concepts (or specific terms) expressed in one language sometime are not expressed in another.</p><p>The difficulty of the multilingual thesaurus construction resides in inter-cultural differences of concepts reflected in the thesaurus structure. Terms at the leaf-level are very difficult to translate. In that case, it is useful to provide an assistant to translate query or thesaurus. This kind of tools is based on a parallel concordancer we developed to generate automatically parallel texts.</p><p>As there are more comparable texts <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> than true parallel texts, we want to try our contrastive indexing system with multilingual comparable texts (see: Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>, "Example of token extraction with a bilingual parallel collection," on page 6). Are we able to find some multilingual statistic relief using the Reduced Deviation method with multilingual documents talking about the same subject but with no word-for-word translation ?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.0">Conclusion &amp; Future Works</head><p>The system combines the common developments in information retrieval and free text indexing with the recent advances in lexical statistic. The open architecture makes it easier to integrate the CFTI system to other applications such as web server, digital library, multimedia databases and document delivery. The handling of structured and unstructured data types (with the use of the SGML standart) provides a platform for indexing and linking documents and multimedia objects.</p><p>The following improvements could be accomplished with a modification of the CFTI system:</p><p>• lemmatization and parsing to work with word-type rather than word-token,</p><p>• multiple terms, compound names and NPs, • communication with the thesaurus browser (not only cut and paste).</p><p>To test the system, we also planned to evaluate the prototype by the users. The criteria used for evaluating should be:</p><p>• The user-friendly use and access,</p><p>• The statistical parameters and thresholds,</p><p>• Utilisation of a lemmatizer, a stemmer or without any (loss of the information granularity),</p><p>• The coverage of the collection, the relevant matter,</p><p>• The quantify, the quality of retrieved folders,</p><p>• The relevance, precision and recall for retrieval.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 1 . Example of token extraction in the Collection Cognac Collection COGNAC -Target Word: cognac Collection COGNAC -Element: &lt;DESC&gt;</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>RD</cell><cell>TOKEN</cell><cell cols="2">Fq. WIN Fq. TXT</cell><cell>RD</cell><cell>TOKEN</cell><cell cols="2">Fq. WIN Fq. TXT</cell></row><row><cell>24.8104</cell><cell>institut</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>93</cell><cell>11.0399</cell><cell>maclou</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>80</cell></row><row><cell>21.6968</cell><cell>cognaçais</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>86</cell><cell>10.4327</cell><cell>autel</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>82</cell></row><row><cell>15.7159</cell><cell>archéo</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>73</cell><cell>9.96775</cell><cell>église</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>118</cell></row><row><cell>15.6222</cell><cell>charentes</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>8.57429</cell><cell>paroissiale</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>70</cell></row><row><cell>14.0965</cell><cell>municipal</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>8.43421</cell><cell>escalier</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>67</cell></row><row><cell>11.7747</cell><cell>poitou</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>8.4182</cell><cell>saint</cell><cell>101</cell><cell>220</cell></row><row><cell>11.3867</cell><cell>musée</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>7.8329</cell><cell>périphérie</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>64</cell></row><row><cell>11.3519</cell><cell>saint</cell><cell>125</cell><cell>128</cell><cell>7.18366</cell><cell>support</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>65</cell></row><row><cell>9.9904</cell><cell>élévation</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>41</cell><cell cols="2">7.17207 hermanowicz</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>89</cell></row><row><cell>9.5808</cell><cell>périphérie</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>5.92809</cell><cell>lambert</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>68</cell></row><row><cell>9.37531</cell><cell>antérieure</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>5.83096</cell><cell>sud</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>73</cell></row><row><cell>9.34375</cell><cell>léger</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>5.5313</cell><cell>hôtel</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>62</cell></row><row><cell>8.77337</cell><cell>maître</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>4.96011</cell><cell>creuse</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>44</cell></row><row><cell>8.34589</cell><cell>histoire</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>4.79652</cell><cell>figure</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>47</cell></row><row><cell>7.91525</cell><cell>détail</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>4.76852</cell><cell>distillerie</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>45</cell></row><row><cell>7.11915</cell><cell>françois</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>51</cell><cell>4.67325</cell><cell>poitou</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>35</cell></row><row><cell>7.11911</cell><cell>élévations</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>4.65019</cell><cell>charente</cell><cell>80</cell><cell>146</cell></row><row><cell>7.11704</cell><cell>paroissiale</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>4.49553</cell><cell>moellon</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>40</cell></row><row><cell>6.60507</cell><cell>civat</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>4.30795</cell><cell>calcaire</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>41</cell></row><row><cell>6.03496</cell><cell>hôtels</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>4.2064</cell><cell>paris</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>73</cell></row><row><cell>5.82131</cell><cell>église</cell><cell>59</cell><cell>51</cell><cell>4.20493</cell><cell>couvert</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>35</cell></row></table><note><p>1. coming from the Inventaire Général and encoding with the CI DTD provided by Euroclid</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE 1 . Example of token extraction in the Collection Cognac Collection COGNAC -Target Word: cognac Collection COGNAC -Element: &lt;DESC&gt;</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>RD</cell><cell>TOKEN</cell><cell cols="2">Fq. WIN Fq. TXT</cell><cell>RD</cell><cell>TOKEN</cell><cell cols="2">Fq. WIN Fq. TXT</cell></row><row><cell>5.15833</cell><cell>prieuré</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>4.20493</cell><cell>commerce</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>35</cell></row><row><cell>4.92605</cell><cell>commerce</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>4.02458</cell><cell>toit</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>45</cell></row><row><cell>4.82293</cell><cell>ville</cell><cell>69</cell><cell>52</cell><cell>3.9654</cell><cell>ensemble</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>34</cell></row><row><cell>4.39818</cell><cell>portail</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>3.92757</cell><cell>retable</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>32</cell></row><row><cell>4.20409</cell><cell>maulny</cell><cell>33</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>3.89277</cell><cell>sculpture</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>30</cell></row><row><cell>4.00413</cell><cell>léger</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>3.82414</cell><cell>martell</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>44</cell></row><row><cell>3.7119</cell><cell>hôtel</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>3.7681</cell><cell>françois</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>92</cell></row><row><cell>3.64024</cell><cell>ensemble</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>3.37964</cell><cell>prieure</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>35</cell></row><row><cell>3.63245</cell><cell>autel</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>3.24144</cell><cell>oeuvre</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>46</cell></row><row><cell>3.4955</cell><cell>chapelle</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>3.05144</cell><cell>vierge</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>25</cell></row><row><cell>3.48562</cell><cell>place</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>11.0399</cell><cell>maclou</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>80</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE 2 . Example of token extraction with a bilingual parallel collection l'abbaye de saint-savin (French) with word Cyprien the abbey of saint-savin (English) with word Cyprian</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>RD</cell><cell>Tokens</cell><cell cols="2">F. Text F. Wi n</cell><cell>RD</cell><cell>Tokens</cell><cell cols="2">F. Text F. Win</cell></row><row><cell>11.1239</cell><cell>savin</cell><cell>128</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>11.7426</cell><cell>st</cell><cell>180</cell><cell>19</cell></row><row><cell>9.10967</cell><cell>saints</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>10.0558</cell><cell>savin</cell><cell>133</cell><cell>14</cell></row><row><cell>5.96213</cell><cell>frères</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>8.38392</cell><cell>saints</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>4.37415</cell><cell>probablement</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>8.04809</cell><cell>brothers</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>3.98536</cell><cell>vie</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4.5643</cell><cell>life</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>3.81915</cell><cell>présence</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4.2158</cell><cell>probably</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>3.66779</cell><cell>homme</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3.92405</cell><cell>registers</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>3.52909</cell><cell>épisodes</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3.92405</cell><cell>abbot</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>3.40129</cell><cell>registres</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3.56263</cell><cell>episodes</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>3.17293</cell><cell>autel</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3.35941</cell><cell>altar</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>2</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing multilingual texts for educational purpose</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bonhomme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Actes des Quinzièmes Journées Internationales IA 95</title>
		<meeting>s des Quinzièmes Journées Internationales IA 95<address><addrLine>Montpellier</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>EC2 &amp; Cie</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Design and integration of full-text indexing in aqaurelle folders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bonhomme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Deliverable D6.3, INRIA, 1997. Aquarelle Project</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross language information retrieval: A system for comparable corpus querying</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Picchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Workshop on Croo-linguistic Information Retrieval</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="33" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>SIGIR&apos;96</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using wordnet as a knowledge base for measuring semantic similarity between words</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smeaton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of AICS Conference</title>
		<meeting>AICS Conference<address><addrLine>Trinity College, Dublin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-09">September 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The lingua parallel concordancing project</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mehl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Woolls</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Electronic Texts and the Text Encoding Initiative, A Special Issue of TEXT Technology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Burnard</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="206" to="220" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Oxford University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Scholl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schmuck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Risk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Michard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pascon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Aquarelle annex i -project programme. IE-2005 Information Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
