<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Framework for Multilevel linguistic Annotations</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Patrice</forename><surname>Lopez</surname></persName>
							<email>lopez@dfki.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">DFKI GmbH Saarbr ucken</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
							<email>romary@loria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">LORIA Vand uvre-L es-Nancy</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Framework for Multilevel linguistic Annotations</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9FC00A2A7F183FEC766FE47E181D75E4</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:02+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This article presents a 3-step model for multilayer annotations of corpora. Each kind of annotation for a textual corporacorresponds to a di erent view on the same document. This principle can be expressed rst with a general relational model dedicated to the organisation of LR. This abstract model is then implemented as an application of the XML formalism for the encoding of large corpora. The exploitation of this kind of annotated corpora requires e cient manipulation processes and reversive access. We propose to use a third step representation based on a set of optimised FSA resulting from the parsing of the XML documents. These propositions have been implemented in the rst version of a workbench dedicated to the French Le Monde corpus.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The majority of existing encoding solutions and tools are usually dedicated to one kind of annotation. In particular because there is a di culty to incorporate di erent annotation schemes within one single hierarchy. Morever the growing size of available corpora makes them di cult to exploit and visualize. Besides, maintaining their structure is highly di cult when the annotations become complex.</p><p>The XML encoding formalism allows exibility, portability and easy interchange of Linguistic Ressources LR. Still XML has two main limits for the general encoding of complex multilevel LR:</p><p>Complex structures cannot be easily represented as a single XML model and there is no general methodology to combine multiple XML hierarchies. What is needed is a way t o represent a n abstract view of the data to be encoded so that to fully capture the di erent relations among them. Although highly general and portable, XML does not comprise mechanisms to allow e ecient access and retrieval mechanisms on the corresponding documents, such as those o ered by a classical database. Moreover, to obtain a word given an annotated information can be very slow since the internal representations are not reversible.</p><p>The requirements for multilevel encoding of corpora are presented for example in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bird and Liberman, 1999</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">, Cristea et al., 1998</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">and Dybkj r et al., 1998</ref>. The di erent kinds of LR involved in the annotation schemes are generally stored in di erent XML documents and linked to a reference textual document the corpus resulting in an acyclic graph structure. This representation, in particular the relations it expresses, can be matched against the abstract model of a relational database to allow e cient store and access to the corresponding data. Indeed, the general workbench d e v elopped by the MATE project makes use of such a relational database for the internal representation of XML encoded information <ref type="bibr">Dybkj r et al., 1999.</ref> The present paper intends to interleave XML and relational database approaches in order to obtain a general methodology and models for complex LR exchange and exploitation. We claim that 1 an additional abstract level similar to the one used in relational databases can be useful to de ne XML encoding principles and 2 a light relational database based on FSA inferred from the XML encoding can beparticularly e cient for internal computation.</p><p>Applied to the multilevel annotation, the preliminary abstract model has to express the rela-tions between the reference corpus and the different annotation levels. The solution we proposeaims at associating the multilayer encoding of multiple views on a same corpus and the encoding of information redundancies. These redundoncies obtained from the XML structure would allow the design of internal representations, which can be optimized in time and space on the basis of FSA Finite State Automata. We argue that a high level of structural organization of the LR is likely to lead to e cient processing, through the identi cation of similar factors and shared properties.</p><p>In the next section, we introduce our preliminary abstract level and present the model for multilevel annotations of textual corpora. We then show how to yield an XML encoding scheme from this model. In section 4, we suggest an internal representation inferred from the XML encoding and based on FSA. Finally a rst implementation of these principles, experimented with a corpus of newspaper articles Le Monde, is described.  A morphological lexicon database, as MUL-TEXT Ide and V eronis, 1994, usually associates an in ected word to a set of lemmas and a set of features. Reversible access is needed for generation for example. A lemma is an abstract entity that is represented with a normal form of a word the entry of a dictionary and can be realized with all possible exions of a word. We can distinguish as ressources entities in ected words, lemma and morphological features including a category that will characterize the in ection. An in ection is a relation between one in ected word, one lemma and a set of morphological features. Depending on the sense that one follows this in ection relation from the lemma or from the in ected word, we obtain a reversible access. Each lemma is characterized by a link to one in ected word which is the normal form that identify this lemma see gure 1. Respectively, an in ected word is not always the normal form of a lemma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Second example: TAGML TAGML Tree Adjoining Grammars Markup</head><p>Language is a general norm for encodind and exchange ressources used with Lexicalised Tree Adjoining Grammars. A working group in France gathers people mainly from TA-LaNa, ENST, INRIA Rocquencourt and LO-RIA who work on this formalism and try to de-ne standards for common grammars and grammar exchange, parsers, and tools developments. TAGML is an exemple of the high level of complexity of the ressources to encode. A LTAG grammar is de ned by a morphological lexicon, a syntactic lexicon and a set of schemas non lexicalized elementary tree paterns. The schema are ordered in tree families in order to capture generalities of lexicalizations given by the syntactic lexicon. Improvment of LTAG parsers and tools depends on how this huge amount of datas can be factorized in order to share computation 1 .</p><p>The previous RROM model for morphological lexicon is extented to the other ressources needed at the syntactic level. An in ection a lemma and a set of morphological features including verb mode for example corresponds to a set of schemas. This lexicalization relation can include the instanciation of co-anchors a lemma and a set of possibly underspeci ed morphological features and of some additional syntactic features in the schema. Each syntactical instanciation give a complete elementary tree. If we assume that linguistic principles given in Abeill e et <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">al., 1990 and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Candito, 1999</ref> are full lled by the grammar, each syntactical instanciation corresponds to only one semantic instanciation semantic consistency principle. This model allows an incremental view of the lexicon ressources.</p><p>The gure 2 presents the corresponding RROM. To simplify, tree families and structuration of features are not included in this example.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Principles for multilevel annotated textual corpus</head><p>The principle of virtual ressources consists in describing a document as a set of elementary links possibly unary to subordinate documents. These links are occurences of a given information type which do not duplicate any content described in the documents which they are referring to. For instance a redundant html subdocument can bereached from di erent others WWW pages. The resulting representation is an acyclic graph which is relevant for the representation of multilayer annotations of textual  In order to use this principle for multilevel linguistic annotation, we m ust identify correctly redundant subdocuments. We h a ve realized this identi cation with a RROM. Each level of annotation morpho-syntactic tags, phrase structure, refering expressions, dialogue acts, topics... becomes a di erent view on the same text. Here, a particular annotation is a relation to a word or a sequence of reference words. We generalize this approach b y considering the words as tags expressed in an independant subdocument. These word tags are then linked to a reference axis. Any k i n d o f c o m bined annotations, such as gestures or sounds, can beintegrated according to this linking principle. This is particularly useful for the encoding of multimodal dialogues which may include gestures, visual scenes, speaking and reference representations.</p><p>The minimal unit of description of a textual corpus used to simulate the reference axis is the event. The events are ordered thanks to a strict order relation. An event corresponds to a point on a reference axis similar to the one of <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bird and Liberman, 1999</ref> and can be identi ed with a key. This axis is similar to the one of Bird and Liberman, 1999 and is adequate to represent a temporal axis. For each level of information, an annotation is a relation between a tag and one or more events. Each level of annotation imposes its own semantics on the link relations. A single link from an event t o a w ord can beinterpreted as an occurence of the word in a textual corpus. Two links to two events starting from a tag of gesture can signify the begining and the end of the gesture. Our experience has shown that a direct encoding of these links with the XML link machinery can result in documents which are di cult to develop, interpret and maintain. By using a RROM to represent the relations between various annotations and the reference axis, as shown in gure 3, we can express a multilevel annotation system with a precise comprehensive abstract model that will lead to an e cient use of virtual ressources.</p><p>In gure 3, we see that events are linked with occurrences of a word or a compound. Compounds can be also viewed as a relation between several words n , edge. Each occurrence of a single word or a compound is linked with a morphosyntactic tag. Dependencies relation between two occurrences allow to obtain a full dependency tree. Finally a phrase tag can also be linked to an occurence relation in order to give the phrase category VP, NP, ... of the phrase dominated by this occurrence.</p><p>One can note the similarity between the RROM and the entity relation models used in relational data bases. The main di erence is that the links do not need contain their own attributes: The model can be realized with the current speci cations of the XML norm. It can also use DTD for contraints expressions on ressources. Our proposition can beseen as an attempt to use the well speci ed methodology of relational databases with the portability, the expressivity and the adequacy of XML for textual datas and the e ciency of nite state representation for internal computation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">XML encoding for Multilevel annotated corpora</head><p>XML encoding and tools have several advantages compared with databases: Standardization aspects data exchanges, unicode, existing dedicated tools parsers, style sheet for document conversion, inheritance of the properties of SGML textual ressources and linguistic oriented formalism, header speci cation, Text Encoding Initiative TEI speci cations, .... Moreover XML includes now interesting structuration features thanks to XML links and XML path speci cation. The second step of our representation, the XML encoding, results directly from the organisation model of ressources. Classically, each annotation is composed by a main tag and a list of attributes. Each annotation is identi ed with a single identi er id. The whole set of possible annotations for a given RE are gathered in a single document called auxiliary ressource document. For each RE we have one auxiliary ressource document that represents only the:D suitable:A settings:Np of:P the:D system:Ns ,:PONCT since:ConjS ... lexicon.xml tag.xml w id="w0" the w w id="w1" suitable w w id="w2" settings w w id="w3" of w w id="w4" the w w id="w5" system w ... t id="t0" D t t id="t1" A t t id="t2" Np t t id="t3" P t t id="t4" Ns t ...</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>function.xml</head><p>phrase-tag.xml f id="f0" subject t f id="f1" modifier t f id="f2" determiner t f id="f3" noun noun complement t f id="f4" S t ... pt id="pt0" NP t pt id="pt1" VP t pt id="pt2" PP t pt id="pt3" AP t pt id="pt4" S t ... occurrence relations occurrence.xml link id="l0" event="0000" targets="lexicon.xmlw0 tag.xmlt0" link id="l1" event="0001" targets="lexicon.xmlw1 tags.xmlt1" link id="l2" event="0002" targets="lexicon.xmlw2 tag.xmlt2 phrase-tag.xmlpt0" link id="l3" event="0003" targets="lexicon.xmlw3 tag.xmlt3" link id="l4" event="0004" targets="lexicon.  one time all the tags necessary for the corpus annotation. For each annotation level, we h a ve a relational document which speci es the links between the tags given in the di erent auxiliary document and possibly the events of the reference axis. These documents are realized with the XML link tags which links the identi ers of the ressources tags with the keys an integer here of the event in relation. The reference axis is not represented explicitly by a document, but is given here implicitly by the list of event identi ers.</p><p>Each auxiliary ressource document supposes that a DTD Document T ype De nition speci es the constraints on the expression of the corresponding annotation ressources. the XML encoding Given the relation model introduced previously and one DTD for each RE, we can specify in a unique way the corresponding XML encoding.</p><p>The table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1</ref> gives an example of a classical annotated corpus and the new encoding documents. Each RE is encoded in an independant XML document: The document corresponding to the RE word of gure 3 can beview as the dictionnary of the corpus, the document morphosyntactic tag as the tag set. An additional XML document, not shown here, gives an explicit labelling for each tag for instance Np stands for plural noun. Each element of these documents are identi ed in order to belinked. Each RR is also de ned in a XML document using XML links as shown table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">2</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">E cient internal representations of the XML documents</head><p>The usual result of a XML parser needs a lot of memory and present generally ine cient access mecanisms for links. Event-based XML parser SAX allows to access to relevant datas without loading the full document, but is slower than a classical parser and has the same drawbacks concerning reversibility o f a c c e s s . Our proposal is to use FSA techniques for the internal representation of the XML document. FSA techniques present time and space optimisations and e cient r e v ersible access. The e ciency of this representation exploit the redundancy of the information. By indentifying and encoding this redundancy with respectively a RROM and a XML document, we can obtain in a straightforward way this e cient i n ternal representation. Each auxiliary ressource document is compiled into an automaton with pre x sharing lexicographic trees. Each XML relational document gives the transitions between the different automata obtained with the auxiliary ressource document. A relational document can be compiled into a transducer which links some auxiliary ressources entries identi ed by their XML id. Edges of this tranducer are labelled with the couple of names in relation see gure 4 in order to allow fully reversible access. The reading of any tag gives in linear time the link to all auxiliary ressources in relation to this tag. Identi ers used in the XML encoding are only used to build this representation.</p><p>In gure 4 the reading of an event key gives the access to all level of annotation which are linked to the corresponding event. Given a word, the access to the following word is just the word associated to the next event k ey. The access to a given word or a given tag results in a list of event keys corresponding to all occurrences of the word or the tag on the reference axis ie in the corpus still in linear time.</p><p>Even in the case of very large corpora, the size of auxiliary ressources automata is limited. On the contrary, the internal representation of the reference axis and of the di erent transitions to words and tags can be very large when there are millions of events. In this case, cache techniques with temporary les may be necessary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">A workbench for visualization and exploitation</head><p>The rst version of a workbench implementing these principles has been developped in the context of a project called CALIN. This graphical workbench is currently specialized for the French Le Monde corpus developped at TA-LaNa University of Paris VII. Still this tool could be easily adapted to other classical tagged corpora or treebanks. The workbench is writen in Java and uses the Sil de XML Parser<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">2</ref> which support XML link and XML path speci cations.</p><p>The workbench allows to visualise the reference corpus, to access to annotated information morphology and syntax simply by clicking on words see gure 5. Three di erent modes allow to access to annotations linked to the word, to the compound or the full sentence containing the selected word. Syntactic annotation can be  edited in a table or with a syntactic dependency tree see gure 6.. The implementation also provides a conversion tool to generate the XML documents from the existing annotated ASCII les as presented table 1. Currently the whole corpus is auto-matically divided into several XML documents which requieres less memory to be loaded by the XML parser than a complete XML document. Existing tools permits the conversion of the corpus in a single level of annotation in the proposed format. We can also project from our XML encoding a particular level of annotation according to an existing standard XML annotation scheme.</p><p>6 Future work Projecting a particular level of annotation of a multi-level annotated corpus in an existing standard format. Moreover we w ant to use the encoding principles proposed here to more complex multimodal annotated corpora resulting from a Wizard of Oz experience combination of speech and gesture interaction. We also plan to study the uniform realization of the RROM model in XML on the basis of the XML schema proposals.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: RROM for morphological lexicon.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Simpli ed RROM for LTAG ressources.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: RROM for multilevel annotated textual corpus.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Internal Finite State Representation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Screen shot of the workbench.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,164.28,454.65,283.41,138.47" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Dependency tree.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Future</head><label></label><figDesc>works on the workbench during next steps of the CALIN project should include: Optimizations for the full Le Monde corpus 1 million of words Search tools on words, tags or tree patterns using FSA based processing. Statistics and frequencies in the corpora. Further research will try to formalize in our model the principle of coding module introduced in the MATE framework Dybkj r et al., 1998. Our goal is then to integrate to the workbench functionalities such a s : Merging several standard one-level annotations of a corpus into our multilevel framework.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Example of a classical textual annotation and XML documents for Ressource Entities.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>XML documents for Ressource Relations.</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>http: www.loria.fr projets XSil de EN sxp</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Lexicalized Tree Adjoining Grammar for English</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anne</forename><surname>Abeill E</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kathleen</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bishop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sharon</forename><surname>Cote</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yves</forename><surname>Schabes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>MS-CIS-90-24</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Departement of Computer and Information Science, University o f P ennsylvania</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A formal framework for linguistic annotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Steven</forename><surname>Bird</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mark</forename><surname>Liberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>MS-CIS-99-01</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>University o f P ennsylvania</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Computer and Information Science</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Structuration d&apos;une grammaire LTAG : application au fran cais et a l&apos;italien</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marie-H</forename><surname>El Ene Candito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University o f P aris 7</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marking-up multiple views on a text: Discourse and reference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dan</forename><surname>Cristea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nancy</forename><surname>Ide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ELREC 98</title>
		<meeting>ELREC 98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The mate markup framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laila</forename><surname>Dybkj R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Niels</forename><surname>Ole Bernsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hans</forename><surname>Dybkj R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Mckelvie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Mengel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
	<note>MATE delivrable D1.2, Odense University</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">David McKelvie, and Andreas Mengel. 1999. The mate workbench</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laila</forename><surname>Dybkj R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Morten</forename><forename type="middle">Baun</forename><surname>Moller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Niels</forename><surname>Ole Bemsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jean</forename><surname>Carletta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amy</forename><surname>Isard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marion</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACL&apos;99 Software Demonstration Program</title>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Maryland</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A structure-sharing parser for lexicalized grammars</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Roger</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Weir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">COLING-ALC, M o n tr eal, Canada. Nancy Ide and Jean V eronis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Kyoto, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1998. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>14th Conference on Computational Linguistics COLING&apos;94</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
