<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">ATILF&apos;s Computerized Linguistic Resources involved in Cooperative Projects</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jean-Marie</forename><surname>Pierrel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
							<email>laurent.romary@loria.fr</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zina</forename><surname>Tucsnak</surname></persName>
							<email>zina.tucsnak@inalf.fr</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">ATILF (Analyse et Traitement Informatique de la Langue Française</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 7118</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">CNRS/Université de Nancy2</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>BP 30687</postBox>
									<postCode>54063</postCode>
									<settlement>Nancy Cedex</settlement>
									<country>France Jean</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">LORIA/INRIA Campus Scientifique</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>BP 239</postBox>
									<postCode>54506</postCode>
									<settlement>Vandoeuvre-les-Nancy Cedex</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">ATILF (Analyse et Traitement Informatique de la Langue Française</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 7118</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">CNRS/Université de Nancy2</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>BP 30687</postBox>
									<postCode>54063</postCode>
									<settlement>Nancy Cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Research Laboratory ATILF (Analyse et Traitement Informatique de la Langue Française</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">ATILF&apos;s Computerized Linguistic Resources involved in Cooperative Projects</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">264227981CF3FEE3904A26C96DBB4212</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>In our Research Laboratory ATILF we started looking for a way to organize and describe the computerized resources already existent. All the ATILF repositories are accessible via the Web at http://www.inalf.fr/atilf for search and retrieval. Now we need to implement a metadata vocabulary and structure to enables others to locate our specific French language resources. The aim of our project is to improve the existent tagging toward an international standard as ISO/TC 37/SC 4 specifies.</p><p>The challenge lies in the unification process of the variability of the existent tagging. In order to overcome all that diversity, our work relies on normalised XML formats. A future perspective: normalised interfaces for representation and access. In this article, we present some of the ATILF's textual resources and their metadata implementation for cooperative project as OLAC and INTERA. All tools and the meta-description files are available over the Internet via an HTTP server.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Metadata initiatives for ATILF's resources</head><p>Each textual database (cf § 4), in standalone, have his own graphical interface and search tool.</p><p>But the amount of effort required by a user to locate our databases, understand how they are organized and perform a query is still very important. By using standard metadata ("data about data") we want to facilitate this process and open our resources to users other than their creators, colleagues and others already familiar   In figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> we present a mapping sample describing FRANTEXT bibliography (cf § 4.1) in OLAC and IMDI metadata.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Implementing metadata on French language resources</head><p>Exploring multiple ATILF resources in correct, effective and efficient use is a challenging task.</p><p>We are using various terminology, notation, organisation of data and search commands. The unified representation of the metadata allows speedy searches, using finally the existing tools.</p><p>The core component of our metadata project is a database server that acts as intermediary between the metadata representation and the virtual harvester. All the computerised resources reside in separate, remote servers. We use XML encoding and TEI specifications.</p><p>The resources presented below are searchable and browsable French repositories across metadata specification, interlinked with existing relevant search tool in order to facilitate users' access .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">First example: FRANTEXT</head><p>Frantext is a corpus of written literary French Atilf's production line </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Second example : TLFi (Trésor de la</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Langue Française Informatisé)</head><p>The TLFi (obvious result of the TLF started in the 60's) can be seen as a lexical database <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Dendien, 1996)</ref>  Semantic and Stylistic studies: If a user chooses to ask for the list of all adjective ending with -esque, present in the TLFi, it is perhaps because he wants to know which ones are pejorative or not…The request can be established, using this kind of criteria. He can also make requests specific to an author of the many examples cited in the TLFi with their reference, and possibly ask which examples from Balzac contain a conjugated form of the verb aimer, not in the source of the example, but in the core of the example. This is only possible because of the hierarchical structure of the textual objects in the article. Frantext can be used by teachers and students in order to detect the nuances of a word, by looking at its environment. It is also possible to concentrate on the evolution of particular semantic fields, on the evolution of a word between its first attestation in the base and the last one, on problems linked to synonymy: are "synonyms" really "synonyms" (for example suspicion and soupcon, or espoir and espérance, etc.), and hence, what is "synonymy"?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Last example: ancient dictionaries and</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Encyclopaedia</head><p>The following resources are all integrated in OLAC archives and in INTERA project. They are searchable and browsable through the search engine Philologic <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Olsen, 1999)</ref>.  Promote development of standards in language resource management.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Encyclopédie ou</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusion</head><p>Frantext, the TLFi as well as all computerized ATILF's resources, do not compose a closed set of textual resources. They can be independently Another objective is to implement several</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>International standards and other Technical</head><p>Reports that cover computer-assisted lexicography and language engineering trough specific annotated information (morphology and syntax).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>with them. The answer to resource discovery is given by various initiatives that are currently developing standards for resource description, including the Dublin Core Metadata initiative, the Open Language Archives Community initiative and the International Standards in Language Engineering metadata initiative. The OLAC linguistics specific metadata set and the harvesting protocol are very suitable to ATILF repositories. Trough a flat structure and a wide coverage of language resource type, the OLACMS facilitate the metadata description. OLAC, the Open Language Archives Community, is an international partnership of institutions and individuals who are creating a worldwide virtual library of language resources by: (i) developing consensus on best current practice for the digital archiving of language resources, and (ii) developing a network of interoperating repositories and services for housing and accessing such resources. ATILF joined OLAC in 2002. The first step was to build a local server http://olac.inalf.fr in order to implement the metadata OAI (Open Archive Protocol) harvesting protocol. Even if the resources keeps the original format, a standard Dublin Core and OLAC metadata description is added in order to have two big archives. The first archive contain the metadata description of the Frantext textual database and the other one all the dictionaries end encyclopedia, especially the French computerized dictionary, TLFi. ATILF archives are harvested and registered for OLAC according OAI (Open Archive Protocol).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure3</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>French</head><label></label><figDesc>Dictionnaire raisonné des sciences, des arts et des métiers, par une Société de Gens de lettres was published under the direction of Diderot, with 17 volumes of text and 11 volumes of plates between 1751 and 1772. Containing 72,000 articles written by more than 140 contributors, the Encyclopédie was a massive reference work for the arts and sciences, as well as a machine de guerre which served to propagate Enlightened ideas. The impact of the Encyclopédie was enormous. Through its attempt to classify learning and to open all domains of human activity to its readers, the Encyclopédie gave expression to many of the most important intellectual and social developments of its time. The current electronic version implements a fast, flexible search engine. It is a cooperative project of ATILF and ARTFL (American and French Research of the French Language). The Encyclopédie (http://encyclopedie.inalf.fr) database contains 20.8 million words, 400000 unique forms, 18000 pages of text, 17 volumes of articles, and 11 volumes of plate legends. One can do: searches for articles or groups of articles (by : article headword, author, category of knowledge, part of speech), full text searches (for : words, phrase, co-occurrences of words, word or phrase frequency per article ) , cross-references from one article to another, links from plate legends to plate images, links to digitized images of each page of text. The resource have a restricted access (an institution can subscribe to a database package: FRANTEXT and Encyclopédie Project). The third edition (1552) of Robert Estienne's Dictionarium latinogallicum marks the culmination of his work on the Latin-French dictionary. Estienne, the father of modern Classical Latin and French lexicography (cf. Starnes 1954), had established for Classical Latin and 16thcentury French a tripartite series of dictionaries: for Latin a monolingual Thesaurus intended for scholars, and two Latin-French dictionaries, one, the Dictionarium latinogallicum, for advanced students, and an abridged version, the Dictionariolum puerorum latinogallicum, for beginners. Jean Nicot's Thresor de la langue françoyse is the key to the development of French lexicography. The sum of four editions of Robert Estienne's bilingual Dictionaire françois-latin, the Threysor assumed, through the contributions of Nicot, the nature of a monolingual French dictionary. Pierre Bayle's Dictionnaire historique et critique stands as the supreme achievement of one of the seventeenth century's most prominent men of letters. The database contains a facsimile version of the 1740 edition. Theses resources are access free at http://dictionnaire.inalf.fr/dictionnaires . Users can handle joint query on all that computerised dictionaries. The Académie française was founded by Cardinal Richelieu in 1635 with the primary goal of creating a French dictionary. A total of eight editions have been published in the years since its foundation, from the first edition in 1694 up until the eighth edition in 1935. The ninth edition is currently in progress. Users can freely search either on the electronic versions of the first (1694), 5th (1798), and 6th (1835) editions or on the 8 th (1932-35) and the 9 th . Defining simple schemas for specific metadata elements and vocabulary.  Develop a complete mapping between IMDI and OLAC metadata standards with respect to ATILF resources and TEI standards.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>consulted and interrogated, and can be a starting point to a number of linguistic projects. The objective of the laboratory ATILF is to let the community know that such resources exist for French Language. These resources have been initiated a long time ago and are today available at ATILF, where work is still in progress. In order not to exclude anyone of the process of distributing these tools, we propose a mutualisation of these resources to the benefit of the entire community. Networks and infrastructure projects as Norma langue (in France), INTERA or OLAC are the best ways to inform a large group of language resource users of the potential of the ATILF resources. The general policy of our laboratory is to welcome and give the research and teaching world the widest access to all our resources.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Conception de systèmes hypermedia à grande échelle pour les sciences humaines ; Présentation de Philologic : le logiciel d&apos; ARTFL, in 67th Congrès de l&apos;ACFAS (Association canadienne française pour l&apos;avancement des sciences)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Andreev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Olsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-05-11">1999. May 11. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Ottawa</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Un serveur de ressources informatisées via le Web</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bernard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bernet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dendien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pierrel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Souvay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tucsnak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Actes de TALN-2001</title>
		<meeting>s de TALN-2001<address><addrLine>Tours</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-07">2001. Juillet 2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="338" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Codage et normalisation de ressources textuelles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bonhomme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000. 2000</date>
			<publisher>Pierrel</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Access to information in a textual database : access functions and optimal indexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dendien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Research in Humanities Computing, Papers from the 1989 ACH-ALLC</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">INTERA (Integrated European language data Repository Area)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dendien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.language-archives.org/Pierrel" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Open language archives community (OLAC). Web site</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Paris</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Editions Hermès</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996. 2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="34" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>J.M.. Ingéniérie des Langues</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Tei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/" />
		<title level="m">Text Encoding Intiative)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Web site</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Annotation automatique de corpus : panorama et état de la technique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Véronis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000. 2000</date>
			<publisher>Pierrel</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
