<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">51DD0BCD142B96D6796933B72BD9009F</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scientific information management</head><p>• Providing the researcher with the means to work • Institutional workspace -The repository as a reporting tool -(cf. HAL: exports for the annual report)</p><p>•</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistics</head><p>-The repository as an indicator of scientific influence -From citation (in publications) to usage (downloads)</p><p>• Deep interoperability -High quality data for high quality services -Exports -imports, etc.</p><p>-Harvesting, indexing: Beyond OAI-PMH -Anticipating the transition from metadata to full-text management Level 3 -bringing intelligence in the repository</p><p>• If only the repository had some knowledge about the data itself -Bringing-in data automatically</p><p>• From publishers to repositories -Extracting information from documents</p><p>• Typing-in information once and for all -Providing specific services for semi-structured datatypes</p><p>• E.g. Synthetic views on a publication</p><p>• Two examples: the PEER project, the Dariah TEI demonstrator</p><p>Intermezzo -the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI)</p><p>The Text Encoding Initiative </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>--•--•</head><label></label><figDesc>Providing access to publications • Subscription policy -Giving him the means to record and disseminate his activity • Research repository • Difficulties -Cope for the high costs of traditional scholarly publishing -Accommodate with the development of new technologies -Getting a comprehensive view on the researcher'Management of the peer-reviewing process • Dissemination -Reaching out libraries, scholars • Long-term availability -Permanent reference and access • Basic terminology -Stage 1: author's draft for review -Stage 2: author's draft after review -Stage 3: publisher's version after copy-editing Publication repositories Intended to deal with the dissemination and long-term availability functions • Open access: a means for an end -Increasing the accessibility of scholarly results -Complementary to the certification process • Components of a publication repository -Technical infrastructure -digital object management -Editorial support -content management, quality assessment (e.g. affiliations) -Political environment -who wants a repository and to which purpose To be or not to be central… • Technical infrastructure (IT) Need not be duplicated -Constant development of new services • Editorial support (Library) Needs to be close to research environments -Needs further functionalities (hidden to researchers) • Political environment (Research management) -Needs to be concerted across institutions -Compromise between institutional visibility and coordination of available means -Research repository policy cannot be disentangled from SI policy (e.g. Springer-MPS) But let's forget about concepts… Why do I use a publication archive? • Record of my production -My publications on HAL • Quick delivery to others -Write, deposit, give away • Because I believe in open access? -Maybe a bad argument • Would I write without the perspective of an "official" publishing? • Would I want to avoid peer-review? -No. Relying on the recognition from my colleagues -Yes. If I would know my results would be used and attributed/recognized -Objective view • Happy to find papers from colleagues on google • Aware that putting my own work is an overhead • Things are made easier thanks to a good infrastructure HAL -a quick overview • Put together in the mid 90's as a mirror to ArXiv -Political independence, difficulty to get additional functionalities -arxiv as a close environment -Initiated by physicists, within CNRS • Wider impact around since mid 2000's -Multidisciplinary: maths, human sciences, computer science -Multi-institutional: INRIA, INSERM, Universities -HAL has become a national publication repository Why do I use HAL(-INRIA)? • Because it's visible -Ranking Web of World Repositories -My colleagues will easily find my publications: Google search [Laurent Romary standards] • Because I feel at home -HAL-INRIA -Within one single instance of HAL: Generic HAL • Because it has a couple of cool features -Online legibility: Romary &amp; Armbruster, 2010 -Facilitated deposit (affiliation): HAL-Deposit -Publication lists: Haltools • Because INRIA has cool librarians… -Completion, correction, interaction, support What do I expect now? • (even) Easier submission -What should I type in information which is already in the document I am depositing? • Better statistics -HAL -Stats -Evolution of access over time -Source of download requests • Better workspace functionality -Creating, managing and disseminating collections -Adding research material (e.g. TEI encoded dictionary samples) Better connection with other publication services -Google scholar, WoZ, Microsoft academic search -Duplicates, missing entries, bad affiliation, no link to HAL… Putting intelligence into the repository I have a dream… Level 1 -getting started quickly • Managing authors -One's own identity -default author, default affiliation(s) -Co-authors -favorite co-authors, favorite co-institutions • Managing institutions -Reliable authority list of institutions and laboratories -Favorite co-institutions • Managing publication loci -Journal list, conferences • Managing publications -Duplicates, corrections, completions Level 2 -the repository as a tool • Researcher workspace -Small scale (cf. dream)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="31,68.39,66.00,591.61,426.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="32,51.00,60.00,618.00,445.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="34,8.00,78.00,703.00,410.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="36,500.50,254.96,219.50,285.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="39,110.52,82.90,481.94,430.63" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Content submission -to repositories &amp; LTP archive</head><note type="other">PEER</note><p>Publishers involved the project The information chaos • ISSN (print)</p><p>What do we have there?</p><p>• A coherent infrastructure to facilitate -The long-term management of scholarly content in research institutions</p><p>• In-depth representation of bibliographical data -Smooth interaction between publishers and research institutions </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Intelligent management of content</head><p>The "TEI repository" Why a "TEI repository"?</p><p>• The continuum of full-text document -Bérardier de Bataut's Essai sur le récit -Online report </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>An opportunity</head><p>• DARIAH -research infrastructure for the humanities</p><p>• Experimenting researchers' environments within DARIAH</p><p>-"Working for the poor": offering a simple workspace for eScholars working on digital documents and collections -Deposit, describe, visualize, publish We can probably try conclude… • Lessons to be learnt for a scientific information policy -No rush, be consequent -Keep all developments within a global strategy -Take benefits from available/demanding communities -be opportunistic -Services, services, services…</p><p>• Mühsam, mühsam ernährt sich das Eichhörnchen</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
