<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3B60ACBFCFE3716C0DE0C7D36DAD40C5</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Country</term>
					<term>Organisation</term>
					<term>Laboratory Repository 1 Author xy Repository 6 PEER Depot PEER Helpdesk Repository 5 Repository 4 Repository 3 Repository 2</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This project is funded under the eContentplus programme 1 , a multiannual Community programme to make digital content in Europe more accessible, usable and exploitable.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tables, Figures &amp; Appendices</head><p>Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1:</ref>    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The Draft report on the provision of usage data 1 and manuscript deposit procedures for publishers and repository managers, deliverable 2.1, set out to establish a workflow for depositing stage-2 outputs in and harvesting log files from repositories to enable the research envisaged in the PEER project. As that report preceded the tendering process whereby the respective research teams were selected, a number of issues were flagged for attention, particularly of the Usage research team, in WP5 and have since been referred for consultation.</p><p>A significant outcome of the previous draft report was the recommendation to establish the PEER Depot as a closed intermediary repository, to receive publisher deposit in the form of both 50% of the full-text outputs, as well as 100% of the metadata outputs; and to serve as a base line control for the research process. The PEER Depot has since been established, and has come to play a significant role in the workflow developed. While the draft report set out a preliminary deposit workflow from publishers to repositories, the central role of the PEER Depot has since influenced further developments in the provision of usage data and manuscript deposit procedures for both publishers and authors. This report is the result of an ongoing negotiation between stakeholder groups comprising publishers and the library/repository community to establish best practice in deposit procedures that are least disruptive of existing publication workflows, while minimizing additional effort in repository ingest activities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Methodology</head><p>Interaction between stakeholder groups has been conducted in a series of face-to-face meetings, in which a progressively increasing number of participants from both publisher and repository communities chose to participate by teleconference. Not only does this signify more efficient communication, it also indicates a growing sense of trust amongst and between stakeholder groups, borne from a common understanding of project objectives, and a pragmatic understanding of the complexity of everyday work processes encountered by both parties.</p><p>The draft recommendations of D2.1 were tested in the course of these discussions. Queries that have arisen in areas of concern are indicated and some alterations to the workflow are formulated in this final report.</p><p>Following the establishment of the PEER Depot, a pilot phase for publisher deposit to the PEER Depot was conducted in M10+11, with satisfactory results. A pilot phase for deposit from the PEER Depot to the repositories and the upload of log files was conducted in M12. Theoretically, the trial workflow has now moved into production, pending the validation of individual publisher deposits following the resolution of specific problems encountered during the pilot phase.</p><p>Two major accomplishments of the combined effort of WP2/3 have been the establishment of a responsible embargo management procedure, now conducted centrally at the PEER Depot for both publisher and author deposit; and an author deposit workflow, developed in progressive scenario testing process.</p><p>Standardised workflow set out in this final report enables a core group of interoperable European repositories, capable in theory of accepting material deposited from third party publishers and authors, beyond the project duration.</p><note type="other">1</note><p>The DoW originally names this task "Harvesting of log files". Since the recommended practice was altered, it is preferred in this document to call it "provision of usage data".</p><p>A further significant achievement of the joint effort of WP2/3 has been formalisation of the transfer from the PEER Depot to all partner repositories in a single simultaneous process, using the SWORD protocol. Not only is this a new application in the transfer of both metadata and full-text articles, it represents a limited percentage of unknown errors in the transfer process. The intention is to have all PEER content mirrored in all participating repositories, to achieve a critical mass, except where precluded for technical reasons. The application of the SWORD Protocol represents best effort at achieving maximum content.</p><p>In addition, a UK-based repository has been invited to join the task force to better reflect usage of predominantly English language content expected. Preliminary enquiries, however, indicate a reluctance to participate in the project, ostensibly on the basis of heavy workloads of repository managers, who furthermore do not benefit financially from the project.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Interaction between stakeholder groups</head><p>Partners and stakeholders across Europe hosted meetings of work package 2/3: STM, London (M2) &amp; (M4); Elsevier, Amsterdam (M6); INRIA, Paris (M8); the SURF Foundation, Utrecht (M10) and the Max Planck Digital Library, Munich (M13).</p><p>This interaction has been supported by the constructive mediation of the Project Manager, who participates in WP2/3 listserv discussions as a representative of the publisher stakeholder group. Similarly, the interaction with the research teams is mediated by WP1, and the research manager is also included in WP2/3 listserv discussions. A recent further development of this interaction has been the establishment of a repository managers' listserv, to include the research manager and a representative of the Usage research team.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Relationship between work packages and dependencies</head><p>Concern was expressed in the draft report at the disjuncture of work schedules in related work packages, so that decisions taken on a technical level in WP2 regarding the specification of log files, for example, might later impact on the suitability of data provided to the Usage research team in WP 5. With the subsequent appointment of the CIBER group from University College London (UCL), selected by tender to conduct the usage research, it has become possible to communicate relevant issues via WP 1, Manage Research Process.</p><p>The benefit of the dependency acknowledged between WP 2/3 and WP 4/5 has been demonstrated in the recommendation of WP 5 to include a UK repository. Since much of the content is in the English language, usage rates will be much improved by increasing the geographic coverage accordingly.</p><p>An attempt has been made to improve the mediated communication between related work packages firstly by means of a designated repository representative, and subsequently by means of a shared listserv of all relevant parties.</p><p>The relationship between work packages remains a high priority to ensure that identified dependencies are addressed and miscommunication remains limited. For example it is emerged after much uncertainty that no common mechanism devised for repositories in the preparation of usage log files can be applied to all publishers. Publishers are individually negotiating with CIBER regarding their log file provision, since they do not have a uniform set-up internally. Therefore, this report treats only publisher deposit to repositories, and the usage data subsequently gathered in repositories.</p><p>1 Content deposits from publishers to repositories</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Convention</head><p>In the context of the PEER project, content refers to stage-2 manuscripts and is understood as peer-reviewed article manuscripts with corrections as accepted for publication, but prior to editing and formatting for publication.</p><p>A trial/pilot phase for publisher deposit to the PEER Depot was carried out in M10+11 the results of which were satisfactory. Participating repositories are now ready to receive stage-2 research outputs from publishers via the PEER Depot, following the expiration of an agreed embargo period.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Established workflows</head><p>In an ideal world, publishers could directly deposit their content to repositories. But considering the different technologies provided by repositories and the disparity of technologies implemented by publishers, it appeared that a centralised point of collection, known as the PEER Depot, would be best suited to gather content from publishers, before processing and final deposit to repositories and to KB's long-term preservation (LTP) depot on behalf of the publishers. The e-Depot at the Koninklijke Bibliotheek in The Netherlands was invited to act as a long-term preservation archive, without participation in the usage measurement. The e-Depot acts in similar role to the publishing industry, and is therefore well positioned to enable the development of workflow, guidelines and standards that will secure the longterm preservation of the project's content. The PEER Depot is hosted at INRIA with the responsibility for facilitating publisher deposit and dissemination to repositories and to the LTP Depot. The content is also retained in the PEER Depot, in case of processing or delivery errors. The PEER Depot receives 100% metadata and 50% full-texts of the publishers' content. Some publishers only participate in the author deposit aspect, thus providing only metadata. The metadata is held extant to provide a control mechanism for the comparative research processes of measuring the balance of the 50% deposit by means of author deposit. This depot shall not be another repository, but a dark archive (not accessible, nor searchable).</p><p>The PEER workflow (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1</ref>) shows the expected parallel paths of publisher deposit and author deposit. • Preferably with an md5 checksum 2</p><p>• The metadata file contained in the ZIP file should include the name of the full-text file, or the ZIP package must contain only one obvious full-text file.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Publishers provide in advance indication of:</head><p>• How to extract PEER-related metadata from the metadata file</p><p>• How/where to find the full-text in the zip file</p><p>• The deposit option chosen regarding metadata (see 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.2)</head><p>Publishers also provide in advance a list of journals contributed to PEER, with their assigned destination, i.e. publisher or author pathway (see Appendix A: Participating journals).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1</head><p>The PublisherArticleId may not be the same article-id as in the metadata, but it must be some kind of unique alphanumerical identifier. 'yymmddhhmmss' is the date in the form year in two digits, month, day, hour, minutes, seconds. 2</p><p>Each ZIP file should be delivered along with its checksum file. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3.1">Full-text format</head><p>For the sake of long-term preservation, the preferred file format of full-texts is PDF/A-1 <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>. Almost all publishers agreed to provide PDF (not PDF/A), which is also acceptable for the purposes of the PEER project. Publishers participating in the author deposit pathway do not provide the full-text in any format. Conversion of source files to PDF is not yet supported by the PEER Depot. The PDF file must include all figures. Provision of supplementary data is not needed since the PEER Depot does not forward them to repositories. Files indicating failed PDF conversion prior to transfer are excluded. The first provided version is authoritative over eventual following versions.</p><p>In order to identify articles, the full-text file received by the PEER Depot are renamed as follows: "PEER_stage2_[urlencoded-DOI].pdf" before submission by the PEER Depot to repositories and the LTP Depot.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3.2">Metadata</head><p>All publishers agreed to provide metadata in an XML format. Because every publisher uses a different DTD standard, it is decided that the PEER Depot would convert all publishers' XML into the TEI DTD standard. The TEI is a widely-used standard for encoding text materials in XML (including metadata). INRIA is in position to provide a 99,9% conversion transformation mechanism from any DTD to TEI.</p><p>Since exports to the PEER Depot might occur in different systems at different stages in the publication workflow, publishers indicated difficulties providing coherent stage-2 metadata.</p><p>In some cases, critical metadata elements, such as embargo dates and persistent identifiers, are either added or first allocated at stage-3 in the publication workflow. To limit disruption of production workflows, it was agreed that the PEER Depot would support three options for gathering metadata. A submission is considered complete when all required metadata are provided.</p><p>• Option 1: All required metadata are submitted at stage-2 deposit.</p><p>• Option 2: Only a subset of metadata is provided during the first deposit including a publisher-article-id; the rest is provided in a second deposit during the embargo period including a publisher-article-id 1 . • Option 3: All the metadata updated by the publisher at stage-3 is submitted again, in replacement of the stage-2 deposit (except the document, which remains stage-2).</p><p>In option 2, for the second pass only, publishers can also provide the complementary metadata in the following forms: While the PEER project recommends the submission of as much metadata as possible, the minimum requirements are marked (*) as set out below. Since some articles may appear online only, or are published online before distribution of the paper edition, it was decided that the PEER Depot would not wait for missing metadata that should be provided by CrossRef (mainly volume, issue, pages), and transmit articles as soon as possible. In this respect, the volume, issue, pages metadata can be considered as recommended, but not mandatory.</p><p>Finally, in the case of backfiles comprising previous articles, already set aside by publishers for the PEER project, and which might be delivered with only a DOI, but no further metadata, further investigation is required to source metadata from known public sources e.g. Public Library of Science (PLoS) or PubMedCentral. Each publisher will be approached individually to check whether backfiles can be provided in a format similar to current articles. In this case, ingestion to the PEER Depot and transfer to repositories can occur immediately, to facilitate the research process.</p><p>A database is used to store the metadata in the PEER Depot and to track events related to submission procedures (e.g. incoming and outgoing timestamps). This information can be made available to the PEER research teams, either through replication, or frequent exports.</p><p>A complete list of articles processed in PEER is thus provided for comparative research between publisher deposit and author deposit procedures. The database also enables monitoring of the activity of the PEER Depot.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3.3">Embargo period</head><p>The period of embargo determines the date of distribution from the PEER Depot to participating repositories and to the LTP Depot. The duration of the embargo period differs from publisher to publisher and from journal to journal and also applies to author submission. These dates result in an agreed generic formula:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PublicationDate + EmbargoPeriod = Distribution Date</head><p>The publication date is provided in the minimum metadata set, defined either at stage-2 or stage-3 deposit. The embargo period, if not otherwise defined, defaults to that provided in the PEER Journal tables 1 .</p><p>The embargo period on publisher contributed content is handled by the PEER Depot. For authors' content provided via the central deposit interface, the embargo period will also be handled by the PEER Depot (see Ch. 2.3.5). For publisher as well as author deposit the embargo period is applied according to the metadata provided in "date of publication" (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> above). As soon as the embargo period expires and the metadata file is complete, the content is ready to be transferred to and processed by the repositories and the LTP Depot.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3.4">Filtering</head><p>Two levels of filtering are envisaged as functions of the PEER Depot. Firstly, of journal titles by publishers for distribution to repositories and the LTP Depot, and secondly, of articles submitted by European authors. The PEER Depot receives 100% metadata and 50% publishers provided full-texts. All selected content -that is 50% of metadata and the corresponding full-texts -is disseminated to participating repositories and the LTP Depot.</p><p>The selection of publisher-deposited full-text is conducted at the journal title level, not manuscript level. The choice of eligible journal titles is defined by the publisher community, with due cognisance of research requirements, viz. behavioural response of specific subject disciplines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>See Appendix A: Participating journals</head><p>In addition, the filtering by type of non-research papers (i.e. letters to the editor) may be operated by the PEER Depot, if the Type metadata is provided.</p><p>1 See Appendix A &amp; the project website http://www.peerproject.eu/about/participating-journals/</p><p>The project design further requires that only articles of European authors should be included in the study. Since publishers do not generally filter content in this manner, it was decided that the location of the corresponding author would be used to identify European content. The automated selection takes place at the PEER Depot, filtered against the coverage metadata element containing the geographical location of the corresponding author (by country). The contribution of additional European authors is regrettably lost to the research process.</p><p>An inevitable outcome of the project design, resulting from the filtering process is a limited research sample. While 50% full-texts of the publishers' content is disseminated to repositories and the LTP Depot, in fact, only that portion represented by the European corresponding author within that 50% are effectively disseminated. The effective percentage of disseminated content will therefore be lower than 50%. This issue is noted for further consideration, and possible adjustment of content quotas to ensure a valid research procedure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4">Deposit procedures from the PEER Depot to repositories</head><p>A wide range of content formats submitted by publishers are normalised by the PEER Depot for transfer to participating repositories. Minimal metadata requirements for participating repositories are set out in the DRIVER Guidelines. 1  • Participating repositories opt to set up a dedicated repository exclusively for receipt of PEER content; or to add content to an existing repository. • Additional effort in the ingest of PEER content is limited to the implementation of the SWORD interface using the SWORD protocol (see Appendix C: The SWORD protocol).</p><p>The LTP Depot is not SWORD compliant, so for transferring the content from the PEER Depot to the LTP Depot, the FTP protocol or a FTP/s client will be used.</p><p>The deposit procedure uses a unified ingestion service, based on accepted international standards. These standards include PDF/A (ISO 19005-1:2005); TEI metadata format for descriptive metadata; ZIP for creating a package containing the PEER content; and the Atom Publishing Protocol (RFC 5023) using the SWORD specification as a transport protocol transferring the package to the repository. The benefit achieved is a core group of interoperable European repositories, capable in theory of accepting material deposited directly by third party publishers and authors beyond the project duration.</p><p>The deposit procedure is an automated process whereby the publications released from embargo are transferred from the PEER Depot to all partner repositories in a single simultaneous SWORD transfer. The intention is to have all PEER content mirrored in all participating repositories, to achieve a critical mass, except where precluded for technical reasons. When the publications in the repository are accepted and stored, an automated confirmation message is sent back to the PEER Depot with the online link to the publication. These locations can be used to notify the author about the links where he or she can find the stage-2 material. 2   The deposit procedure from the PEER Depot to the repositories is illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">2</ref> below.  The transfer of 50% full-text content and the author submitted files from the PEER Depot is conducted as follows:</p><p>• On a daily basis, as articles are normalised continuously</p><p>• Submission by FTP/S 1 transmission 2 or SWORD protocol</p><p>• As ZIP files, one per article 3</p><p>• The ZIP package contains only one pdf data file and one metadata file</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">• File naming convention as o [PEER_stage2_[urlencoded-DOI].pdf] o [PEER_stage2_[urlencoded-DOI].xml] o [PEER_stage2_[urlencoded-DOI].zip]</formula><p>in order to identify PEER articles in repository log files, slashes in the DOI format are encoded as "_slsh_". • Submission accompanied by an md5 checksum 4   • In the case of FTP/S, an acknowledgement file named ack_PEER_stage2_[urlencoded-DOI].txt comprising only the repository internal identifier, which is the URL pointing to the created resource, will be returned in successful ingestion (void if unsuccessful).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4.1.1">Normalisation and Packaging</head><p>The metadata and the full-text files submitted by publisher deposit and that submitted by author deposit are normalised, since repositories expect a unified standard of the material. The different variations of the delivered metadata formats (mostly NLM format in different versions) are converted to the TEI metadata format. The full-text files are delivered by the publishers in PDF or PDF/A format. Both files are packaged in a ZIP compliant file.</p><p>The filename of these files are renamed to contain the DOI and follows the following syntax: "PEER_stage2_ [urlencoded-DOI].</p><p>[ext]" for all files accounts where [ext] has to be replaced with respectively "xml" (TEI metadata), "pdf" (full-text) and "zip" (package). For all files accounts where [urlencoded-DOI] has to be replaced with the DOI string that accompanies the publication, and in some cases, not encouraged, all slashes in the DOI string may be replaced with the following string: "_slsh_" (for security reasons concerning the web server, 1 FTP/SSL is a secure way to transfer files. The opensource command line tool cURL can be used as a FTPS client.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2</head><p>FTP pull has two advantages: repositories do not have to install a FTP-server; and they have confirmation of successful ingest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3</head><p>A single zip-file is essential to enable the PEER Depot to identify clearly each article, i.e. the material is not spread into many files that need to be gathered together. <ref type="bibr">4</ref> Each ZIP file is delivered along with its checksum file.</p><p>when changing webserver configuration is not allowed). Then the filename is URL-encoded (RFC 3986), to avoid unusual behaviour upon unrecognised characters.</p><p>Examples using the DOI "10.2345/38884.299_299" creates the following filenames:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">• PEER_stage2_10.2345_slsh_38884.299_299.xml • PEER_stage2_10.2345_slsh_38884.299_299.pdf • PEER_stage2_10.2345_slsh_38884.299_299.zip</formula><p>The application profile of the TEI metadata tells the repository manager how to interpret the metadata fields in the PEER context. Both the TEI metadata DTD (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>) and the way of packaging provide the repository a standard what to expect when they receive a PEER package. This standard is put under a unique namespace that can be used when sending the package using SWORD-APP. The name space goes by the URI: http://purl.org/net/sword-types/tei/peer/ .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Agreements and conventions</head><p>• Package contains one metadata file and one PDF file   • Basic authentication is used</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">•</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4.1.3">SWORD: Notifying successful transfer with file location</head><p>When the SWORD interface has received the package it unpacks the ZIP-file and stores the PDF and Metadata into the repository. When this is done the SWORD interface immediately notifies the PEER Depot about the successful operation with the URL of the PDF located at the repository.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Agreements and conventions</head><p>• HTTP-header response element "Location" MUST contain the URI of the Media Link Entry, as defined in ATOMPUB. • The Media Link Entry URI MUST dereference.</p><p>• The Media Link Entry URI MUST contain an &lt;atom:content&gt; element with a "src" attribute containing a URI. • The Media Link Entry URI MUST contain the location of at least the PDF file in the repository. • The Media Link Entry MAY occur more than once containing other relevant locations to the publication at the repository. • The Media Link Entry URI MUST NOT contain internal server paths.</p><p>• &lt;atom:id&gt; MUST contain an IRI (Internationalised Resource Identifier, RFC 3987), allowing Unicode, or an URI (which is a subset of an IRI) • &lt;atom:author&gt; MUST contain the user sending the package, it MUST NOT contain the author of the publication. • Additional mandatory fields are &lt;atom:title&gt; and &lt;atom:summary&gt;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4.1.4">SWORD: Notifying unsuccessful transfer of the file</head><p>In the case of ingestion things might go wrong in three places:</p><p>1) At the HTTP protocol level 2) At the SWORD interface level 3) At the repository upon ingestion Level 1 and 2 describe errors that happen on the surface, on the "communication" level. Level 3 describes an error that occurs below the surface, inside the repository.</p><p>Providing error handling at the HTTP level (1) is considered standardised in all repositories, this MUST be used, and will not be mentioned here further. Providing error handling at the SWORD interface level (2) described in the SWORD protocol v1.3 SHOULD be used, and will not be explained here, but we will refer to the SWORD v1.3 specifications. Error handling at the repository level (3) SHOULD also be used and will be explained below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ingestion Error feedback</head><p>When a file has been successfully transferred to the repository, the case might be that the repository cannot ingest the received file. The most appropriate response might be that there is something wrong with the ingestion and not with the transmission.</p><p>To provide the PEER Depot with a clue about that the file is not processed in the repository the following error handling information SHOULD be used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Error URI Usage notes</head><p>http://peerproject.eu/sword/error/ErrorOnIngest The server MUST also return a HTTP status code, which describes the situation most likely.</p><p>This introduces a new namespace "http://peerproject.eu/sword/error" and an error type "ErrorOnIngest", which means the document couldn't be stored in the repository because of an error like • the repository is down (status code 503)</p><p>• the repository takes too long to answer the request</p><p>• the repository requires authentication, the SWORD interface cannot fulfil</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SWORD Error feedback</head><p>The following error handling procedures are written in the SWORD protocol v1.  Due to rapid implementation, it has been decided 1 not to put effort in the error handling procedures. The first priority is to get SWORD working and rely on the standard HTTP error messages to identify problems.</p><p>However, it is recommended that the SWORD and Ingestion error handling is enabled to provide finer granular feedback. This information is useful for better analysis when a problem occurs, that might lead to a quicker solution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4.2">Metadata</head><p>Publisher profiles indicate a wide range of metadata schema deployed. Derived from the DRIVER Guidelines 2 , the minimum required set of metadata elements common to all publisher submissions, will be transferred to repositories:</p><p>• Mandatory elements : Title, Creator, Date, Type and Identifier</p><p>• Additional recommended elements as available</p><p>• PEER Depot transforms received metadata to TEI</p><p>• PEER Depot exports only TEI metadata files, as per repository preference</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4.3">Embargo period</head><p>The embargo period differs according to each journal.</p><p>• Publication date plus embargo period determines the date of distribution from the PEER Depot to participating repositories PublicationDate + EmbargoPeriod = Distribution Date o Where "publication date" is the date of publication of the stage-3 publication, it can be found in the metadata provided by the publisher.</p><p>o "Embargo period" is the period of time an article is not allowed to be released determined by the name of the Journal that can be found in the table of Journals participating the PEER project (see Appendix A: Participating Journals)</p><p>o "Distribution date" is the date when the PEER Depot is allowed to transfer the article to the repositories (after the expiration of the embargo period). • After author deposit, and if an e-mail address is provided, authors will receive a confirmation message that indicates notification of availability in the participating repositories following expiration of the embargo period. The confirmation message relies on the previous transfer of relevant metadata from publishers. • Where possible, authors are then notified accordingly, with the links of the repository pages where they can find their deposited material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1.5</head><p>Deposit procedures from the PEER Depot to LTP Depot</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.5.1">Introduction</head><p>The e-Depot of the National Library of The Netherlands (KB) aims to ensure perpetual access to the published records of the arts, humanities and social sciences, science, technology and medicine, and the digital cultural heritage. The KB assures publishers, libraries and end users 1 See minutes of PEER WP 2/3 meeting, 3 rd September 2009, MPDL, Munich. 2 DRIVER Guidelines: http://www.driver-repository.eu/DRIVER-Guidelines.html that the information preserved in the archive will outlast the transience of digital information carriers and formats. The role of the KB in the PEER project is to act as the long-term preservation (LTP) archive. The e-Depot is not an additional PEER repository, but in fulfilment of the curatorial responsibility of the library and repository community, will serve as longterm preservation depot in which the data objects and the accompanying metadata are kept safe beyond the duration of the project. The KB provides access to the content, based on the available access information in the metadata of the stage-2 manuscripts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.5.2">Content</head><p>The LTP Depot only receives and archives the final version of the content (PDF+ accompanying XML in one zip file) as delivered to the PEER Depot. The KB does not receive authors' content directly from the author, but (after a possible embargo period) via the PEER Depot with the authors' PDF incl. the accompanying complete (stage-3) XML metadata from the publishers. As the LTP Depot preserves content objects, only those records from the PEER Depot that contain an object and accompanying metadata will be transferred to and archived in the LTP Depot. This means that metadata only records are not transferred from the PEER Depot to the LTP Depot.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.5.3">Workflow for Transfer to LTP Depot</head><p>The function of the LTP Depot is to preserve stage-2 manuscripts as deposited in the PEER Depot. Consequently, the LTP Depot has a different role and place within the PEER workflow functioning as an archive in which data objects and the accompanying metadata are kept safe. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1</ref> shows the place and role of the LTP Depot in relation to the PEER Depot and the PEER repositories.</p><p>As described in the workflow, stage-2 manuscripts are fetched from the PEER Depot by FTP/S. Before transfer takes place, the content of each zip file is converted to its final stage for archiving into the LTP Depot. Each zip file contains:</p><p>• A main file in full-text PDF format</p><p>• The complete accompanying metadata file</p><p>In processing the content, bibliographic metadata described according to the PEER/TEI DTD is converted to KB's DTD, whereas the original metadata delivered by the PEER Depot is stored with the content and converted metadata. Processing of the packages is based on the OAIS reference model 1 .</p><p>The LTP Depot is investigating the possibility of responding an acknowledgement file named "ack_PEER_stage2_[urlencoded-DOI].txt" to the PEER Depot upon successful preprocess on its side. The acknowledgement file should comprise only the repository internal identifier (which may be a URL). Upon unsuccessful pre-processing, the acknowledgement file should be empty, and the rejection would be handled by the involved teams.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.5.4">Metadata</head><p>Within the PEER project standardised metadata is applied according to the metadata requirements set out in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>. Publishers deliver the stage-2 manuscripts including metadata to the PEER Depot, and where possible, further recommended and optional elements are included. The PEER Depot converts the bibliographic metadata into the PEER/TEI DTD, which once transferred -as stage-3 i.e. most complete metadata -to the repositories and the LTP Depot is mapped according to local usage. The Dublin Core Metadata Element Set is commonly applied. Both the PEER Depot and the KB process 1 http://public.ccsds.org/publications/archive/650x0b1.pdf bibliographic metadata according to the PEER /TEI DTD -stored in XML format -into their systems, together with the stage-2 manuscript. This bibliographic metadata may be converted to local workflows, for providing access through the local catalogue for example.</p><p>Further investigation is required of the possible future inclusion of an International Standard Name Identifier (ISNI) <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref> and ultimately, a Digital Author Identification (DAI), <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref> as these standards become more widely accepted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.5.5">Digital Preservation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PDF Guidelines</head><p>The article itself is required in a PDF-format. The KB maintains PDF guidelines which are mainly about the following subjects: Accessibility and structure, Fonts, Compression, Images, Executable actions and Colour. The KB is able to archive all PDF versions. For preservation purposes, PDF/A is the most suitable version. The main reason for this preference is that PDF files are portable across systems and platforms without changing the content or authenticity of the document now and in the future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>File information</head><p>For every file, main file and supplements, the KB requires the file name of a zip file, the file name of a main file, the file format and the file version. Regarding the file format the KB advises to handle PUID (Persistent Unique Identifier) as a standard. File information can be added in the metadata and is important for migrating files in the future, which might otherwise become unreadable. To ensure long-term preservation, it could happen that specific files need to be migrated to another (readable) file format.</p><p>The  There are no strict boundaries between the different categories of metadata, some elements can also be sub-types of other elements and there is also a lot of overlap between the different categories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Content deposits from authors to repositories</head><p>The development of an appropriate workflow for author deposits has proved to be most challenging, as the author response is unpredictable. This chapter sets out a process of author deposit that, as far as possible, does not interfere in established practice. Authors are therefore encouraged to follow their established practice of deposit in an institutional or subject-specific repository. Failing such practice, central deposit in the PEER Depot for distribution to designated repositories is recommended. It is highly unlikely that authors would be willing to deposit twice, nor does the project wish to impose additional work on those authors willing to participate. On the other hand, a direct author deposit procedure parallel to that of publisher deposit is not possible, without undue intervention in scholarly practice. Instead, authors eligible for participating in the PEER project are notified via the publisher and invited to respond.</p><p>There is currently no effective mechanism in place to ensure significant author participation, and without it, the value of the research might be questionable. The author deposit workflow is acknowledged as no more than an effort to keep track of authors self-archiving to PEER repositories and other repositories. However, it is precisely this lack of a controlled response to the author deposit procedures that will inform the behaviour and usage research investigations in Work Packages 4 &amp; 5 respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Options for authors</head><p>The author deposit procedure is envisaged in alignment with the normal points of contact between publishers and authors, as follows:</p><p>• Authors submitting manuscripts to eligible journals will be informed by the publisher about PEER and its objectives. • At the point of acceptance, the author will be invited to participate, and to visit the PEER Helpdesk for further details of the project. The request for deposition will include a request to inform the project, should the author intend to deposit the manuscript in a repository of choice, other than in PEER (see Ch. 4.2.4.3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Communication with authors</head><p>For reasons of data privacy, the participating publishers are not able to make the contact details of eligible authors available, and no direct communication is envisaged. Publishers are therefore provided with generic texts to communicate sufficient and consistent information to authors. At the point of acceptance of their manuscripts by their publishers, the authors will receive an invitation to deposit their manuscript within the framwork of the PEER project:</p><p>This journal is participating in the PEER project &lt;http://www.peerproject.eu/&gt;, which aims to monitor the effects of systematic self-archiving (author deposit in repositories) over time. PEER is supported by the EC eContentplus programme &lt;http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/activities/econtentplus/index_en.htm&gt;.</p><p>As your manuscript has been accepted for publication by [Journal name], you may be eligible to participate in the PEER project. If you are based in the European Union, you are hereby invited to deposit your accepted manuscript in one of the participating PEER repositories. You may also choose to deposit in a non-PEER, institutional or subject repository in addition to, or as an alternative to deposit in a PEER designated repository. If depositing your accepted manuscript in a non-PEER repository, please set an embargo period of X months from the date of publication of the journal article for the public release of your accepted manuscript. For further information on PEER deposit, non-PEER deposit and embargo periods please visit the PEER Helpdesk: http://peer.mpdl.mpg.de/helpdesk.</p><p>Due to data protection issues, the project is not allowed to use author e-mail addresses for authentication.</p><p>Possible alternatives to improve the author deposit -given that the anticipated low deposit rate threatens the validity of the project -are the registration at a central point and perhaps even a centralised deposit. The advantage of the latter is seen additionally in the possibility to enable any PEER author to deposit to each designated PEER repository, indirectly, through the PEER Depot. For this purpose, the SWORD protocol, originally applied to the transfer of publisher data from the PEER Depot to the participating repositories would also serve as the mechanism to facilitate author deposits to repositories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1">Remote author authentication</head><p>The following alternative strategy for author authentication has been devised:</p><p>• Authentication at the PEER repository of choice, possibly by a single (PEER-guest) account. This account could then be used to disambiguate between the standard and the PEER related repository content. • Centralised authentication conducted at the PEER Depot or the PEER Helpdesk, either by the author requesting an account (self-registration), by providing his/her e-mail address or as anonymous deposit (no authentication at all) -but with a spam-preventing functionality such as reCAPTCHA 1 .</p><p>The recommendation for centralised authentication for remote author deposits found project support, though members of this work package are aware that this procedure requires extra effort to develop and integrate such functionality as a new application in the workflow.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2">Embargo management by repositories</head><p>The embargo period differs for each journal. A list of journal titles and the corresponding embargo period was provided by the participating publishers and is publicly available at the PEER website 2 . It has been acknowledged that repository management of the embargo period requires considerable and repeated effort. Therefore it was decided to manage the embargo of author deposits centrally at the PEER Depot prior to repository transfer in a manner similar to that for publisher deposit:</p><p>• Publication date extended for the duration of the embargo period determines the date of distribution of an article from the PEER Depot to participating repositories. • PEER Depot holds any content previously received via author deposit until matching metadata are received from the publishers. • Matching of publisher deposited metadata with the metadata received from author deposits determines the release of the deposits to participating repositories after the expiration of the embargo period.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3">Automated metadata matching process (duplicate author deposits)</head><p>To ensure the correct handling of the respective embargo period of an article, it was regarded necessary to conduct an automated process to match the author deposit with the corresponding metadata provided by the publisher at the repositories.</p><p>In the workflow originally envisioned, the PEER Depot would have transferred the metadata corresponding to an author submitted article only after the expiration of the embargo period signalling to the repositories the release of the article. The metadata provided by the author 1 http://recaptcha.net/ 2 http://www.peerproject.eu/about/participating-journals/ would then have been overwritten with the publisher's version, since this is expected to be of a higher standard.</p><p>Repositories would have most likely received the full-texts from author self-archiving first, and thereafter the corresponding metadata from the PEER Depot (after expiration of embargo period). The identification would have taken place by matching author name and article title. Solely for the purpose of matching metadata and as an exception, taking the data protection issues into account, the use of author e-mail addresses was recommended as a means to match metadata and article. The DOI would not have been suitable as identification element, since the authors do not know the DOI at the time of deposit.</p><p>This procedure may still have resulted in some elements of manual checking e.g. author names written with special characters or variations of names (abbreviations, academic titles…). 1   However, as both publisher deposits and author deposits are conducted via the PEER Depot, the process of matching of metadata has been natively moved to the PEER Depot.</p><p>Authors provide the stage-2 manuscript metadata, full-text, and optionally corresponding author's e-mail, when making their deposit. This is the basis to match the author provided metadata with the metadata received from the publishers. Once metadata are matched and the embargo period has expired, the PEER Depot proceeds with the deposit of the stage-2 manuscript to the participating repositories. Thus an additional effort to match or overwrite author deposited metadata with the publisher deposits for repositories is avoided and the process is simplified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.4">Author deposit to a participating PEER Repository</head><p>In a process of consultation between members of the work packages 2 and 3, a series of author deposit workflow scenarios were developed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>See Appendix E: Alternate author deposit workflow scenarios</head><p>The guiding principle throughout remains the freedom of authors to choose to deposit their data to an alternative repository of their choice, in accordance with already established practice, and to inform PEER of this deposit. This functionality is enabled by the PEER Helpdesk.</p><p>Eligible (EU) authors who receive an invitation from the publisher to deposit their accepted manuscript to PEER are directed to the PEER Helpdesk, where they are offered two options:</p><p>1. Authors have the option to deposit their accepted manuscripts directly. Here they have the opportunity to enter their metadata and upload their manuscripts.</p><p>2. Authors may choose to deposit in their institutional repository, a subject-based repository or on their personal website. Authors who choose to do so are kindly requested to notify the project by inserting the URL of the article in the repository of choice (see Ch. 2.3.5 and 4.2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.3).</head><p>There is no authentication mechanism in place; instead, a reCAPTCHA 2 is used to prevent automated deposits and spamming. See The chosen method of author deposit is regarded as a satisfying solution for both the project and the authors, since it limits the author's effort: By making one deposit the manuscript will be available in all participating repositories. The PEER author deposit workflow is described in Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> below 1 .</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>: PEER author deposit workflow</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.5">Author deposit to a non-PEER repository</head><p>When invited to deposit data to PEER, authors are given an additional option to inform PEER on alternative deposit, in case they have deposited their stage-2 manuscripts in a non-PEER repository.</p><p>The PEER Helpdesk directs authors for this purpose to a form where they can provide information on the URL of the item/repository where they have deposited their data, their name and optionally, an e-mail address for further contact by PEER behavioural research team.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.6">Monitoring author response</head><p>Deposit will be monitored by the behavioural research undertaken in WP4, with the appointed team being the Department of Information Science and LISU at Loughborough University, UK, and measured against the 100% metadata control managed by the PEER Depot.</p><p>The project is aware of the fact that it is not possible to predict the behaviour of authors invited to deposit. It is noted that limited contact with authors, and hence minimal support for author deposit could affect the size of the research sample available in WP4. An option of supplementary harvesting by the PEER Depot, as a means of redress, requires further investigation.</p><p>3 Provision 1 of usage data</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Introduction</head><p>This chapter defines how repositories should make available usage data to enable research on usage statistics, i.e. usage levels and patterns. 2 According to decisions taken in the PEER project, a very basic solution is presented: PEER repositories participating as usage data providers should upload usage log files in a regular manner. The usage log file is a text (ASCII) file containing, at a minimum, a record of the time and origin of requests for the PDFs provided by PEER.</p><p>The party selected to perform usage research in WP5 (CIBER group, see Ch. 3.1.2) is required to approach publishers individually for access to their log files. As a consequence, this interaction with publishers will not be described further in this report. See Appendix F: Current and planned practice in the provision of usage data in a participating repository</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1">Work package interdependency</head><p>The PEER project <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref> will investigate the effects of the large-scale deposit of publications in repositories on user access, author visibility, and journal viability. Three tenders have been launched for behavioural and usage (December 2008) as well as for economic research (September 2009), respectively 3 . In order to enable this research organised in work package 1 and 5 of PEER, WP2 and WP3 are required to prepare the technical ground. This chapter describes basic assumptions and decisions relevant for specifying what WP2 and WP3 can provide for the usage research. The objectives of the usage research will be:</p><p>a. to determine usage trends at publishers and repositories b. understand source and nature of use of deposited manuscripts in repositories c. track trends, develop indicators, and explain patterns of usage for repositories and journals <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[2]</ref> Thus, usage research requires:</p><p>• Complete information on the publications to be observed (see Ch. 2)</p><p>• Recorded usage events for these publications from all participating repositories as data-providers</p><p>The remainder of this chapter describes how these requirements can be met by the PEER project, specifically WP2 and WP3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Usage research team</head><p>The CIBER group from University College London (UCL) has been selected to perform usage research. Together with the behavioural research team it will provide final reports 1</p><p>The DoW orginally names this task "Harvesting of log files". Since the recommended practice was altered, it is preferred in this document to call it "provision of usage data". 2</p><p>The publishers are individually reaching agreement with CIBER regarding their log file provision, since they do not have a uniform set-up internally. 3 http://www.peerproject.eu/press-releases-announcements/ mid 2011 and will feed into model development to determine whether (and how) traditional publishing systems can co-exist with self-archiving. 1   CIBER is concerned that the rate of usage of the material be limited if no repositories from English speaking countries are included, since the vast majority of content is English language. They expressed the need to expand the repository task force to achieve better geographic representation. Thus, CIBER recommended the addition of a repository in the UK to better reflect the usage of predominantly English language content. Furthermore, log files from the repositories for at least six months are required before PEER content becomes available in order to indicate if this additional content makes any difference to usage levels. For participating repositories that are dedicated PEER repositories this requirement cannot be met, since they contain no legacy content.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3">Motivation</head><p>Usage research in the domain of digital scholarly publications has recently been discussed intensively in the context of developing expressive indicators and metrics for the impact of scholarly publications (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[3]</ref> for a recent summary). Other than the conventional approaches based on citations and often related to complete journals rather than to the article level, usage events are thought to have the potential of providing higher temporal and thematic resolution ("quicker and more precise"). Methodologies have been developed <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref>, also in large scale projects (e.g. MESUR <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref>) and standards are about to be expressed (e.g. PIRUS <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[3]</ref>). Within PEER, it was assumed that these developments are premature -thus implicating unforeseen work for the project -and it was decided <ref type="bibr">[6]</ref> not to prepare the infrastructure for the use of such methodologies or standards but rather to provide 'raw' web-server log files to the party acquiring the usage research tender. Thus, specific questions to be answered by this document are limited as follows:</p><p>• How can raw web-server log files be transmitted from local data providers to the Usage research team? • What is the structure of the log files?</p><p>• Which data shall be as minimum provided with the web-server log files?</p><p>• How can PEER articles be identified in log files?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Transmission of Log files</head><p>Local data providers upload their local log files to a secure server located at UCL. UCL has set up accounts for the data providers in order to upload by SSH based protocol rsync, SCP or SFTP. An automated upload by rsync over SSH on a daily basis with one (compressed) file per day is preferred. Alternatively the dropbox at &lt;http://www.ucl.ac.uk/dropbox/&gt; may be used. In this case the files should be sent weekly or monthly with all the daily files in a compressed archive format. The reader may picture this package as a tar.gz or zip-file with the naming convention:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PEER_usage_[data_provider_name]_[yyyymmddhhmmss].log.[tgz | zip]".</head><p>The chosen file naming convention is specifically designed to avoid mistaken file overwriting.</p><p>The KB, though, will not deliver log files to the PEER project.</p><p>1 Any data supplied to CIBER will be stored on a secure server located at UCL in London and held in accordance with UCL data protection policies, http://www.ucl.ac.uk/efd/recordsoffice/dataprotection/</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Structure of Log files</head><p>The log analysis team requests full and raw logs for two reasons <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[7]</ref>.</p><p>1. Additional information over and above the minimum enables better validation of the data.</p><p>2. Additional information provides information on patterns of use, and thus the development of a richer model of user behaviour.</p><p>This implies refraining from the application of cleaning routines, typical of analytic tools such as AW-Stats [8]. Also, it is assumed (according to <ref type="bibr">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">7]</ref>) that log files may contain non-PEER documents and that the filtering out PEER documents is an obligation of the research team (see also "Identification of Documents") <ref type="bibr">[11]</ref>.</p><p>A  1 It should be noted that, at least according to German law, IP-addresses are not allowed to be recorded and handed over to a third party. IP-logging can be either suppressed in the configuration of the applied logging-routine or the log file has to be made anonymous before submitting them. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">2</ref> PubMan repository reports it cannot provide a username in the logs. This is also anonymised, and only logged-in users vs. non-logged in users are tracked.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>As an apache configuration:</head><p>"%h %l %u %t \"%r\" %&gt;s %b \"%{Referer}i\" \"%{User-agent}i\""</p><p>Where for reasons of confidentiality data has to be suppressed or anonymised then the redacted fields should be replaced with a hash value. In the particular case of IP addresses it is essential to provide the first three octets of the IP, e.g. '128.40.47.21' may be rewritten as '128.40.47.xxx'. A hash of the full value in addition is highly desirable.</p><p>The suggested procedure for redaction is thus:</p><p>Original log entry: It is expected that different software environments (e.g. simple apache server logs as in the case of standard repository systems or complex service oriented architectures as in the case of the MPDL) will cause different local policies for providing log files and some pitfalls are manifest:</p><p>• The filename or identifier appearing as http-request in the log file may only be known to the application (repository) but has no reference to PEER documents. • In other cases raw log files may contain only cryptic calls of services (e.g. a PHP script 1 Web-services, Session Management, Cookie etc.) that does not contain any identifier and render a later identification of documents difficult or impossible. • When http-'post' is used instead of http-'get' the identifier may be used as 'TYPE=HIDDEN' and does not appear in the log file.</p><p>These cases -as well as the many others that can occur -would render it impossible for the research team to infer which usage event belongs to a specific PEER-document. Thus, specific elaborations of the log files are to be prepared by an individual data provider. These elaborations might have different formats and encodings (e.g. TXT, CSV, XML, XLS) but the use of simple ASCII-textfiles is highly recommended, to avoid errors in the postprocessing by the research team and to limit their workload.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Identification of documents</head><p>Raw log files contain much data of no relevance to the PEER project. Although WP1 have decided to leave the task of filtering out that data that are relevant for PEER to the Usage research team, it is the assumed responsibility of WP2 to indicate the identification of the usage events for publications relevant for PEER. This is conceived here essentially as any kind of object identifier that can be used to match strings in the usage log files.</p><p>As agreed <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[7]</ref>, the research design (WP1) foresees that 100% metadata for publications eligible in PEER are provided by the publishers (via a continuous FTP upload to the PEER Depot). These metadata will be provided by PEER to the Usage research team (see 3.1.2), in order to obtain the current list at any given point in time, enabling the matching between usage events in log files and eligible articles.</p><p>It has also been agreed <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[12]</ref>, that an identifier will be created at the PEER Depot (see Ch. 1.3.1) that should be used by repositories as a filename after the document has been received from the PEER Depot.</p><p>This filename of the full-text provided by PEER should, in an optimal situation, allow easy tracking of usage events in the log files. It is therefore mandatory for participating repositories to represent this PEER-filename, either in the URL of the document or in any form that allows a later mapping between an internal identifier occurring in the usage event and the PEER-filename 1 . In the latter case, the deposit procedures of a participating repository must thus ensure storage of the PEER-filename as an additional identifier for each document. Furthermore, the participating repository must provide a list with pairs of local identifiers and PEER-filenames or a pattern to match to the research team, to track which usage event belongs to which document.</p><p>It was also decided <ref type="bibr">[6;7]</ref> that only 50% of the articles eligible in PEER are deposited on behalf of the publishers while the other 50% are subject to spontaneous author submission. The latter 50% will be deposited via a central author deposit interface to the PEER Depot and transferred to all participating repositories. Therefore the PEER Depot makes this matching before depositing to repositories. Thus usage events can be readily identified in the raw log files also for spontaneous deposited articles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Expected Result</head><p>The expected result of this procedure is a service provided by UCL, by which each participating repository uploads raw server log files that contain usage events of PEER articles. The additional requirement of a list of articles eligible in PEER is subject to the specification of the deposit process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4</head><p>Ongoing support for publishers and repository managers</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Introduction</head><p>Communication between the publisher community, the PEER Depot and the repository community has been ongoing during the course of the project and is documented in this chapter to bring together the recent developments and resolution of outstanding issues described in D2.1 Draft report on the provision of usage data and manuscript deposit procedures for publishers and repository managers.</p><p>Due to the overlapping nature of the work, the main point of contact between the members of work package 2/3 is the list service &lt;peer-wp2-3@inria.fr&gt;. The Project Manager serves to represent the publisher community and is included in the listserv communication mechanism. Face-to-face meetings are held regularly between participating publishers, the repository task force and above all, the members of the respective work packages. This provides the opportunity to discuss issues in detail which would exceed the limits of e-mail contact. Several meetings dedicated to discussing technical issues in work package 2/3 were held at various locations. Partners and stakeholders across Europe hosted these meetings: STM, London (M2) &amp; (M4); Elsevier, Amsterdam (M6); INRIA, Paris (M8); SURF Foundation, Utrecht (M10) and Max Planck Digital Library, Munich (M13).</p><p>The draft recommendations of D2.1 were tested in the course of these discussions. Queries that have arisen in areas of concern are indicated and some alterations to the workflow are formulated in this final report.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Establishment of a Helpdesk</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.1">Helpdesk functions</head><p>Actors involved in the ongoing support facility envisaged include authors, publishers, repository representatives and PEER researchers. Support for stakeholders on deposit is available from two sources. Firstly, the PEER website offers general information on the project and detailed information tailored to the needs of the various stakeholder groups.</p><p>Secondly, a PEER Helpdesk 1 online interface has been established. The Helpdesk is envisaged as a key point of contact for all the stakeholder communities participating in PEER and has been established primarily as a central point of author support, available at &lt;http://peer.mpdl.mpg.de/helpdesk&gt;.</p><p>This online interface, linked from the PEER website, is an authoritative source of information. Publishers refer authors to the Helpdesk that, in turn, will direct the author to the deposit interface (see Ch. 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">&amp; Appendix D: Peer Author Deposit interface specification).</head><p>As an online interface the Helpdesk will facilitate outreach and information provision activities and will moreover provide advice and support on the implementation of the D3.1 Guidelines 2 , and questions of deposit and transfer, as described in this report.</p><p>The Helpdesk will offer direct support by means of an online query and mediated response service throughout the project duration. Automated systems have been investigated based on the following project criteria:</p><p>• Meeting the diverse needs of three identified stakeholder communities</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Efficient query handling and response mechanisms</head><p>• Handling of specific query behaviour on predetermined information-seeking tasks 1 http://peer.mpdl.mpg.de/helpdesk 2 http://www.peerproject.eu/reports/ The technical representatives of work package 2/3 came to the result to implement the support facility in the form of a ticket system (software Trac, which offers a Wiki and an issue tracker in one). A ticketing system is highly effective since the questions and answers are well documented. Each query result will be published, and the participants are able to review arising issues. This system then also provides a mechanism of passive interaction for those seeking assistance, but are unwilling to ask -a notable online query behaviour pattern. Where the ticketing system is made public, the "wisdom of crowds" principle can be applied to gain more efficient response to complex problems. Furthermore, frequently asked questions (FAQs) have been developed on the basis of the query results for future reference and published on the Helpdesk site, based on that established in DRIVER 1 . Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">6</ref> below shows the generic ticketing system workflow: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.2">Helpdesk Workflow</head><p>The Helpdesk workflow has been modelled on the DRIVER Helpdesk system, supported by the collaborative Wiki concept: Everybody receives all the queries and answers. But to ensure that each question gets answered, every query is passed on to a designated member of work package 2/3 who will be responsible for allocated areas of support. The moderator at SUB Göttingen is to monitor the Helpdesk and refer queries to representatives of WP2/3 as per designated responsibilities.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.3">Helpdesk for Publishers and Repository Managers</head><p>Publishers will deposit both 50% of the full-text outputs, as well as 100% of the metadata outputs from eligible journals at the PEER Depot. The 50% full-text outputs will be transferred from the PEER Depot to the repositories participating in PEER.</p><p>Although it is expected that implementing the D3.1 Guidelines is straightforward, the PEER Helpdesk will, however, support the consistent explanation and information on guiding publishers and repository managers through the deposition process.</p><p>The support for publishers is provided by experts resp. representatives of INRIA and is expected to cover queries regarding the expected metadata schema, transfer procedures, deviations from profile submitted, etc.</p><p>The support for repository managers is provided by expert representatives from SURF and MPDL. It is expected to cover queries regarding how to obtain the "NSCA combined" log file format, if not directly available. This might entail the provision of scripts for mapping from other formats, help for using the PEER-filename in the repository, advice on the corresponding interface to implement the SWORD protocol, etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.4">Helpdesk for Authors</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.4.3">Guidance for authors on deposit procedures</head><p>For reasons of data privacy, no direct communication is envisaged between the project members and eligible authors. The procedures of author communication in the framework of the PEER project are described in detail in the D3.1 Guidelines. Therefore, the D3.1 Guidelines are not directed at the author community directly, but rather they reflect the considered opinion of the work package in consultation with the publisher community on recommended practice in offering assistance to authors.</p><p>The PEER Helpdesk will not only offer guidance to publishers and repository managers, often already involved in large-scale archiving, but mainly to authors, who may need PEER website</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PEER Helpdesk (Trac)</head><p>FAQticket results</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>e-mailticket results</head><p>Author guidance in self-archiving for the first time. A recent study by Swan indicates that a substantial proportion of the author population (36%) are unaware of the possibility of providing Open Access to their work by self-archiving, and that only 49% of the author population have self-archived in some way. Of relevance to the PEER Helpdesk is the observation that authors have frequently expressed reluctance to self-archive because of the perceived time required and possible technical difficulties in carrying out this activity. However, similar findings suggest that only 20% of authors found some degree of difficulty with the first act of depositing an article in a repository, and that this dropped to 9% for subsequent deposits. 1  Therefore, information on the Helpdesk is intended to be given in a plain and easy way.</p><p>The authors will be guided to the PEER Helpdesk by their publishers. The PEER Helpdesk offers:</p><p>• Generic information on the PEER project</p><p>• Option of deposit</p><p>• The possibility to pose questions by creating a ticket</p><p>• FAQ</p><p>• Information on embargo periods</p><p>• Information on and for publishers</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Information on and for repositories</head><p>Enabling the author to choose to deposit their data within the scope of the project but also to an alternative repository of their choice, in accordance with already established practice, the PEER Helpdesk offers the author two options of deposit:</p><p>a. PEER Author deposit</p><p>In line with the way of author deposit the project agreed upon (Ch. 2.3.4) the author will be guided from the Helpdesk to the central deposit interface for deposit of accepted manuscripts from participating PEER journals in PEER repositories. At the same time he/she will be alerted that by deposting once, his/her manuscript will be available in all the participating repositories after the expiration of the embargo period.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>b. non-PEER Author deposit</head><p>As agreed in D3.1 Guidelines 2 , the project will address those authors who do not wish to deposit within the framework of the PEER project. Accordingly, the author will be guided to a dedicated page on the Helpdesk, where he/she is requested to insert the URL of the article submitted in his/her preferred repository of choice. The data gathered will be sent to the behavioural research team.</p><p>No direct communication between the project and the author is envisaged for reasons of data privacy 3 . Nevertheless, for the project, in particular for the behavioural research team, it would be worth collecting details of non-PEER deposits. Therefore, the author is additionally requested to provide his/her name and e-mail address to enable the behavioural research team to possibly contact him/her with a questionnaire. If author information is to be used […], permission will be asked of the authors at the point where the author provides this information.</p><p>Individuals may be contacted for the purposes of PEER research either by publishers, repositories, or directly by the research teams. Where such contact takes place, it will be undertaken in accordance with the data protection and privacy policies of the relevant organisation. 1   Hence, it is optional for the author to provide the two last details on a voluntary basis. The author will be alerted that by giving his/her e-mail address he/she agrees to be addressed by the behavioural research team. Although we cannot determine how many author deposits will be done outside the scope of the project, because authors may or may not declare their intent, the information gathered on alternative deposit may provide useful information to the behavioural research.</p><p>1 PEER Privacy Policy: http://www.peerproject.eu/privacy-policy/</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusions</head><p>This report concludes the development of an overall framework for depositing stage-two outputs in and for harvesting log files from repositories. An innovative workflow has been devised to describe and standardise the deposit from publishers to repositories that demonstrates, in a core group of interoperable European repositories, the capability of accepting material deposited from third party publishers and authors beyond the project duration.</p><p>The development of an appropriate workflow for author deposits has proved challenging, as the author response is unpredictable, and cannot readily be standardised. The guiding principle adopted is that authors are encouraged to follow their established practice of deposit in an institutional or subject-specific repository. Failing such practice, a central deposit in the PEER Depot for distribution to designated PEER repositories is recommended.</p><p>A number of concerns remain, and may yet impact on the project outcomes. The author deposit workflow described in this report is acknowledged as no more than an effort to keep track of authors self-archiving to PEER repositories and other repositories. While it is precisely this lack of a controlled response to the invitation to participate that will inform the behaviour and usage research investigations in Work Packages 4 &amp; 5 respectively, without significant author participation, the value of the research may ultimately be compromised.</p><p>Another concern arising from the project design is the limitation of the research sample, resulting from the filtering process. While 50% full-texts of the publishers' content is disseminated to repositories and the LTP Depot, in fact, only that portion represented by the European corresponding author within that 50% are effectively disseminated. The effective percentage of disseminated content will therefore be lower than 50%. This potential deficiency is noted for ongoing monitoring in work package 3, and adjustment of content quotas is recommended during the course of the project to ensure a valid research procedure.</p><p>Evident too is the delayed research implementation affected by the 6 month embargo period. Ongoing attempts to secure back files accumulated by publishers may serve to alleviate this concern. Furthermore, log files from the repositories for at least the previous six months are required before PEER content becomes available in order to indicate whether additional PEER content makes any difference to usage levels. For participating repositories that are dedicated PEER repositories this requirement is invalid, since they contain no legacy content.</p><p>Despite the accepted recommendation by CIBER to support an increased rate of usage of predominantly English language content material by the inclusion of repositories from English-speaking countries, this has yet to be achieved. Although this recommendation will be pursued, preliminary enquiries indicate a reluctance to participate in the project, ostensibly on the basis of heavy workloads of repository managers, who furthermore do not benefit financially from the project.</p><p>The final report on the provision of usage data and manuscript deposit procedures for publishers and repository managers reflects a collaborative effort between publishers and the library and repository stakeholder communities to achieve a feasible workflow for depositing stage-2 outputs and for harvesting log files from repositories. The limitations of the project design have been identified and made known to the behavioural and usage research teams in WP 4 and 5 respectively, to monitor their anticipated impact on the project outcomes. An example of an implementation of such a container would be a ZIP-file containing a fulltext manuscript in the PDF/A-1 format and descriptive metadata in the TEI-XML format.</p><p>The container is being submitted by a client to a SWORD interface service (server) as a bit stream using a HTTP POST request consisting of a header containing information about authorisation and the bit stream (type and format of the container) in order for the server to be able to interpret the bit stream properly, and a body part containing the bit stream itself (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">9</ref>). Upon reception, the server sends a HTTP response back to the clientagain consisting of a header and a body part -with the header containing a HTTP status code indicating a success or failure of the attempted deposit according to regular HTTP semantics, and a response document containing additional APP/SWORD specific information about the deposit being made. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Use of SWORD in PEER</head><p>In the PEER workflow there are two scenarios of deposits into the PEER repositories specified: deposit made by PEER and deposit made by authors (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_16">10</ref>) This results in an n:n-relation between repositories and deposit sources either the PEER Depot or third party services operated by an author (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">11</ref>). To prevent multiple tailored solutions and implementations it is important to define a standard process for the deposit of material into repositories.</p><p>The processes may be categorised into two types of mechanisms: push and pull. An example of the pull mechanism is the KB's mechanism of the e-depot harvesting repositories through OAI-PMH and pulling content using a webclient (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">12</ref>) which downloads the objects specified in the location entries in the metadata. An example of the push mechanism is the SWORD deposit mechanism where the data is being pushed by an agent (i.e. a webservice or desktop application representing a user) to the SWORD interface of a repository which then accepts or rejects the deposit (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">13</ref>). Finally, a third, hybrid mechanism can be created by setting up an FTP server to which deposits can be uploaded (pushed) by an agent. A repository may then pull the FTP content which is then being pulled into the repository (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">14</ref>). A disadvantage of this mechanism is that this only provides direct feedback to the agent about status of the upload, not of the status of the actual deposit into the repository. This may lead to the situation when an agent successfully uploads data to the FTP server, but the data is being rejected by the repository afterwards because it does not adhere to rules the repository enforces on its contents without the agent being informed about this rejection -something that is not the case when using SWORD.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">15</ref> provides a schematic overview of the use of SWORD in the PEER deposit scenario. Here a publisher transfers manuscripts and metadata into the PEER Depot where the manuscripts and metadata are being converted and crosswalked to the formats specified for the PEER deposit process. The converted and crosswalked manuscripts and metadata are then being packaged into a container and sent to the SWORD interface service of a repository where the contents are being unpacked from the container. Upon reception these MAY be converted and crosswalked into an internal storage format before they are being archived into the repository. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Package Support</head><p>The PEER Submission Information Package (SIP) MAY be expressed using (a combination of) different formats (i.e. XML containers or RFC 1951 compliant ZIP archives) and/or serialised using different structural models (i.e. DIDL, METS, ORE, TEI, NLM, MODS, DC). The mappings between the SIP, its components and the formats and structures will be defined and expressed using specialised application profiles developed in the PEER context. It is recognised that the repository MAY want to keep track of data that is being deposited within the PEER context by creating a single user account to the PEER Depot. This then covers the publisher deposit workflow, but does not provide for a solution for the case of author deposit through another web service which MAY use different credentials.</p><p>A possible solution MAY be the use of mediated deposit where a client authenticates using its assigned credentials on behalf of another known user (e.g. a web service authenticates using its own credentials and makes the deposit on behalf of the PEER user which is used by the PEER Depot).</p><p>This method MAY also be used to authenticate on behalf of other users (i.e. authors, librarians, data stewards, research assistants, etc.) that already have a valid user account at the repository.</p><p>The use of mediated deposit is considered OPTIONAL and is currently not implemented in the application of the SWORD profile within the PEER project.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1">Mediation in Service Description</head><p>Servers supporting mediated deposit MUST indicate this by including a SWORD:mediation element with a value of "true" in the Service Document as defined in the SWORD profile version 1.3 section 2.1.</p><p>For servers that do not include a SWORD mediation element in the Service Document, a default value of "no" SHOULD be assumed by clients.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Auto-discovery</head><p>AtomPub makes no recommendations on the discovery of Service Documents.</p><p>The SWORD profile states that it is RECOMMENDED that server implementations use an &lt;html:link rel="sword" href="[Service Document URL]"/&gt; element in the head of a relevant HTML document to assist with service discovery.</p><p>In addition, it is RECOMMENDED to also include an &lt;atom:link rel="sword" type="application/atomsvc+xml" href="[Service Document URL]"/&gt; element in relevant response documents such as Error Documents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Nested Service Descriptions</head><p>Nested Service Descriptions MAY be used to specify alternative collections for both organisational (i.e. generic collection with a nested PEER specific collection) and technical purposes (i.e. a specific interface or service instance to cater for specific types of content packaging).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Use of APP features</head><p>The contents of the following section are organised according and supplementary to the document SWORD Atom Pub Profile version 1.3 part B. If a SWORD profile section or feature is omitted, implementations MUST behave as defined in SWORD profile.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Securing the Atom Publishing Protocol</head><p>The SWORD profile states servers SHOULD support the use of HTTP Basic Authentication over TLS. Because from a trust perspective it is important to confirm the identity of the PEER Depot during the deposit proces, this statement is considered insufficient for the purposes of the PEER project.Therefor this requirement has been restated as follows:</p><p>Servers implementing SWORD MUST support HTTP Basic Authentication (RFC 2617) over TLS (RFC 2818).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Creating and Editing Resources</head><p>When depositing resources using SWORD, resources are created by a server when a client makes an HTTP POST request with the resource in the HTTP request body. If the deposit is made successfully, the server then gives a HTTP reponse with the HTTP 201 Status code in the header of the response indicating the resource has been successfully created at the repository side.</p><p>Servers returning a HTTP 201 status code after a deposit MUST preserve the resource deposited.</p><p>Clients receiving a HTTP 201 status code MUST consider the resource deposited as being accepted for storage by the repository.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Asynchronous treatment of resources</head><p>It MAY however be the case that the repository implements an additional asynchronous validation process after which a resource MAY or MAY NOT be accepted. This for instance is the case when a repository uses an intermediate repository where resources deposited through the SWORD interface are temporarily stored, after which they will be moved to a final location within the repository when they are properly validated by a repository manager. When a resource is then being rejected by the repository during the validation process after the server has sent an HTTP 201 response to the client, the situation MAY arise where the client considers the resource as being successfully deposited into the repository, while in fact the resource is NOT being stored into the repository. This situation is viewed as undesirable.</p><p>Servers implementing an asynchronous validation process MUST return an HTTP 202 Accept response code indicating the request has been accepted for processing, but the processing has not been completed.</p><p>Clients receiving a HTTP 202 status code upon deposit of a resource MUST consider the resource deposited as NOT being stored into the repository.</p><p>RFC2616 states that there is no facility for the re-sending of status codes. Therefore, a client will not receive a notification of the outcome of the processing carried out by the server. In order to allow clients to retrieve the outcome of the deposit, the sword:treatment element MAY contain the status of the processing of the deposited resource.</p><p>Servers implementing HTTP 202 status codes MUST supply a permanent link to the Atom Entry document of the response.</p><p>Servers implementing HTTP 202 status codes MUST update the sword:treatment element of the Atom Entry document of the resource with the status of the processing of the deposited resource.</p><p>Client SHOULD implement a mechanism to confirm the successful deposit by periodically checking back at the server with an HTTP GET request to the permanent link supplied by the server, in order to check the contents of the sword:treatment element of the Atom Entry describing the deposited resource when a HTTP 202 status code has been received upon deposit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">PEER Object Model</head><p>In order to future proof agreements and guidelines for a technical model, it is important to detach the technical implementation from the abstract object and information model. Furthermore, it is important to keep this abstract model aligned with other developments in the area the model will be used in. For PEER, there are two of such developments:</p><p>• OAIS Reference Model for its use by the KB</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• DRIVER object model for Enhanced Publications for its use in DRIVER context</head><p>In PEER, manuscripts and metadata will be transferred between authors, publishers, the PEER Depot, Open Access repositories and an LTP Depot exploited by the KB.</p><p>This results in a PEER object consisting of a manuscript object which is being described by one or more metadata objects (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_22">18</ref>). The D2.1 report provides an exhaustive metadata field set to be used in the PEER project (see Table <ref type="table">5</ref>, below). For deposit the PEER object will be packaged into a container. The OAIS reference model specifies the Submission Information Package (SIP) as a specialised Information Package (IP) -which is used by the KB in the e-depot -for submission purposes (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_23">19</ref>). An IP consists of content information that is being described by Package Description Information (PDI).</p><p>The content information object is defined as a data object (i.e. PDF file) interpreted using representation information (i.e. mime-type, encoding version, etc.) (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">20</ref>). Note the structure information being a part of the representation information.</p><p>The PDI (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_24">21</ref>) contains Reference Information (i.e. bibliographic descriptions and persistent identifiers), Provenance Information (i.e. information about the conversion process), Context Information (i.e. reference to the research project a publication is based on) and Fixity Information (i.e. a checksum). The PEER information model can be mapped onto the OAIS Reference Model as depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_25">22</ref>. Here the structure object containing the structural information is being added to the PEER object model. Atom feed is to be contained in an XML file. The metadata is serialised in TEI, again contained in an XML file. The manuscript is encoding in PDF/A, contained in a PDF-file.</p><p>The XML file containing the ORE Atom feed, the XML file containing the TEI document and the PDF file containing the manuscript are then being packaged in a compliant ZIP-file. Upon deposit using SWORD, the ZIP-file is being placed into the body of the HTTP POST request. The Header contains an MD5 checksum and MAY contain authorisation information (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">24</ref>).</p><p>The HTTP POST request is then being sent to the SWORD Interface Service as described in paragraph 1.2. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Overview of the technical process</head><p>Generally speaking, the technical process of deposit can be broken in sequential order to the serialisation and deposit request sub-processes on the client side (i.e. the PEER Depot) and the de-serialisation, response and store sub-processes on the repository side (i.e. publicly available repository).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.1">Serialisation -Client side</head><p>The serialisation processes involve the serialisation of the metadata from an internal storage to a specific (agreed upon standard) metadata field set and structure (i.e. DC) and the packaging of the metadata and object file(s) into a content package (i.e. MPEG-21 DIDL XML containers or compliant ZIP archives) which MAY include adding a manifest describing contents and their correlation (i.e. the relation between an XML file containing the descriptive metadata of a full-text publication and a PDF-file containing the actual full-text publication) to a bit stream.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2">Deposit Request -Client side</head><p>The deposit request process includes a client posting the data to a service (i.e. the HTTP POST request in SWORD) and the server receiving the data and placing it into a temporary storage (either in memory or on disk).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.3">De-serialisation -Repository side</head><p>In the de-serialisation process the receiving server tries to interpret (decode) the bit stream again, in essence validating the contents. This MAY include the unpacking (when using ZIP archives) or decoding (when using XML containers) of the bit stream to be able to interpret the individual contents. It MAY also include the mapping or crosswalking of the metadata structure to an internal (proprietary) metadata field set and/or structure. This process MAY not necessarily be taking place in the actual interface service; it MAY include the sending of the bit stream to an internal storage service which then indicates a success or failure to the deposit service.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.4">Response -Repository side</head><p>After the contents are being de-serialised successfully and the server confirms the contents of the received bitstream, the server MUST reply its status to the client (when using SWORD this means reporting the appropriate HTTP status code and correct Atom/SWORD response document). If the deserialisation process has failed for whatever reason, the server SHOULD reject the deposit request to indicate an unsuccessful deposit to the client, or accept the deposit with an HTTP 4xx status code and appropriate exception message indicating a partial successful deposit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.5">Store -Repository side</head><p>The final step of the deposit process includes the storage of the received (meta)data into the internal (meta)data store. This part of the process is implementation specific and considered outside the scope of this document.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Functional Requirements</head><p>A repository implementing a SWORD interface service in the PEER context MUST be able to:</p><p>• Authenticate a user</p><p>• Receive, process and respond to an HTTP POST request as specified in this document • Interpret and store a PEER Submission Information Package as specified by the PEER project</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Implementation Steps</head><p>The implementation steps can be broken down into the implementation and exposure of the web service to the outside world and interface with the repository on the inside.</p><p>Depending on specific needs, an implementer of the SWORD profile may either choose to make an implementation by using one of the repository specific implementations available for DSpace, ePrints and Fedora on Sourceforge 1 or to write a custom SWORD server implementation (optionally by using the generic Java library also available from Sourceforge).</p><p>For the repository specific option please refer to the documentation provided with the designated packages.</p><p>The second option either involves writing a service from scratch or use the source code available from the SWORD Java library. This library contains ready to implement code for writing servers and clients.</p><p>In addition to creating the web service which behaves according to the guidelines specified in this document, special attention should be paid to the creation of crosswalk rules to map the expression(s) of the PEER SIP to the internal repository data structure and semantics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Common implementation faults</head><p>In the initial testing phase, a number of common implementation faults have been identified. This paragraph will provide a brief overview of these findings and provide guidelines in order to avoid these mishaps.</p><p>1 SWORD Project, SourceForge.net: SWORD -Project Web Hosting -Open Source Software, viewed on 25 March 2009, http://sword-app.sourceforge.net/</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.1">Mandatory fields for Atom Entry</head><p>A number of issues have been identified with regard to the contents of the Atom Entry within the service response documents.</p><p>RFC 5023 (Atom Publishing Protocol) states:</p><p>Implementers are asked to note that [RFC4287] specifies that Atom Entries MUST contain an atom:summary element. Thus, upon successful creation of a Media Link Entry, a server MAY choose to populate the atom:summary element (as well as any other mandatory elements such as atom:id, atom:author, and atom:title) with content derived from the POSTed entity or from any other source. A server might not allow a client to modify the server-selected values for these elements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.2">Field Semantics</head><p>All contents of the Atom Entry document are to be interpreted as within the SWORD context. For example, atom:author states the author of the transaction (i.e. authenticated user), not that of the contents being transported (i.e. author of the publication).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.3">Atom:Id</head><p>The contents of the atom:id field MUST be encoded using IRI (International Resource Identifier) as defined in RFC3987.</p><p>Valid example:</p><p>&lt;atom:id&gt;http://hdl.handle.net/2437.2/20&lt;/atom:id&gt;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Invalid example:</head><p>&lt;atom:id&gt;1234&lt;/atom:id&gt;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Locations</head><p>When the server has processed the submission information package containing the fulltext and metadata files, a number of locations may be identified:  • Author registers at the PEER Helpdesk.</p><p>• Author selects a participating repository for deposit.</p><p>• Author enters URL of additional /alternative repository of choice.</p><p>• Author is redirected to the chosen repository to make deposit.</p><p>• Author is authenticated under generic PEER guest account.</p><p>• Author deposits his/her data in the repository.</p><p>• Author receives a notification of successful deposit.</p><p>• Embargo management is handled by the repository.</p><p>• Repositories transfer their usage log files to the Usage research team.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Problems:</head><p>• Setting up a central author registration application means an additional effort of funding and staff resources. Author accesses the PEER repository website + registers at repository to make deposit. Authors, including remote authors (= not affiliated to the repository host institution), are authenticated for deposit. Author makes deposit at repository/ies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Repositories:</head><p>-Send notification of successful deposit to author -Embargo management -Usage log file transfer to Usage Research Team Author follows invitation to access further details via PEER Helpdesk and selects a participating repository for deposit, or enters URL of additional /alternative repository of choice.</p><p>Author receives notification of acceptance, including invitation from publisher to self-archive stage-2 article.</p><p>• Central registration is dependent upon authentication of generic PEER account at repositories. • Embargo management requires automated matching process at repositories: match author submitted article with metadata from publishers (transferred by PEER Depot) and overwrite author's metadata with publisher's metadata. Elements of manual checking may occur (e.g. special characters). It is possible to combine the central registration with a central deposit with the authors uploading their articles directly into the PEER Depot. Author deposits will in this scenario be handled like publisher deposits, with distribution to all participating repositories, and where duplicate filtering and embargo management will also happen at the PEER Depot.</p><p>The workflow for central author deposits is described in scenarios 3 &amp; 4 below. • Author registers at the PEER Helpdesk.</p><p>• Author is redirected to a deposit interface on the PEER Depot.</p><p>• Author deposits his/her data in the PEER Depot.</p><p>• Author receives notification of successful deposit.</p><p>• Embargo management at the PEER Depot, as per publisher deposits.</p><p>• Distribution of author deposits to all participating repositories, as per publisher deposits. • Repositories transfer their usage log files to the Usage research team.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Problems:</head><p>• Central deposit seen as interference with the 'natural way' of author depositreferred to and approved by Executive. • No communication between authors and repositories. • Author is redirected to the PEER Depot for registration and deposit. • Author registers at the PEER Depot.</p><p>• Author deposits his/her data in the PEER Depot.</p><p>• Author receives notification of successful deposit.</p><p>• Embargo management at the PEER Depot, as per publisher deposits.</p><p>• Distribution of author deposits to all participating repositories, as per publisher deposits. • Repositories transfer their usage log files to the Usage research team.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Problems:</head><p>• Setting up a central author registration application means an additional effort of funding and staff resources. • Central deposit seen as interference with 'natural way' of author deposit -referred to and approved by Executive. • No communication between authors and repositories. Author receives notification of acceptance, including invitation from publisher to self archive stage-2 article.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author registers &amp; deposits at PEER Depot</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PEER Depot:</head><p>-Send notification of successful deposit to author -Embargo management -Distribution of author deposits to all participating repositories, as per publisher deposits.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>12 Table 2 :FiguresFigure 1 :Figure 2 :Figure 3 :</head><label>122123</label><figDesc>FiguresFigure 1: PEER workflow......................................................................................................................10 Figure 2: Deposit procedure from the PEER Depot to the repositories................................................15 Figure 3: Transmission action via the HTTP-protocol ..........................................................................17</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Notification of successful transfer from PEER Depot to repository .......................................17</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 5 :Figure 6 :Figure 7 :Figure 8 :Figure 12 :</head><label>567812</label><figDesc>Figure 5: PEER author deposit workflow ..............................................................................................28 Figure 6: UML activity diagram of Helpdesk ticketing system workflow ...............................................37 Figure 7: PEER Helpdesk: Input flow ...................................................................................................38 Figure 8: Content Package or Container ..............................................................................................53 Figure 9: HTTP request and response structure in the SWORD context.............................................53 Figure 10: PEER Workflow ...................................................................................................................54 Figure 11: Deposit situation ..................................................................................................................54 Figure 12: OAI-PMH data harvest ........................................................................................................54 Figure 13: SWORD data deposit ..........................................................................................................54 Figure 14: SWORD versus FTP ...........................................................................................................55 Figure 15: SWORD use in PEER for PEER Depot...............................................................................56 Figure 16: Submission Information Package structure.........................................................................56 Figure 17: PEER deposit workflow .......................................................................................................58 Figure 18: PEER Object model ERD ....................................................................................................60 Figure 19: OAIS Information Package ERD .........................................................................................62 Figure 20: OAIS Content Information Object ERD ...............................................................................62 Figure 21: OAIS Package Description Information ERD ......................................................................63 Figure 22: OAIS Reference Model-PEER Information Mapping ..........................................................63 Figure 23: Technical Mapping of the PEER model...............................................................................64 Figure 24: HTTP Mapping of the Technical Model ...............................................................................65 Figure 25: Scenario 1 ...........................................................................................................................71 Figure 26: Scenario 2 ...........................................................................................................................72 Figure 27: Scenario 3 ...........................................................................................................................73 Figure 28: Scenario 4 ...........................................................................................................................74</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: PEER workflow</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>a. a single XML file, not zipped b. a CSV file (see Appendix B: Technical specifications for CSV metadata provision) Derived from the DRIVER Guidelines [3], the minimum required set of metadata also includes the mandatory fields recommended in DRIVER viz.: Title, Creator, Date, Type and Identifier. Mandatory fields are marked (*).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Deposit procedure from the PEER Depot to the repositories</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Package format is ZIP • Metadata format is TEI (Text Encoding Initiative) according to the PEER-TEI Application Profile (see Ch. 1.3.2) • PDF format is PDF/A (ISO 19005-1:2005) • Filenames are renamed in the following syntax: PEER_stage2_[DOI].[ext] • [DOI] is the Digital Object Identifier of the publication • [ext] is the extension of the files, either PDF, XML or ZIP • All the slashes in the filename may be replaced with: "_slsh_" This is not encouraged, the default action is to change the webserver configuration to allow slashes. • All filenames are completely URL-encoded 1.4.1.2 SWORD: Transporting embargo released stage-2 materialThe complete ZIP file is then ready for transfer to the repositories on expiration of the embargo period. The embargo period differs per journal and is listed accordingly in Appendix A: Participating journals. The algorithm setting the release date is described in Ch. 1.4.3 below. The transfer is authenticated via the SWORD-APP protocol, posts being authorised only by the PEER Depot.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3 below depicts the transmission action via the HTTP-protocol.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Transmission action via the HTTP-protocol</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Notification of successful transfer from PEER Depot to repository</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Appendix D: Peer Author Deposit interface specification The article and metadata submitted by the author are transferred to the PEER Depot where a. the metadata is matched against those received by the respective publisher b. embargo management takes place c. the author is informed about transfer of data to repositories 2 See minutes of PEER WP 2/3 meeting, 25 th June 2009, SURF, Utrecht. 2 http://recaptcha.net/</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: UML activity diagram of Helpdesk ticketing system workflow</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>below shows the Helpdesk input flow. 1 DRIVER Helpdesk: http://helpdesk.driver.research-infrastructures.eu/ Expert Moderator Inquirer (author, publisher, etc.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: PEER Helpdesk: Input flow</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: Content Package or Container</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: HTTP request and response structure in the SWORD context</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10: PEER Workflow Figure 11: Deposit situation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Figure 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 12: OAI-PMH data harvest</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Figure 13</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Figure 13: SWORD data deposit</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Figure 14 :</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Figure 14: SWORD versus FTP</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Figure 15 :</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Figure 15: SWORD use in PEER for PEER Depot</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Figure 16 :</head><label>16</label><figDesc>Figure 16: Submission Information Package structure</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>Figure 18 :</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Figure 18: PEER Object model ERD</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Figure 19 :</head><label>19</label><figDesc>Figure 19: OAIS Information Package ERD</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head>Figure 21 :</head><label>21</label><figDesc>Figure 21: OAIS Package Description Information ERD</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head>Figure 22 :</head><label>22</label><figDesc>Figure 22: OAIS Reference Model-PEER Information Mapping</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_26"><head>Figure 23 :</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Figure 23: Technical Mapping of the PEER model</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_27"><head>Figure 25: Scenario 1 Scenario 2 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 25: Scenario 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_29"><head>Figure 26 :</head><label>26</label><figDesc>Figure 26: Scenario 2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_30"><head>Scenario 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Central registration at PEER Helpdesk, central deposit at PEER Depot via Helpdesk• Author receives notification of acceptance, including invitation from publisher to selfarchive stage-2 article. At this stage publication date is undetermined, and embargo period is unknown. • Author follows invitation to access further details via PEER Helpdesk.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_31"><head>Figure 27: Scenario 3 Scenario 4 :</head><label>34</label><figDesc>Figure 27: Scenario 3</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_33"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 28: Scenario 4</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="29,91.52,149.10,447.03,374.61" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Minimum metadata requirements</figDesc><table><row><cell>ISSN</cell><cell>These elements are not mandatory to electronic publication and can</cell></row><row><cell>(e-ISSN,</cell><cell>be derived from CrossRef after DOI is provided. They may therefore</cell></row><row><cell>p-ISSN)</cell><cell>not be provided by publishers.</cell></row><row><cell>Volume</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Issue</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>First Page</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Last Page</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Type*</cell><cell>Default value = article. Mapped to info:eu-repo/semantics/article,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>info:eu-repo/semantics/acceptedVersion</cell></row><row><cell>Subject</cell><cell>Subject headings; Scientific classification (defaults to what is provided</cell></row><row><cell>Headings</cell><cell>in the PEER Journal tables)</cell></row><row><cell>Language</cell><cell>Language of the article, ISO 639-3 (defaults to 'eng')</cell></row><row><cell>Embargo</cell><cell>Embargo period for PEER Depot (defaults to what is provided in the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PEER Journal tables)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Publisher name Name of publisher (can be derived from the PEER Journal tables or</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>FTPS homedir and is provided in the metadata file as an element)</cell></row><row><cell>Access</cell><cell>Open Access or Restricted</cell></row></table><note><p><p>1</p>Because the second pass completes the first one, metadata provided twice are not updated.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">3</ref>, and SHOULD be implemented to provide useful error handling information.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Error URI</cell><cell>Usage notes</cell></row></table><note><p>http://purl.org/net/sword/error/ErrorContent The supplied format is not the same as that identified in the X-Packaging header and/or that supported by the server http://purl.org/net/sword/error/ErrorChecksumMismatch Checksum sent does not match the calculated checksum. The server MUST also return a status code of 412 Precondition Failed. http://purl.org/net/sword/error/ErrorBadRequest Some parameters sent with the POST were not understood. The server MUST also return a status code of 400 Bad Request. http://purl.org/net/sword/error/TargetOwnerUnknown Used in mediated deposit (see Part A Section 2) when the server does not know the identity of the X-On-Behalf-Of user. http://purl.org/net/sword/error/MediationNotAllowed Used where a client has attempted a mediated deposit, but this is not supported by the server. The server MUST also return a status code of 412 Precondition Failed.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>SWORD error feedback</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Metadata categories specified under OAIS model</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Log file format</figDesc><table><row><cell>Optional fields that are missing must be represented as "-". Log files are ascii-textfiles.</cell></row><row><cell>Fields are blank-separated and events are paragraph-separated. Please refer to the</cell></row><row><cell>Website [11] for details.</cell></row><row><cell>An example is:</cell></row><row><cell>66.249.66.5 --[12/Jan/2009:20:31:53 +0100] "GET /pdf_frontpage.php?source_opus</cell></row><row><cell>=87&amp;startfile=Egelhaaf_et_al_UniForsch2002.pdf HTTP/1.1" 302 414 "-" "Mozilla/5.</cell></row><row><cell>0 (compatible; Googlebot/2.1; +http://www.google.com/bot.html)"</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The Location element of the HTTP header response MUST contain the URI of the Media Link Entry, as defined in ATOMPUB. The Media Link Entry URI MUST dereference, and MUST contain an atom:content element with a src attribute containing a URI.</figDesc><table><row><cell>1. Location of the Media Link Entry</cell></row><row><cell>2. Location of the original submission information package</cell></row><row><cell>3. Location of the fulltext</cell></row><row><cell>4. Location of the metadata</cell></row><row><cell>…</cell></row><row><cell>SWORD APP Profile v1.3 states:</cell></row><row><cell>Example:</cell></row><row><cell>HTTP/1.1 201 Created</cell></row><row><cell>Date: Mon, 18 August 2008 14:27:11 GMT</cell></row><row><cell>Content-Length: nnn</cell></row></table><note><p>Content-Type: application/atom+xml; charset="utf-8" Location: http://www.myrepository.org/geo/atom/my_deposit.atom</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Further information is available at the Max Planck Digital Library Wiki (see http://colab.mpdl.mpg.de/mediawiki/Peer:_Author_Deposit).</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Repository Task Force</head><p>The Repository Task Force has been successfully established with the following six participating repositories:</p><p>• PubMan, Max-Planck-Gesellschaft zur Förderung der Wissenschaften e.V. (MPG) http://dev-pubman.mpdl.mpg.de/pubman/ • HAL, Institut National de Recherche en Informatique et en Automatique (INRIA) Centre pour la Communication Scientifique Directe (CCSD/CNRS) http://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/ • Göttingen State and University Library (UGOE) http://repository.peerproject.eu:8080/jspui/ • BIPrints, Uni Bielefeld http://129.70.12.25/opus4/public/home • Kaunas University of Technology, Lithuania http://peer.elaba.lt/fedora/search • University Library of Debrecen, Hungary http://ganymedes.lib.unideb.hu:8080/udpeer/</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>However, since it is expected that authors may choose to respond immediately upon receipt of invitation to deposit, the invitation will be linked to the PEER Helpdesk website where authors are informed on their deposit options:</p><p>• For deposit to the PEER Depot, an online interface is established to guide authors through a simple deposit procedure (see Appendix D: Peer Author Deposit interface specification). In this case authors may provide their e-mail address for further contact by the PEER Depot upon successful deposit to participating repositories (see Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>). • When depositing to other repositories (not participating in PEER), authors are invited to provide the URL of the item location in the repository, their name and optionally, an e-mail address for later contacts by the PEER research team. Although we cannot determine how many authors deposit outside the PEER Depot, because authors may or may not declare their intent, any information gathered on alternative deposit may provide useful to the behavioural research.</p><p>The PEER Helpdesk additionally provides further information to authors on the PEER project itself; information on participating repositories or on the handling of the embargo period. Authors may also post their questions via the Trac 1 ticketing system to the PEER project support team.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>See Chapter 4: Ongoing support for publishers and repository managers</head><p>When depositing to the PEER Depot, the author receives two feedback messages:</p><p>1. Upon successful submission: A message is shown on the screen to notify the author that his/her submitted publication will be deposited in all PEER participating repositories 2 after the expiration of the embargo period. 2. Upon deposit to the participating repositories i.e. after the embargo period expires:</p><p>The PEER Depot will transfer the author submitted manuscript to all participating repositories. As the SWORD 3 protocol is used for this purpose, each repository confirms the accepted deposit by a message containing the URL which indicates the location of the article in the repository. The URLs from all repositories are collected and e-mailed to the author.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Author deposit workflow</head><p>Several scenarios for the author deposit workflow were considered (see Appendix E: Alternate author deposit workflow scenarios) before the definition of the final workflow for the author deposit. As outlined in the [DoW], [D2.1] and [D3.1], it was assumed that authors would deposit their stage-2 manuscripts directly to the repositories participating in PEER.</p><p>A problem was foreseen however in the fact that this assumption does not take into account the authentication of the author with the repositories during the deposit workflow (see Ch.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.3.1).</head><p>As most participating repositories do not allow for anonymous deposits, some authors might not be able to deposit in the repository of their choice, even if they wished to do so. Some repositories allow for registration directly via their repository interfaces, but those repositories based at a university, are restricted by the authentication based on the network and the IP address of the client. Therefore, separate authentication of authors not affiliated to the repository host organisation would have been necessary for all repositories. We insist that, except for 'publisher_article_id' and 'doi' which are used for linking both passes, there is no overlapping between the metadata sets of both passes. Metadata submitted twice will not be updated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix C. The SWORD protocol 1 Introduction</head><p>In the PEER project, selected stage-2 material from publishers is being transferred to or deposited into the PEER Depot after which the content is being transferred from the depot to multiple, publicly available repositories.</p><p>The stage-2 material will be transferred in a Submission Information Package (SIP) containing the full-text publication, metadata and the complementary stage-2 source files. The SWORD AtomPub profile contains specific features that allows for an application-level deposit of material into repositories.</p><p>The PEER information model can be mapped onto the OAIS Reference Model and the DRIVER object model for Enhanced Publications.</p><p>Implementers may set up their own server conforming to these guidelines using one of repository specific implementations available from SourceForge, or write their own custom implementation either using the generic Java library, also available from SourceForge, begin their implementation from scratch.</p><p>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119.</p><p>It is assumed that the reader of this document has knowledge of the PEER D2.1 report 1 , SWORD profile v1.3 2 , the OAIS 3 Reference Model 4 and the DRIVER 5 II Enhanced Publication object model and Functionalities 6 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">SWORD overview</head><p>The SWORD AtomPub Profile is an application profile of the Atom Publishing Protocol (APP) (RFC 5023) 7 that contains specific features that allows for an application-level deposit of material into repositories.</p><p>The APP is based on the HTTP transfer of Atom-formatted representations. It is easy to think of APP as a way of publishing just Atom Syndication Format feeds. While it is true that APP provides the means to publish Atom Syndication Format Entries to collections (such as blogs), it also provides a mechanism for the publishing of binary formatted data called Media Resources in APP context (Internet Engineering Task Force 2007). While in the blog scenario this mechanism may be used to add attachments to a blog post i.e. images, audio, video, documents), SWORD exploits this for the publishing (or deposit) of material into repositories, usually in some form of content packaging in which data and descriptive metadata are being held together in one container (see Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>). The SWORD profile offers the possibility to enumerate multiple packaging formats in the Service Document and supply a Quality Value attribute indicating a preference and level of support for a designated package format.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">Package support in Service Description</head><p>The server MAY support multiple packaging formats with varying quality values according to the support of the PEER Submission Information Package (SIP).</p><p>The server MUST support at least one package format with Quality Value "1.0", indicating full support where all components supplied within the SIP will be processed and understood when using the designated package format.</p><p>All supported formats MUST be listed in the Service Document.</p><p>All formats listed in the Service Document MUST have a Quality Value attribute assigned.</p><p>The value used in the &lt;sword:accepted Packaging&gt; element MUST NOT overload any values enumerated in the SWORD Content Package Types.</p><p>The server MAY use the &lt;sword:service&gt; element in the Service Document to indicate the existence of other service interfaces supporting additional package formats.</p><p>The server SHOULD NOT accept a specific package format across multiple interfaces with different levels of support as indicated by the Quality Value attribute in the Service Document.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">Package Support during Resource Creation</head><p>If a server receives a POST request with a format that is not listed as an accepted format in the Service Document, the server MUST reject the package by returning an HTTP status code of 415 (unsupported media type).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3">Package description in entry documents</head><p>When describing packaged resources in Media Entry documents, the server SHOULD add sword:packaging elements to the entry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Mediated Deposit</head><p>The following paragraph is considered informative, but is included for clarity in the use of the SWORD profile outside the PEER project.</p><p>The PEER workflow offers two ways a manuscript can be deposited into one of the publicly available PEER repositories: either by publisher deposit (through the PEER Depot) or by author deposit (where the publisher informs the author who deposits his/her article(s) via the depot interface /the PEER Depot at the actual publicly available repositories).</p><p>For the author deposit, the author MAY make the deposit by proxy through a web service (i.e. by filling in a form to provide the metadata and upload a file containing the full-text material) after which the web service is making the actual deposit. The web service MAY not be used for the PEER project exclusively in which case the web service MAY use its own credentials to authenticate at the server (at the repository side).   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Field Name Semantics Syntax</head><note type="other">Title</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary</head><p>Authors are invited to self-deposit publications to the PEER repositories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Actors</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corresponding author</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flow of Events</head><p>1. A user chooses to deposit his/her publication to the PEER Depot.</p><p>2. The user can enter basic metadata by using a webform (Note: journal name is provided from a list)</p><p>3. The user can upload a PDF file.</p><p>3.1. The system checks the file mimetype and gives an error message, if the file is not recognised as application/pdf.</p><p>4. The user needs to fill out a text shown on an image to avoid spamming (ReCAPTCHA 1 mechanism).</p><p>5. The user finalises the submission by submitting the form.</p><p>6. The webform performs a simple validation.</p><p>6.1. The webform content is validated successfully: 6.1.1. The system shows a confirmation message.</p><p>6.2. The webform content is validated unsuccessfully: 6.2.1. The system informs the user on missing/not populated mandatory fields, or wrong image recognition and asks the user to correct the entries and resubmit the form. The use case ends unsuccessfully.</p><p>7. The system packs the metadata and the PDF file into an archive and saves the content to a dedicated directory on the server (see Processing and Deposit of publications).</p><p>8. The use case ends successfully.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional information on depositing interface 2</head><p>• All data will be deposited to all participating repositories.</p><p>• The user must select the journal name from a predefined list of journals.</p><p>• Metadata will be provided in TEI-XML format.</p><p>• Deposit interface will pack the metadata and provided PDF file into an archive.</p><p>• The archived data will be posted to the Peer Depot via ftps 3 protocol. • Author selects a participating repository for deposit or enters an URL of additional/ alternative repository of choice. • Author accesses the participating repository's website.</p><p>• Author registers 1 at the repository in order to be able to make deposit. Authors, including those not affiliated to the repository host institution, are authorised for deposit. • Author deposits his/her data in the repository.</p><p>• Author receives a notification of successful deposit.</p><p>• Embargo management is handled by the repository.</p><p>• Repositories transfer their usage log files to the Usage Research Team.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Problems:</head><p>• Authors can be authenticated and authorised only if they access from the repository's host institution network (e.g. university network). • Embargo management requires automated matching process at repositories: match author submitted article with metadata from publishers (transferred by PEER Depot) and overwrite author's metadata with publisher's metadata. Elements of manual checking may occur (e.g. special characters). • Random deposit by non-PEER authors difficult to monitor, as there is no possibility to identify if potential deposits come by following a PEER invitation or not.</p><p>1</p><p>The author registration may vary from one repository to another e.g. sending an e-mail to the repository managers or fill-in a web form for requesting the privileges. For purpose of simplification of the workflow analysis these details are not further depicted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix F.</head><p>Current and planned practice in the provision of usage data in a participating repository PubMan@MPDL PubMan@MPDL (http://pubman.mpdl.mpg.de/pubman/) is a participating repository in the PEER repository task force. As it is primary importance to limit additional effort imposed upon participating repositories, PubMan@MPDL is well positioned to provide a sample of current practices against which the PEER specification for the provision of usage data can be measured.</p><p>The PubMan@MPDL supports scientists and institutes in the management and the digital curation of their publications. This solution addresses all disciplines and focuses on the target groups of scientists, local librarians and local IT. It is built as an eSciDoc solution (see http://escidoc.org) that focuses on publication management. PubMan is used at present by several early-adopter Max-Planck Institutes. It is anticipated be used by all institutes within the Max-Planck Society (MPG) and to replace the current eDoc publication repository of MPG.</p><p>PubMan@MPDL provides the log files in the format NCSA combined. The request contains the following information:</p><p>• Item identifier (escidoc:265993)</p><p>• File identifier (escidoc:265992)</p><p>• File name (PEER_stage2_10.1080_slash_00268970903078542.pdf)</p><p>• Session identifier (FC7627E3DED9E5F00E57C5861AC53A57)</p><p>Notes: Due to technical constraints, the file name has all slash symbols (coming from the DOI identifier) replaced with "_slash_" string. Due to privacy issues, the last three digits in the IP address of the request are be replaced with "XXX".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HAL@INRIA</head><p>HAL uses Apache and produces log files in the format NCSA combined.</p><p>BiPrints@UniBi http://repositories.ub.uni-bielefeld.de/biprints/ BiPrints uses APACHE and produces log files in the format NCSA combined. 66.249.66.5 --[12/Jan/2009:20:31:53 +0100] "GET /pdf_frontpage.php?source_opus =87&amp;startfile=Egelhaaf_et_al_UniForsch2002.pdf HTTP/1.1" 302 414 "-" "Mozilla/5. 0 (compatible; Googlebot/2.1; +http://www.google.com/bot.html)"</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Establishment of a Helpdesk .....................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">2.1 Helpdesk functions.............................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">2.2 Helpdesk Workflow ............................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Helpdesk for Publishers and</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Repository Managers ..........................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">2.4 Helpdesk for Authors .........................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Guidance for authors on deposit procedures</title>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Conclusions ...............................................................................................................................</orgName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>References</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A-1 ISO 19005-1: Document Management -Electronic document file format for long-term preservation -Part 1: Use of PDF 1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pdf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.pdfa.org" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<ptr target="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NLM Journal Publishing Tag Set</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.driver-support.eu/documents/DRIVER_Guidelines_v2_Final_2008-11-13.pdf" />
		<title level="m">DRIVER Guidelines</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.isni.org/" />
		<title level="m">International Standard Name Identifier</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.surffoundation.nl/smartsite.dws?ch=eng&amp;id=13480" />
		<title level="m">DigitalAuthorIdentification</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">PEER -Description of Work</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">PEER Steering Committee Meeting</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Frankfurt</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-11">Nov-2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">PEER Kick-Off Meeting</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Sophia-Antipolis</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-09-12">12-Sep-2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">PEER_stage2_[url-encoded-DOI].zip&quot; for publisher content and &quot;PEER_author_[url-encoded-DOI].zip&quot; for author content. There may be an additional mapping between the original PEER filename and the filename used in the repository</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>The filename will be</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Journal of Pragmatics 0378-2166 Social Sciences &amp; Humanities Journal of Theoretical Biology 0022-5193 Life Sciences Materials Science in Semiconductor Processing 1369-8001 Physical Sciences Nuclear Engineering and Design 0029-5493 Physical Sciences Radiotherapy and Oncology 0167-8140 Medicine Sociologie du Travail 0038-0296 Social Sciences &amp; Humanities French Solar Energy 0038-092X Physical Sciences Telecommunications Policy 0308-5961 Physical Sciences IOP Publishing Classical and Quantum Gravity 0264-9381 Physical Sciences Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical 1751-8113</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">PEER Technical Meeting</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-11-07">London 7-Nov-2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="268" to="3369" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Medicine</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The 0261-4189 Life Sciences</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Gene Therapy 0969-7128 Life Sciences</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>1466-4879 Life Sciences</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes &amp; Immunity</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Leukemia 0887-6924 Medicine 6 Nature Genetics 1061-4036 Life Sciences 6 Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology</title>
		<idno>1545-9993 Life Sciences 6 Oncogene 0950-9232 Life Sciences</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Sciences &amp; Humanities 6 Concurrent Engineering 1063-293X Physical Sciences Cultural Geographies 1474-4740 Social Sciences &amp; Humanities Ethnicities 1468-7968 Social Sciences &amp; Humanities European Journal of Cultural Studies 1367-5494 Social Sciences &amp; Humanities European Journal of Industrial Relations 0959-6801 Social Sciences &amp; Humanities Biochemical Pharmacology 0006-2952 Life Sciences Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) -Molecular Basis of Disease 0925-4439 Life Sciences Biophysical Chemistry 0301-4622 Physical Sciences Composites Science and Technology 0266-3538 Physical Sciences Computer Speech &amp; Language 0885-2308 Physical</title>
		<idno>Mechanics -A/Solids 0997-7538 Physical Sciences Experimental and Toxicologic Pathology 0940-2993 Life Sciences Experimental Gerontology 0531-5565 Medicine Human Movement Science 0167-9457 Life Sciences Icarus 0019-1035</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Sciences International Journal of Non-Linear Mechanics 0020-7462 Physical Sciences Journal of Econometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1350" to="9047" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Life Sciences</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Clinical Nutrition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="954" to="3007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Medicine</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>1018-4813 Life Sciences 6 Molecular Psychiatry 1359-4184 Medicine</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Human Genetics</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Medicine Journal of Clinical Ultrasound 0091-2751 Medicine Journal of Community and Applied Social Psychology 1052-9284 Social Sciences &amp; Humanities Journal of Medical Virology 0146-6615 Medicine Journal of Physical Organic Chemistry 0894-3230 Physical Sciences Molecular Microbiology 0950-382X Life Sciences Oral Diseases 1354-523X Medicine Pediatric Anesthesia 1155-5645 Medicine Pediatric Pulmonology 8755-6863 Medicine Phytotherapy Research 0951-418X Life Sciences Social Development 0961-205X Social Sciences &amp; Humanities ZAAC -Zeitschrift für anorganische und allgemeine Chemie / Journal of Inorganic and General Chemistry 0044-2313 Physical Sciences German / English &lt;entry</title>
		<idno>&lt;updated&gt;2008-08-18T14:27:08Z&lt;/updated&gt; &lt;author&gt;&lt;name&gt;jbloggs&lt;/name&gt;&lt;/author&gt; &lt;summary type=&quot;text&quot;&gt;A summary&lt;/summary&gt; ... &lt;content type=&quot;application/zip&quot; src=</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.myrepository.org/geo/atom/my_deposit.atom" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">&lt;title&gt;My Deposit&lt;/title&gt; &lt;id&gt;info:something:1&lt;/id&gt;</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1368" to="5031" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Haemophilia</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Server MUST use the correct MIME-type reference in the type attribute of the atom:content element in the Media Link Entry. The Media Link Entry MUST contain an atom:element with a src attribute containing the location of the fulltext. This is used in the feedback e-mail to the author. The Media Link Entry MAY contain an atom:element with a src attribute containing the location of the original submission information package, the raw metadata</title>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>ORE-ReM</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>jump-off page</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
