<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="fr">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">DARIAH: Advancing a digital revolution in the arts and humanities across Europe</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sally</forename><surname>Chambers</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">DARIAH: Advancing a digital revolution in the arts and humanities across Europe</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F3C0D35BC4F3AD62F3F153DC8906F798</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 4 Dec 2013</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access archive for the deposit and dissemination of scientific research documents, whether they are published or not. The documents may come from teaching and research institutions in France or abroad, or from public or private research centers. L'archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est destinée au dépôt et à la diffusion de documents scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="fr">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DARIAH: Advancing a digital revolution in the arts and humanities across Europe Laurent Romary and Sally Chambers (DARIAH-EU)</head><p>DARIAH, the Digital Research Infrastructure for the Arts and Humanities, is committed to advancing the digital revolution in the arts and humanities across Europe, by connecting resources and tools with the emerging next generation of digital scholars.</p><p>DARIAH, the Digital Research Infrastructure for the Arts and Humanities, is committed to advancing the digital revolution that has captured the arts and humanities. As more sources become digital, more digital content is being produced and more digital tools are being deployed, we see a next generation of digital scholars in the humanities emerge. DARIAH aims to connect these resources, tools and scholars, ensuring that the state-of-the art in research is sustained and integrated across European countries.</p><p>DARIAH works closely with research communities via our increasing network of affiliated projects. For example, with archaeologists (via ARIADNE, Advanced Research Infrastructure for Archaeological Data Networking in Europe), medieval and modern historians (via CENDARI, Collaborative European Digital Archive Infrastructure) and Holocaust researchers (via EHRI, European Holocaust Research Infrastructure). This collaboration fosters the production of digital reference material of all kinds (archival descriptions, transcription, annotated images, musical simulations, 3D models, etc.) and makes it essential to offer a data platform combining generic and specific hosting facilities.</p><p>Although some digital humanities projects such the TEI (Text Encoding Initiative) have already achieved a high-level of maturity and reach, beyond these pioneers, many new projects are funded where scholars need to collaborate and require help and support. It is important not to forget the wide majority of scholars with little or no background in digital methods. The vision for DARIAH is therefore to offer a portfolio of infrastructure orientated activities centred around research communities across the broad spectrum of the arts and humanities, no matter how far advanced they are in the digital revolution. http://www.dariah.eu/</p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
