<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D86F07A27F9FAD20F0BA68D55F30AE74</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Formulas, Tables, figures, graphics</term>
					<term>References Patents -Very formal</term>
					<term>Title/inventors/claims/abstract/ description</term>
					<term>Multilingualism (EPO)</term>
					<term>Formulas, Tables, figures, graphics Standards -Very formal</term>
					<term>Introduction/scope/terms and definitions/description/referen ces/annexes</term>
					<term>Formulas, Tables, figures, graphics</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Publications</head><p>-The essence of publishing • Importance of attribution • Reflects the context and time of the research (project, affiliation, biography) • The hidden hand of reviewers Patents -A variety of roles • Applicant/inventor/representati ve • Opponents • … and examiners Standards -Priority to the institution • Consensus building =&gt; large expert group • ISO: no authors but project leaders • W3C: editors Structure</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>• Necessity to put together an infrastructure for ingesting and delivering massive amount of scholarly papers</p><p>-Heterogeneous formats from publishers -Homogeneous delivery platform</p><p>The national Istex project The Istex document repository TEI as a pivot format for interchange  The (simplified) patent life-cycle</p><p>• Patent application in one or several patent offices -USPTO, Japan, EPO (directly or initiated in a specific country) -First application: reference date for the patent ("coming into force") -Form a "Patent family"</p><p>• Examination process for one application The situation so far</p><p>• Complete implementation in the back-office system -Integration of several so-far dispersed data-bases -First large-scale implementation of &lt;standOff&gt;</p><p>• Quite a few customisations -maintained in a reference ODD specification</p><p>-Re-use of TEI attributes at various places</p><p>• @type, @cert, @sortKey -Bibliographic references to patents</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">-Complex classification mechanism (&lt;classCodeGroup&gt;) -&lt;body&gt; in &lt;interp&gt; … -Let's &lt;party&gt;!</formula><p>• All in all a large scale demonstration of the TEI possibilities</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>WHY THE TEI?</head><p>Why the TEI, indeed?</p><p>• Two essential features -The very rich TEI vocabulary</p><p>• covers (nearly) all the features needed in a scientific information scenario -The huge customisation capabilities offered by the TEI architecture (modules, classes, ODD)</p><p>• Allows one to fine-tune models for highly constrained environments</p><p>• One more feature… -The short decision cycle of the TEI standardisation process</p><p>• "external" maintenance of most of the schema components and documentation -Towards "thin" specifications and documentations</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A vision for scientific information</head><p>• A family of formats within the TEI information space -Sharing common components in a stable environment -Comparison of information coverage thanks to the ODDs -Avoiding fragmentation</p><p>• The JATS, BITS syndrome, with the argument that "one size does not fit all" • There is no one size in the TEI, but a full-blown online catalogue…</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Strategy</head><p>-Pushing compliance as far as one can -Strong re-use of TEI components (attribute, elements, classes) -Push proposals to the TEI council as early as possible But life is not always easy…  -542: make &lt;occupation&gt; part of &lt;author&gt;</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">• Ambered!</formula><p>Expected example &lt;author&gt; &lt;persName&gt; &lt;forename type="first"&gt;Olivier&lt;/forename&gt; &lt;surname&gt;Le Deuff&lt;/surname&gt; &lt;/persName&gt; &lt;email&gt;oledeuff@gmail.com&lt;/email&gt; &lt;occupation&gt; &lt;p&gt;Docteur en sciences de l'information et de la communication, &lt;hi rend="bold"&gt;Olivier Le Deuff&lt;/hi&gt; a soutenu en 2009 une thèse sur &lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;La culture de l'information en reformation&lt;/hi&gt;. Il est chercheur au laboratoire PREFics (Plurilinguismes, Représentations, Expressions Francophones -information, communication, sociolinguistique), une composante du PRES Université européenne de Bretagne, Université Rennes 2. Il est également webmaster du Guide des égarés (&lt;ref target="#www.guidedesegares.info"/&gt;).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/occupation&gt; &lt;/author&gt; Is an author a person or a name?</p><p>• The content model of &lt;person&gt; would be an ideal candidate for &lt;author&gt; -E.g. &lt;occupation&gt; can be a child of &lt;person&gt;</p><p>• Still &lt;author&gt; does not have a clear-cut semantics</p><p>-"contains the name(s) of an author"</p><p>• "TEI Council subgroup unanimously believes that it is incorrect to put information inside &lt;author&gt; other than the author's name."</p><p>-So why a wrapper? Only to qualify the person as an author? -Why such an elaborate content model? -Where to put information attached to authors in a scientific information se case?</p><p>• "(Other information, like e-mail address and occupation, should be inside the &lt;bibl&gt; … that is, &lt;author&gt; is not a substitute for &lt;bibl&gt;, it contains only the name(s).)"</p><p>• &lt;author&gt; has been partially conceived in the perspective of the poor &lt;respStmt&gt;</p><p>The situation so far • Reflect a cultural tension</p><p>-"Any more prosopographical information should be stored in the standard TEI manner"</p><p>• What if we have other types of intervening parties?</p><p>inventor, applicant, examiner etc.</p><p>Towards a new element?</p><p>• &lt;party&gt; to replace &lt;respStmt&gt; with a more person-like component • Modelled upon &lt;author&gt; -Member of model.respLike -Content model: macro.phraseSeq?</p><p>• Seen as a generic element for other respLike objects -&lt;party role="author"&gt; = &lt;author&gt; -*rem. We need inheritance…+</p><p>• Already implemented in the EPO PDM model… -&lt;party type="inventor"&gt;&lt;/party&gt; A similar tension with &lt;abstract&gt; -"quite a major change"/"transgressive"/"very undesirable change"/"put it in the front"</p><p>• Hack with list, typed ab, etc.?</p><p>-Having &lt;div&gt; in the header is a total protonic reversal!</p><p>• Project: designing a div-like element specific to the header</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>THE RETURN OF TBX</head><p>TBX?</p><p>•   • att.global attribute class: @xml:id, @xml:lang, @xml:base, @xml:space • @target =&gt; att.pointing: making ID/IDREF be URI -Outdated element -Can be used to generate TBX compatible data univocally -Is probably the most optimal way the get DH colleagues to be acquainted with good terminological practices • And the customization can be customized! -Getting rid of unwanted TEI objects for TBX afficionados -Providing description of more complex data categories Towards a new chapter in the TEI guidelines? Or maintenance of an official customization?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A NEW MODEL FOR EMBEDDED STAND-OFF ANNOTATIONS</head><p>A long-standing issue </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>LanguagePublications-••••</head><label></label><figDesc>Semi-formal • Loose keywords, when any • Community of practices • Creativity is part of the publication process… Patents -Obfuscating • Achieving widest coverage and preventing retrieval Standards -Very formal • Central role of the terms and definitions section • Based on the principles of terminology Network Publications -Semi-formal • References pointing to previous publications in the same domain • Citation is an essential aspect of scholarly fame… Patents -Very formal • Citations in the application description • Citations as annotations from the examiner • Impact on acceptance or refusal Standards -Very formal • Section 2: normative references • Possible additional bibliographic section at the end Workflow Publications -Semi-formal • Traditional (vestigial?) concept of peer-review • From author's initial manuscript to publisher's version • Evolution in the role of each version (e.g. prior art) Patents -Very formal • Review by patent examiners • Coordination of multiple submissions: national, US, Europe, etc. • Importance of initial submission date Standards -Very formal • Decision process reflecting membership structure • ISO: WD, CD, DIS, FDIS, IS • One single reference document An infrastructure for scholarship -Open dissemination of scholarly papers -Metadata and documents • An attempt to counter-balance the hegemony of private publishers -Cf. Green open access • An essential tool for assessment and strategic planning -E.g. H2020 open access policy HAL -the French national repository • Developed and maintained at CCSD, Lyon • Offers portals to various higher education and research institutions -E.g. HAL-Inria portal • Accompanied by incentive measures -E.g. Inria's deposit mandate The TEI as an in-depth metadata format -Going beyond the standard Dublin Core representations available in OAI-PMH interfaces -Recording precise data for scientific information (affiliations, licences, etc.) Preparing for an extension to full-text management -PDF 2 TEI (Grobid) -Re-publication framework (HTML, ePub) Big deals and national licences -Global negotiation frameworks for journal subscriptions -Additional requirements concerning archival and reuse (text and data mining)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>-</head><label></label><figDesc>Search report, communications, decision, appeal, opposition -Patent documents may be revised at each stage • Necessity to have a single model for dealing with all stages and versions • Again, the TEI appeared to be the optimal</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>•-</head><label></label><figDesc>Idno Required a series of ticket (since 2008) • Make it an identifier, not a number • Allow it in &lt;author&gt; (and aligning &lt;person&gt; :-}) • Affiliation -Already there, and you can put quite a lot in it… Going further -Allowing biographies • Biographies are a standard component of author descriptions in scholarly publication -They may change heavily in size and content within a corpus of publication -They may range from a simple text to a structured content• Two tickets in place -543: make the content of &lt;occupation&gt; more structured• Easy…</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Term Base eXchange • Implement an onomasiological model for lexical data -Concept to term • Published as an ISO standard (ISO 30042, building upon ISO 16642) • A long time ago in another galaxy… -Was initiated within the TEI guidelines • Bringing it back to the TEI is more than a cool thing to do -But a nice ODD exercise and a nightmare for the council… TEI and onomasiological representations • ISO 6156:1987 (Mater) • 1989: Setting up the TEI • Specific chapter of the TEI guidelines dedicated to the representation of terminological data • The SGML-based representation integrated in the TEI framework remained there until the P4 edition • ISO 12200 (Martif): 1999, improves the TEI proposal (bracketing), but breaks the link to the TEI by going ISO • document structure strongly inspired from the TEI (e.g. the header-text organisation; entries embedded within a &lt;text&gt; and &lt;body&gt; hierarchy); • reaching out to the translation and localisation industry • 1999-2003: Abstracting away • ISO 12620:1999: data categories and ISO 16642 (TMF): 2003, meta-model • Basic for the specification of a variety of terminological formats • ISO 30042:2008 TBX (TermBase eXchange) , after work carried out in LISA • Current: TBX-Basic, TBX-Min … Conceptual Principles</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>••</head><label></label><figDesc>Addressing a new (?) user community: digital humanists -Importance of primary sources and construction of secondary digital objects (annotations, indexes, etc.) -Onomasiological sources in field linguistics • Taking the best from the onomasiological work in the last 40 years -Avoiding simplistic representations such as SKOS and thesaurus standards • Fostering more convergence in standardization -Favoring reuse of components from various standardization worlds • But do we have any kind of histocompatibility? Tissue typing • Host: the TEI document structure -Terminological entries can occur at many places • Specific section, inline, between other TEI elements -As far as building up a terminological database in TEI • E.g. recording bilingual philosophical vocabulary from Wittgenstein's works -Keeping all inline annotation facilities for textual fields • Names, dates, foreign expressions, notes, pointers, feature structures… -Improved documentation with the rich TEI header • Important from a scholarly perspective • Graft: a TBX-like terminological entry -Structural skeleton • Inspired from TBX-Basic (DCA style) • Note that TBX already has an ODD spec! -Data categories• Initially reduced to a very small number of meaningful categories for a DH scenario • subjectField, definition, source, partOfSpeech, grammaticalGender, etc. • In particular: no project management data categories Ensuring the graft by means of namespaces • Incompatible tissues -Attributes</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>&lt;tbx:xref&gt; (cf. URI mechanism) -TEI elements in their own namespace • &lt;tei:term&gt; • &lt;tei:hi&gt;: bringing the semantic back on tracks • &lt;tei:ref&gt;, &lt;tei:ptr&gt;, &lt;tei:note&gt; • Second life -Rich textual content model The patient after surgery &lt;termEntry xmlns="http://www.tbx.org"&gt; &lt;descrip type="subjectField" xml:lang="fr"&gt;Industrie mécanique&lt;/descrip&gt; &lt;langSet xml:lang="de"&gt; &lt;descripGrp&gt; &lt;descrip type="definition"&gt;endloser Riemen …&lt;/descrip&gt; &lt;admin type="source"&gt;De Coster, Wörterbuch, …&lt;/admin&gt; &lt;/descripGrp&gt; &lt;tei:note&gt;wird zum Antrieb der Lichtmaschine, des Ventilators …&lt;/tei:note&gt; &lt;tig&gt; &lt;tei:term&gt;Keilriemen&lt;/tei:term&gt; &lt;admin type="source"&gt;De Coster, …&lt;/admin&gt; &lt;/tig&gt; &lt;/langSet&gt; &lt;langSet xml:lang="fr"&gt;… &lt;/langSet&gt; &lt;/termEntry&gt;A chimera?• TBX@TEI is not a proper subset of TBX -Document structure -Changes in the content model of &lt;termEntry&gt; • Still:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>••-•</head><label></label><figDesc>Stand-off annotation has been a core concept in the TEI guidelines since the beginning -Cf. Chapter: Linking, Segmentation, and Alignment • But: not integrated in the TEI architecture -Stand-off elements can appear anywhere in a TEI document -Trade-off between on-site vs. grouping (&lt;back&gt;) • Plus: An old conflict with the NLP community • Need for a proper, and inclusive, treatment of stand-off annotations Basic concept Building up an autonomous document containing primary source and additional annotations Annotations are conveyed with their specific meta-data -Stand-off annotations may be recursively organized -Stand-off annotations may point to textual as well as facsimile content -Coherence with existing models (Open Annotation, ISO TC 37) should be ensured • Typical use-cases -Human annotations on a document • critical editions, patent examination, open peer review • Internal prosopography, entities at large -Text mining • Named entity recognition, keyword/terms extraction August 2012: new tickets by Javier Pose (EPO) • January 2014: Workshop in Berlin -Draft of a first proposal -Setting-up a github environment • May 2015: Council meeting in Ann Arbor -Several updates to the proposal The Open Annotation model -TEI (possible) implementation annotation body target &lt;span type="" from="" to=""&gt;Any TEI object (with @xml:id) or &lt;surface&gt; &lt;bibl&gt;, &lt;person&gt;, &lt;place&gt;, &lt;fs&gt;, &lt;note&gt;, &lt;body&gt;, MAF, SynAF &lt;interp type="" inst="" ana="corresp="#_theSurface" ulx="1253" uly="802" lrx="22" lry="29"/related to the annotation, such as annotator, revisions of the annotations,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="21,0.00,148.81,720.00,344.78" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="43,176.49,-0.00,538.41,540.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>SCENARIO 3 -MANAGING THE BACK-OFFICE OF THE EPO</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>The European Patent Office</cell></row><row><cell>• General strategy: no information should be lost • The European one-stop shop for patent -Nearly everything in sourceDesc applications -+ Keywords, Summary, Copyright • Examination of each application by experts from • Strict author description -Deep encoding of names the field (examiners)</cell></row><row><cell>-Deep encoding of affiliations (Web of Science -3-level) -Based on existing patents as well as scholarly -Deep encoding of addresses -getting the country right • Precise publishing information publications (aka Non Patent Literature)</cell></row><row><cell>-Pagination, DOIs, volume, issue, journals name(s)</cell></row><row><cell>-Yes, biblStruct is cool!</cell></row><row><cell>• Necessity of constantly adapting the target model</cell></row><row><cell>-(That's why JATS sucks, if you ask)</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>availability</head><p>Recursive construct: allows the organisation of annotations par method, annotator, campaign</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>standOff -main components</head><p>• listAnnotation -a double semantics -Equivalent to &lt;text&gt; in TEI document -Groups elementary annotation chunks</p><p>• span -business as usual -Identifies a markable within the full-text of the document -Need to improve guidance about the use of pointers</p><p>• interp -extended usage -Attributes</p><p>• @type: provides the type of the annotation -Cf. @type on the parent standOff element</p><p>• @resp: the entity who is responsible for this annotation • @inst: lists the components (span or surface) to be annotated • @ana: points to annotation content (body in OA speak) Application: interlinear annotation</p><p>• Encoding interlinear annotation as inline content (in &lt;text&gt;) &lt;listAnnotation who="#SPK0" start="#T9" end="#T12" xml:id="au1"&gt; &lt;u xml:id="u1"&gt; &lt;seg xml:id="seg45" type="utterance" subtype="declarative"&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w43"&gt;Nee&lt;/w&gt; &lt;pc xml:id="pc3"&gt;,&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w44"&gt;hab&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w45"&gt;kein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w46"&gt;Führerschein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;/seg&gt; &lt;/u&gt; &lt;spanGrp type="en"&gt; &lt;span from="#T9" to="#T12"&gt;No, I don't have a driver's license.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;spanGrp type="pos"&gt; &lt;span from="#w43" to="#w43"&gt;NE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#pc3" to="#pc3"&gt;$,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w44" to="#w44"&gt;VAIMP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w45" to="#w45"&gt;PIAT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w46" to="#w46"&gt;NN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;/listAnnotation&gt; Many thanks to Thomas Schmidt! ISO CD 24624 -Transcription of Spoken Language Application: interlinear annotation</p><p>• Encoding interlinear annotation as stand-off markup -In &lt;standOff&gt; &lt;listAnnotation corresp="#u1"&gt; &lt;spanGrp xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="en"&gt; &lt;span from="#T9" to="#T12"&gt;No, I don't have a driver's license.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;spanGrp xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="pos"&gt; &lt;span from="#w43" to="#w43"&gt;NE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#pc3" to="#pc3"&gt;$,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w44" to="#w44"&gt;VAIMP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w45" to="#w45"&gt;PIAT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w46" to="#w46"&gt;NN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;/listAnnotation&gt; -In &lt;body&gt; &lt;u xml:id="u1" who="#SPK0" start="#T9" end="#T12"&gt; &lt;seg xml:id="seg45" type="utterance" subtype="declarative"&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w43"&gt;Nee&lt;/w&gt;&lt;pc xml:id="pc3"&gt;,&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w44"&gt;hab&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w45"&gt;kein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w46"&gt;Führerschein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;/seg&gt; &lt;/u&gt; Issues (many)</p><p>• Which header do we need?</p><p>-Standoff annotation requires very specific meta-data -If we adopt the TEI header, we need to make it more flexible…</p><p>• Should we have a convergence with biblFull (where profileDesc is missed, BTW, SF:533, deeply ambered)</p><p>-Stand-off annotations may be generated by humans and machines</p><p>• how to put &lt;author&gt; (editionStmt) and &lt;appInfo&gt; (encodingDesc) at the same place?</p><p>• How do we provide guidance concerning annotations?</p><p>-Mapping the OA model to precise TEI constructs? -Allowing a wide variety of possible vocabularies depending on the use case?</p><p>• TBX entries, MathML, full-text annotation (&lt;body&gt;?)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>WHERE DO WE GO FROM HERE?</head><p>Reflecting on our practices</p><p>• Cf. missed opportunities -ISO could have gone TEI, we could have prevented JATS to occur, and yes the Computational linguistic community should have been in since ages…</p><p>• Going for more inclusiveness -Avoiding fragmentation -the TEI should not fork too much -Be ready to adapt (note: none of the proposed changes are backward incompatible…)</p><p>• Evolutions at the benefit of everyone -Convergence between primary and secondary sources</p><p>• Organisational point of view -Shall we acknowledge external vocabularies as part of the TEI architecture? -Shall we host external document types in the TEI framework? -Shall we go towards sub-committee in the TEI technical council? -How do we maintain global coherence?</p><p>• A strategy of anticipation?</p><p>• [Gabriel Bodard] Just to note, Carrie, that this has already been implemented in the latest EpiDoc release (try validating against http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/te i-epidoc.rng and see if it works for you), in anticipation of forthcoming TEI compliance...</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
