<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="fr">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Open Access in Japan -a multi-institutional perspective</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jos</forename><surname>Baeten</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Ambassade de France au Japon</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2016. hal-01290936</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Ambassade de France au Japon</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2016. hal-01290936</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Pascal</forename><surname>Estraillier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Ambassade de France au Japon</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2016. hal-01290936</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Ambassade de France au Japon</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2016. hal-01290936</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Claude</forename><surname>Kirchner</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Ambassade de France au Japon</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2016. hal-01290936</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Ambassade de France au Japon</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2016. hal-01290936</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexandre</forename><surname>Moatti</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Ambassade de France au Japon</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2016. hal-01290936</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Ambassade de France au Japon</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2016. hal-01290936</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Ambassade de France au Japon</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2016. hal-01290936</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Open Access in Japan -a multi-institutional perspective</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D8079215BB001FA77B96C5B166D4F07E</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 19 Mar 2016 Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution| 4.0 International License</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access archive for the deposit and dissemination of scientific research documents, whether they are published or not. The documents may come from teaching and research institutions in France or abroad, or from public or private research centers. L'archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est destinée au dépôt et à la diffusion de documents scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="fr">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Open Access in Japan -a multiinstitutional perspective</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scientific information and open access -an introduction and an overview of the context in France and Europe</head><p>The wide dissemination of research results is an essential component of a prosperous development of science and technology. The legacy of the scientific publishing landscape, created in the print era, as well as the prospect that the wide deployment of information technologies may lead to a simplified dissemination of research assets, have made necessary for researchers, libraries and all institutions involved in higher education and research to contribute to an in-depth evolution of the scientific communication processes.</p><p>Without drawing a complete history of the open access movement here, we can identify some major milestones, which have lead to the current situation:  Dramatic increase in journal subscription costs in the 90"s (so called "serial crisis");  Setting of the first publication repositories with arXiv in 1994, following several year of pioneering dissemination of digital papers on ftp sites, mailing lists etc.;  Emergence of the Open Access movement stating that scientific content, seen as a public good, should be freely accessible and re-used. We can mention here the Berlin declaration issued in 2004 and signed by many scientific organisations worldwide<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">2</ref> :  Further deployment of institutional, thematic or national repositories worldwide (see <ref type="bibr">Romary &amp;Armbruster, 2006)</ref> contributing to the expansion socalled green Open Access<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">3</ref> :  Rise of new publishing models based on the payment by authors of an Article Processing Charge (APC) in order to make the paper available online at the time of publication (part of what is named gold Open Access<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">4</ref> ).</p><p>Behind the notion of public good, we can also mention the importance of scientific, institutional or national sovereignty, whereby publicly funded research should lead to productions that remain within the remits of their producers. This has direct consequences at various levels: preservation of authors" copyright, setting up reliable infrastructures, defining publication cots in accordance to clear services provided by third parties (as opposed to the current non-competitive publication market), with the objective of increasing the capacity of public actor carry out their assessment or strategic planning duties in full independence <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">5</ref> .</p><p>In Europe, despite isolated attempts to favour the publishing business <ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">6</ref> , green open access has taken up strongly and in particular France has developed a national Some institutions such as Inria or CWI have managed to go even further by mandating researchers to deposit publications within their repositories. Such mandates are usually linked to annual assessment, whereby the papers in the repositories are taken as the sole source for reporting by researchers or research teams.</p><p>Initiatives are also taking place to develop new publishing models that decouple the notion of publication, understood as the dissemination of the content publicly online, from the peer-reviewing process. We can mention here the Episciences initiative <ref type="bibr">(See Berthaud et al. 2014)</ref> in France that offers an environment for implementing so-called overlay journals on top of existing publication repositories.</p><p>Open access is also one element in global reshaping of the dissemination of research results from a wider perceptive. The issue has for instance been high up on the political agenda of the G8, with its Open Data charter 8 , and the underlying copyright issues (re-usability, for instance for text and data mining) is an essential component of the European Union copyright reform 9 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Main objectives</head><p>The main objectives for the European delegation during this series of meeting were the following ones:</p><p> Understand the situation of open access in Japan, in particular to identify factors for change in this domain;  Compare the main issues in Japan with the political and technical settings in France and at CWI;  Identify some possible collaboration themes that would allow our countries to develop better and stronger open access policies in the future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contextual information</head><p>The Japanese academic landscape is based upon a large group of 774 universities (86 national universities, 83 public universities and a majority of 605 private universities). At a political level, three main institutions are in charge of the higher education and research policies: MEXT: Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology) and two funding agencies: JST: Japan Science and Technology Agency and JSPS: Japan Society for the Promotion of Science.</p><p>The stay was organised in two complementary types of meetings:</p><p> series of discussions with institutional actors, among which Prof.Harayama, the above-mentioned institutions and the NII management;  workshops dedicated to specific communities of interest and stakeholders.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CSTI (Council for Science, Technology and Innovation)</head><p>Yuko Harayama is an Executive Member of the CSTI at the Cabinet Office. The CSTI has been seminal in producing an important report in March 2015 aiming at defining a national policy in the domain of open access to scientific result. In this context our delegation had the opportunity to exchange some core ideas with Prof.Harayama. The main topics addressed during this meeting were the following one:</p><p> Importance of scientific sovereignty and to define ways of mastering the dissemination of scholarly result;  The possibility to go towards a more pro-active policy in the domain of scientific article deposit in publication repositories, taking the examples of the ambitious deposit mandate policies of Inria and CWI;  The necessity to experiment new scientific publishing models based on public platforms;  International collaboration between Japan and Europe in the above-mentioned themes.</p><p>MEXT (Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology)</p><p>"MEXT has started to work with JST to introduce mandatory rule for scientists to publish their papers and data sets open accessible attached to public funds. "</p><p>In particular, MEXT originated an open access mandate for all PhD theses in Japan in March 2013 through the institutional repository of the PhD awarding institution.</p><p>From an infrastructural point of view, MEXT finances the technical support provided by NII concerning scientific publication platform and in particular the work carried out on journal management environments and publication repositories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>JSPS (Japan Society for the Promotion of Science)</head><p>There are 3 funding agencies in total in Japan, two under the auspices of the Ministry of Higher Education and Research (MEXT): JSPS and JST, one under the auspices of the Ministry of Industry (MITI): NEDO. Among the three the JSPS, established in 1932, represents the biggest one with a budget of around 2 billion Euros per year.</p><p>The meeting took place in presence of MakotoAsashima, executive director of JSPS, and was the opportunity to have an in-depth discussion on open access issues in relation to the forthcoming report by CISTI due in March 2015.</p><p>In the domain of scientific information and open access, the JSPS has had several programs to encourage the move of scholarly society journals from print to electronic, as well as specific support for gold open access publication. It should be noted that current plans do not integrate any specific support for green open access.</p><p>A specific discussion took place concerning the opportunity to better coordinate open access issues within the GRC (Global Research Council). G8, ANR</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>JST (Japan Science and Technology Agency)</head><p>JST provided us a series of questions that served as a basis of discussions and allowed us to better understand their current topics of interest. We provide specific details about the corresponding interaction.</p><p>A specific debate took place during the meeting on the compatibility between the development of open access journal and the role of depositing papers in publication repositories. A consensus actually emerged to understand that the necessity of mandating deposit in public repositories remains when papers are being published within open access journals, in order to ensure that a reference corpus of scientific publications be maintained by governmental institutions. The debate also addressed to related aspects:</p><p> The role of publication repositories for the early (pre-peer review) dissemination of scholarly manuscripts, with the possibility of both getting quick and efficient community feedback on scientific results, but also to take precedence since such manuscripts can serve, for instance, as prior art during patent examination. In the case of papers that are not further published (or refused) in traditional journals, it appears that keeping these records are essential to maintain a rich scholarly background for future research;  The danger of (probably ephemeral) private platforms such as Academia or Research Gate offering hosting services for scholarly papers and which bring in the risk of even more fragmentation of our scientific assets. For countries like Japan (with Jairo cloud) or France (with HAL) where there exist a national publication repository strategy, a stronger information campaign should deter scientists from using such platforms to record their productions.</p><p>JST expressed their interest in stronger collaboration schemes between Japan and Europe on publication platforms and supported the idea that specific links with the developments carried out within NII should be established.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>NII (National Institute of Informatics)</head><p>Beyond its core mission as a research institution in the domain of computer science (with 80 permanent researchers), NII plays a central role in the Japanese scientific information landscape since it is in charge of implementing and operating the main national information infrastructures for universities in Japan. If we were to compare to the French situation, it groups together missions that are spread across ABES (central catalogue), CCSD (national repository HAL), Persée (digitisation of scholarly journals in human sciences) and INIST (provision of subscribed content).</p><p>An early program initiated between 2004 and 2007 provided initial support for the implementation of institutional repositories within up to 70 universities:</p><p> NII-ELS is a platform dedicated to the online delivery of digitized legacy journals from scholarly societies in Japan (thus close to the scope of Persée). It hosts the content of 109 journals but does not really offer the service of a publication platform. It seems the content is about to move to J-stage;  JAIRO Cloud is a centralized digital research object repository, allowing not only universities to implement publication portals within it, but also offering research data archiving and publication facilities.</p><p>Besides, NII provides targeted services concerning publishers" copyright policies (SCPL -Society Copyright Policies in Japan, similar to SHERPA/ROMEO) or assessment of repository downloads (ROAT -Repository Output Assessment Tool).</p><p>We consider NII as a model for future scientific information infrastructure where technical support is strongly coupled with research activities (for instance in the domain of text and data mining or visualisation).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Library and information science workshop</head><p>The workshop provided a comprehensive overview of the situation in various (public and private) universities in Japan as well as an overview of the current organisational and technical issues at a national level.</p><p>There are as a whole 1486 University libraries (289 national, 129 public and 1068 private) in the academic sector. From an organisational point of view, several consortia are relevant for the management of scientific information in Japanese universities:</p><p> JCCUL, Japanese Coordinating Committee for University Libraries. It has signed in 2010 an agreement with NII in scientific information for the higher academic sector;  JUSTICE (Japan Alliance of University Library Consortia for E-Resources) is the equivalent organisation to Couperin 10 in France in that it is in charge of the negotiations with publishers, with the difference that its activities do not comprise the setting up of centralised subscription consortia ("groupement de commande" for Couperin). JUSTICE currently has a membership of 516 libraries in close collaboration with the NII;  DRF (Digital Repository Federation) groups together institutional repository initiatives (150 members). DRF is a member organisation to COAR (Confederation of Open Access Repositories). This structure seems to evolve into the Institutional Repository Promotion Committee, set in 2013 between NII and university libraries;  Finally, SCREAL Standing committee for research in academic libraries.</p><p>The Japanese libraries have altogether the quite large budget of 21 831 million Yens dedicated to subscriptions with a total number of 4970 journal titles. The recent drop of the Yen exchange rate, coupled with an increased VAT applied to subscriptions and a global reduction in University library budget dramatically impacts on the capacity to keep to this budget. The current consequence is a tendency to abandon the big deal model in favour of the identification of relevant title portfolio within each university.</p><p>The institutional repository (IR) landscape was until now extremely fragmented with a large network of 370 university repositories that has steadily (hita-hita, cf. Tsuchide et alii, 2013) increased over the years. They are mainly operated by the university libraries and comprise an impressive number of items (1 400 000) as of 2014. NII has played strong role in this development by first supporting several university repository projects and recently by offering a centralised repository service (JAIROcloud) where Universities can develop their own portal, in a setting which is quite equivalent with what we have in France with HAL<ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">11</ref> . Most of the institutional repositories have a "everything welcome policy" (for instance in Chiba), whereby the aim of the platform is to host all types of scholarly productions, comprising reports, grey literature at large, theses, wide public articles, posters etc. in complement to research article in the narrow sense of the term.</p><p>University bulletins (or Kiyo), mainly in the social and human sciences domain, represent a majority of the content of these institutional repositories<ref type="foot" target="#foot_7">12</ref> . This reflects the fact that IRs are not seen as a tool for providing open access to otherwise published material but more of a document repository for locally generated documents (texts or data). The deposit mandate on PhD thesis can be also seen from this perspective.</p><p>Universities begin to have difficulties in keeping their maintenance budget for their local institutional repositories, which may lead to a step-by-step switch to JAIRO. Beyond the budget aspects we see numerous advantages to this, based on our experience with HAL: coherent meta-data description, connection to national authority files, quicker take up of new technologies (e.g. visualisation and data mining) and better connection with international initiatives (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Romary and Armbruster, 2010</ref>; https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00399881).</p><p>As a general conclusion, we have observed a strong independence of each university, with in general a low political support to institutional repositories at University management level. Institutional repository contents are also very heterogeneous, and it is hardly foreseeable that Universities will issue OA mandates in the future, not even strong requirements. Of course the national request made for PhD theses ensures at least that most of them are available in the repositories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Researchers' workshop</head><p>Several projects and institutions were presented, and a broad exchange of views took place about these projects, that were either in the field of exact sciences as well as human sciences (in particular: digital humanities). Among the latter, we can cite the projects of the Japanese Association of Indian and Buddhist Studies<ref type="foot" target="#foot_8">13</ref> , the Japanese Association for Digital Humanities (www.jadh.org), the Japanese Association for Religious Studies (www.jpars.org), or the Research Institute for Sustainable Humanosphere, Kyoto University (http://www.rish.kyoto-u.ac.jp/), or the Digital Silk Road Project, one of the pioneers (http://dsr.nii.ac.jp , since 2001).</p><p>The National Diet Library, responsible in Japan for legal deposit of books and reviews, presented also its projects; in France, it is not the Diet Library but the BibliothèqueNationale de France which is in charge of legal deposit 14 . The questions of legal deposit of the Web sites (that is implemented in France by a law of 2007), as well as the legal deposit under electronic format (which is a different question, not available in France) have been discussed.</p><p>The question of research data (scientific "big data") has also been raised; the Japanese delegation gave the interesting example of the preservation of records for unique scientific phenomenon, like eclipses or big earthquakes. This is part of Japanese implication in the international Research Data Alliance (www.rdalliance.org).Japan Science and Technology Agency (JST) curates data centres in several scientific realms, dedicated to this mission of research data preservation.</p><p>Several points arose during the discussion between the French delegation and the Japanese institutes, among which:  The possibility of having digital humanities projects better known by a larger public, for example through Wikipedia (systematically indexing these projects on the related Wikipedia pages; in the other way, also releasing iconography from research institutes for Wikipedia pages).  The possibility of associating a larger public to some digital projects: for example transcription of historical manuscripts by internet users; or "participative science" (in botanic, in astronomy, etc.) where scientific data coming from non-researchers is aggregated to complement and enrich research data as well as programs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contextual analysis</head><p>For many years, the favourable exchange rate between the Yen and the Dollar, in which most subscription contracts were set up, has attenuated the effects of the serial crisis in Japan and created a feeling of wealth with regards the private scholarly publishing sector. This has resulted in the negotiation of numerous big deals between Japan academia and publishers and also a particularly strong dedication to the newly introduced Gold open access model, as compared to what has been experienced in Europe. The recent devaluation of the Yen, coupled with an increase of the VAT rate on foreign products has completely changed the perspective on publishing cost and the actual role of private publishing in the dissemination of scientific information.</p><p>The Tōhoku earthquake and tsunami in 2011 has also had an important impact on the role of the government and governmental agencies with regards scientific research.</p><p>Whereas most of the national institutes for instance were quite autonomous in defining their research priorities, the dramatic consequences of the tsunami has awaken the Japanese authorities to the necessity to define strong research priorities in such domains as energy, environment or information technology. This in turn has created a favourable background for a stronger national policy in the scientific information domain.</p><p>From an academic point of view, the development of scientific information policies in Japan have been subordinated to three main important factors:</p><p> The fragmentation of the university landscape with 774 universities as a whole and the importance of the private sector (605 private universities as opposed to 86 national and 83 public universities);  The central role of scientific societies, which have maintained a specific portfolio of scientific journals. This has induced specific initiatives towards the corresponding publishing sector, for instance in terms of publication platforms;  A strong autonomy of Japanese universities, and within them of Professors, which lies at the root of the current fragmentation of the publication repository landscape so far, but also slowed down various initiatives towards more concerted actions in the open access domain.</p><p>In the recent years, Japan has seen a dramatic growth in the number of open access repositories within its universities and research organisations. With 388 repositories, which reflect the fragmented academic landscape in Japan, there are currently great discrepancies in actual coverage, technical developments and prospect for sustainability across these platforms 15 . Another important issue is the reduced coverage of these repositories in terms of real scientific publications (around 15% of journal 16 articles). Kiyos (departmental bulletins) represent more than a half of the content, with also an increasing importance of PhD theses (4,4%) thanks to the national deposit mandate. The PhD mandate, which explicitly refers to the IR of the awarding institution has also contributed to the fragmentation of the landscape: no specific national service has been set in place, as is the case in France with STAR and TEL<ref type="foot" target="#foot_10">17</ref> , and the European portal DART<ref type="foot" target="#foot_11">18</ref> .</p><p>The relation to commercial publishers is very specific in Japan with a very high budget that seems to reflect that commercial publishers have tend to see Japan as a "Poule aux oeufsd"or"<ref type="foot" target="#foot_12">19</ref> : 260 M€ (to compare to the subscription budget in France: 80 M€), which has also been amplified by a strong Gold open access policy. One factor here is the central role for national journals with two additional issues:</p><p> The specific language issue, whereby gold open access and often associated with the need of advanced copy-editing in English;  The absence of a real policy for new quality assessment factors, with the journal citation index remaining a major reference in Japan; </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions -Perspectives</head><p>Over the week"s discussions that took place between Japanese and European colleagues, it has become clear that there is a need to a closer collaboration between us all in order to go towards a more ambitious scientific information policy that would favour the open access dissemination of both publications and data. In particular, very similar views have been shared concerning the need to take over again the sovereignty over scientific information, and consequently identify public policies and infrastructures that would ensure that the scientific common good is not exclusively given away to the private sector. The objective is both to be able to provide a better dissemination of scientific results, but also to offer the possibility to implement new services (indicators, data mining) based upon a comprehensive pool of scientific content.</p><p>Several concrete domains have been identified, which could be the basis of future collaborations:</p><p> Sharing our principles and the way we communicate towards scientific communities. In particular, we need to have a better coordination of our information concerning the risks of gold open access;  Compare our technical developments. It has become clear for instance that NII and Inria have a very similar role in their being at the intersection of computer science research and scientific information services development.  Creating better communication channels between our institutions and in particular our library networks (Couperin in France, JUSTICE in Japan) about the various negotiations and agreements that are taking place with private publishers, concerning: subscription deals, gold open access deals and specific licencing agreements (re-use and data mining). This could lead to the identification of bilateral coordination when facing major hurdles in future negotiations;  Developing strategies to strengthen the role of digital librarians and data scientist with the perspective to increase the sustainability and re-use of the digital scientific content that will be produced in the future. The importance of such new professional profiles has been identified by both sides as crucial to scientific information policies in the digital world;  Coordinate the evolution of the copyright legal landscape in order to favour access and re-use of scientific content;</p><p>There are clearly lessons to learn for the French scholarly landscape. The Japanese example tells us in particular the danger of having a fragmented publication repository landscape and French Universities such as Strasbourg or Bordeaux should look at the consequences of developing and maintain their own platforms. From a political point of view, the deposit mandates of Inria and CWI have clearly been seen as examples that should followed step by step (hita-hita again…) by various university libraries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants au premier workshop (28 Janvier 2015)</head><p>Crédit photo : Ambassade de France au Japon Une délégation réunissant des experts français dans le domaine de l"Open Access, sujet clé à l"échelle mondiale pour le monde de la recherche, a été invitée par le Service pour la Science et la Technologie à venir au Japon du 27 au 30 Janvier 2015. Cette mission visait à rencontrer l"ensemble des parties prenantes pour faire un point complet sur la situation au Japon en matière d"Open Access et d"envisager de possibles collaborations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>L'Open Access -un nouveau modèle pour la recherche scientifique mondiale</head><p>L"Open Access ou « Libre Accès » consiste en la mise à disposition immédiate, gratuite et permanente sur Internet des publications scientifiques issues de la recherche et de l"enseignement. Ce mouvement, initié dans les années 90, a pris de l"ampleur ces dernières années face au pouvoir de pression grandissant des éditeurs de revues scientifiques et leur mainmise sur les données, soulevant des questions sur la souveraineté numérique des pays.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Renforcer la coopération franco-japonaise</head><p>La délégation française, coordonnée par l"Inria (Institut national dans le domaine des sciences du numérique, a pu à cette occasion rencontrer les responsables de différentes institutions japonaises impliquées sur le sujet de l"Open Access : le MEXT (Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology), la JSPS (Japan Society for the Promotion of Science), la JST (Japan Science and Technologyagency), le NII (National Institute of Informatics), et également le Dr Yuko Harayama, membre exécutif du CSTI (Council for Science, Technology and Innovation). Deux ateliers de travail, l"un réunissant des représentants de bibliothèques universitaires, le second les scientifiques japonais impliqués sur ce sujet, sont venus compléter ces entretiens. Les discussions ont notamment porté sur :</p><p>-Les plans existants de souscription aux revues scientifiques et de licenses nationales (coûts, services associés comme l"archivage et l"exploration de données, ou « data mining »). -La politique existante et la position japonaise sur la question des modèles « Gold Open Access » où les auteurs paient pour la publication de leur article, « Green Open Access » où les auteurs déposent une copie de leurs articles sur une page personnelle ou une archive ouverte, ou encore les modèles hybrides. -Plus particulièrement sur le modèle « Green Open Access », l"état actuel de déploiement d"archives ouvertes (et la politique menée pour encourager les chercheurs à y déposer leurs publication) et de plateformes d"évaluation et à contenu éditorial (épi-journaux, « overlay journals »..) -La politique en matière d"accès libre aux données de la recherche :</p><p>infrastructures et recommandations au niveau national pour la mise à disposition libre des données de recherche.</p><p>De nouvelles possibilités de collaboration, pour la synchronisation d"archives et de plateformes, le développement des services associés, mais également pour l"échange de bonnes pratiques en vue de sensibiliser les chercheurs, ont été mises en valeur. A l"issue de cette mission, un rapport fournira un état des lieux sur le statut actuel de l"Open Access au Japon et ces perspectives de collaboration.</p><p>Contact : Mme Evelyne ETCHEBÉHÈRE, attachée pour les Sciences et Technologies de l"Information et de la Communication à l"Ambassade de France.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Still, there are several positive factors that are likely to help Japan taking a leading role in the open access movement:  The dramatic growth of open access repositories in Japan in the recent year, despite the fragmentation effect we have already mentioned created a real culture of repository management in Japan as well as a factor for higher collaboration between Japanese university libraries;  The centralisation role of NII and in particular the recent deployment of JAIRO cloud 20 or the provision of a national journal management platform is likely to create in the very close future a very strong and coherent infrastructure at the service of forthcoming open access policies 21 ;  Mandate (PhD) MEXT has started to work with JST to introduce mandatory rule for scientists to publish their papers and data sets open accessible attached to public funds. [Source MT]  The strong influence of library networks (cf. the pioneering role of Universities such as Chiba)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="21,90.00,72.00,453.60,302.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>publication repository platform: HAL 7 .At national level, the French Minister for Research has issued in January 2013 a strong statement on open access to scholarly results, where the archiving of publications in open access repositories, and in particular the HAL national platform, has been given priority, in complement to the definition of new viable editorial and business model for scientific publishing.</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>http://openaccess.mpg.de/Berlin-Declaration</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_1"><p>green open access can be defined as the free dissemination of scholarly papers by authors themselves</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_2"><p>green open access can be defined as the free dissemination of scholarly papers by the publishing platforms where the article has been submitted.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_3"><p>for instance without relying on the sole Journal Impact Factor</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_4"><p>See for instance the infelicitous proposal in:</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="10" xml:id="foot_5"><p>http://www.couperin.org</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="11" xml:id="foot_6"><p>As opposed to France where major universities have chosen to have their IR portal developed within HAL, JAIRO Cloud initially took up within smaller universities which could not afford deploying their own IR environment.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="12" xml:id="foot_7"><p>Kiyos are also disseminated using the CiNii service from NII (http://ci.nii.ac.jp)</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="13" xml:id="foot_8"><p>www.jaibs.jp  </p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="16" xml:id="foot_9"><p>In universities such as KeiO (KOARA repository) with a specific policy, the rate can reach 40%, with a clear impact on visibility.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="17" xml:id="foot_10"><p>https://tel.archives-ouvertes.fr/STAR</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="18" xml:id="foot_11"><p>http://www.dart-europe.eu</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="19" xml:id="foot_12"><p>ガチョウと黄金の卵</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="20" xml:id="foot_13"><p>JAIRO cloud now hosts 60% of all IR in Japan, in particular from smaller universities with limited in-house implementation resources.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="21" xml:id="foot_14"><p>A typical example is Chiba University, a precursor in the domain of setting up an institutional repository and associated overlay services, which now experimenting a switch to JAIRO cloud.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="22" xml:id="foot_15"><p>http://www.ambafrance-jp.org/Compte-rendu-Mission-d-experts</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We are much thankful to two essential persons that have made our visit to Tokyo possible. First, EvelyneEtchebehere from the French embassy has been seminal in identifying the need for such a visit, providing the corresponding financial and logistic support and finally managing to have some essential doors open. Second, SyunTutiya from the National Institution for Academic Degrees and University Evaluation, who provided most of our contact persons in Japan and identified the</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Annexes</head> <ref type="bibr">(1985)</ref> <p>in mathematics of the University of Minnesota (USA). He worked at the Technical University of <ref type="bibr">Delft (1983</ref><ref type="bibr">Delft ( -1984))</ref>, at the Centre for Mathematics and Computer Science (CWI) in Amsterdam <ref type="bibr">(1984-1985 and 1989-1991)</ref> and at the University of Amsterdam <ref type="bibr">(1985)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1986)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1987)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1988)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1989)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1990)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1991)</ref>, before getting appointed in 1991 as full professor of computer science at the TechnischeUniversiteit Eindhoven (TU/e).</p><p>As of October 2011, he is general director of CWI in Amsterdam, keeping a part-time professorship at TU/e. As of January 2015, this part-time professorship is replaced by one at the Institute of Logic, Language and Computation of the University of Amsterdam.</p><p>He is well-known as a researcher in formal methods, in particular in process algebra and its applications. To date, he supervised 29 Ph.D. degrees. He was scientific director of the national research school Institute for Programming research and Algorithmics <ref type="bibr">(1996)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1997)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1998)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1999)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2000)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2001)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2002)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2003)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2004)</ref>, dean of the department of Mathematics and Computer Science of the TU/e <ref type="bibr">(1996-1999 and 2002-2004)</ref>, and initiated the Embedded Systems Institute in <ref type="bibr">Eindhoven (1996)</ref>. He chairs the steering committee of the CONCUR conferences and is a member of the KHMW (Royal Holland Society of Arts and Humanities). Recently Claude Kirchner has also been involved in the set-up of the FUN (France UniversitéNumérique) French gouvernemental MOOC initiative and was an organizer of the DagstuhlPerpective Workshop on MOOCs (http://www.dagstuhl.de). He is member of numerous scientific advisory committees, member of the committee for ethical research in digital science in France (CERNA) and president of Inria"s Institutional Review Board (COERLE), président of the CCSD (Centre pour la Communication ScientifiqueDirecte) steering committee.</p><p>AlexandreMoatti, 55 ans, estingénieur en chef des Mines (Conseilgénéral de l'économie, de l'industrie et des technologies, ministère de l'Industrie) et parallèlementchercheurassocié à l'université Paris-VII-Diderot (laboratoired'histoire des sciences et des techniques sphere UMR 7219 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>17:10 Closing</head><p>Citizen science in France is just emerging (like in Japan).</p><p>Press release from the French embassy 22</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Compte-rendu : Mission d'experts français sur l'Open Access</head><p>Une mission d"experts français portant sur l"« Open Access » a été organisée du 27 au 30 Janvier 2015 à Tokyo, par le service pour la Science et la Technologie de l"ambassade de France au Japon.</p><p>Une mission d"experts français portant sur l"« Open Access » a été organisé du 27 au 30 Janvier 2015 par le service pour la Science et la Technologie de l"ambassade de France au Japon.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Report by the Expert Panel on Open Science, based on Global Perspectives Cabinet Office, Government of Japan</title>
		<ptr target="http://www8.cao.go.jp/cstp/sonota/openscience/150330_openscience_en1.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">150330_openscience_summary_e n.pdf  Full report</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-03-30">March 30. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Promoting Open Science in Japan -Opening up a new era for the advancement of science</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hita-Hita: Open Access and Institutional Repositories in Japan Ten Years On</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yuinishizono</forename><surname>Ikukotsuchide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Masako</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shigeki</forename><surname>Sugita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kazuo</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hideki</forename><surname>Uchijima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Capelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jens</forename><surname>Gustedt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claude</forename><surname>Kirchner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Loiseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3233/978-1-61499-409-1-78</idno>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://www.ebooks.iospress.nl/publication/36552&gt;.&lt;10.3233/978-1-61499-409-1-78&gt;.&lt;hal-01002815v2&gt;" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">EPISCIENCES -an overlay publication platform. Dr. PanayiotaPolydoratou. ELPUB2014 -International Conference on ElectronicPublishing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Greece</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IOS Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013-07">July 2013. Jun 2014. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="87" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chris</forename><surname>Armbruster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>&lt;hal- 00399881</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Beyondinstitutionalrepositories. International Journal of Digital Library Systems, IGI Global</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
