<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Implementation of the IFIP Digital Library in the HAL open publication repository</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Estelle</forename><surname>Nivault</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alain</forename><surname>Monteil</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurence</forename><surname>Farhi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Implementation of the IFIP Digital Library in the HAL open publication repository</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BC2EF00710618B3DC12DAF3D6F3EE882</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 6 Jun 2016 Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution| 4.0 International License</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:02+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract xml:lang="fr">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access archive for the deposit and dissemination of scientific research documents, whether they are published or not. The documents may come from teaching and research institutions in France or abroad, or from public or private research centers. L'archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est destinée au dépôt et à la diffusion de documents scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The International Federation for Information Processing (IFIP) is a nongovernmental and non-for-profit umbrella organization of national societies working in the field of information processing. It was founded in 1960 under the auspices of UNESCO. Its Digital Library (DL) comprises more than 30 000 documents (conference proceedings, workshops, tutorials, surveys…), most of which have been published as volumes with Springer. In 2014, IFIP settled an agreement with Inria, the French National Research Institute for computer science and applied mathematics, to migrate the existing content to the HAL open publication repository and maintain it there in the long run.</p><p>A collection is a personalized browsing environment associated to specific groups of publications and linked to a persistent URL. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AURéHAL</head><p>Contact: ifip-dl@inria.fr</p><p>The advanced search facility allows one to query all meta-data fields as well as the full-texts of the DL.</p><p>Each volume is associated to a table of contents. The links on article titles provide access to the document entry in HAL together with the full-text when available (non-embargoed). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HAL Ifip Collections</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">Table of contents -------------- -------------- -------------- ------------</formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>/hal.inria.fr/IFIP</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Generation of Bibliographical Data (Grobid) combined with X2Hal service: a way in progress to the automatic extraction of meta-data from PDF files and connect the author affiliations to the central authorities service AuréHAL: https://aurehal.archives-ouvertes.DL consists of a main collection for all documents and sub-collections by series, volumes, technical committee (TC) and working groups (WG). Each deposit is added to one or more subcollections.• Main collection • Proceedings volume • Reference view Documents can be reached in several ways: • Browse by author, year, author affiliation, TC and WG • By conference titles • By the series collections: AICT, AICT Survey, AICT Tutorial, LNBIP, LNCS https://hal.inria.fr/IFIP https://hal.inria.fr/IFIP-AICT-447 https://hal.inria.fr/IFIP-AICT-447/hal-01301409 Consultation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Scripts and stylesheets on GitHub: https://github.com/INRIA/IFIPSpecifications • Grobid: https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid • CAPELLI Laurent, FARHI Laurence, ROMARY Laurent, "A TEI conformant pivot format for the HAL back-office" (Poster): https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01221774v1 • ROMARY Laurent, ARMBRUSTER Chris, "Beyond institutional repositories", in International Journal of Digital Library Systems, 01-2010, p. 44-6: https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00399881</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
