<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">DD0A53018E67529CE781A8CFF3A0EE7F</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>• The TEI guidelines as specifications -Documentation and schemas are generated from one single specification file</p><p>• Expressed in a TEI sub-language: ODD (One Document Does it all)</p><p>Varieties of TEI Conformance</p><p>• Pure TEI-all subset -Most TEI projects</p><p>• TEI subset with extensions -Cf. TBX in TEI</p><p>• Non TEI document with TEI constructs (defined as an ODD)</p><p>-EAG extensions in the EU Cendari project The central role of customization   • Does not prevent one from knowing the TEI components… -Most projects can live with just a subset of the TEI ontology</p><p>• With the strong possibility to impact on the guidelines themselves -E.g. &lt;abstract&gt;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPLORING NEW (AND OLD) REALMS</head><p>TEI: you're not alone… </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SCIENTIFIC INFORMATION?</head><p>Characterising scientific documents  The (simplified) patent life-cycle</p><p>• Patent application in one or several patent offices -USPTO, Japan, EPO (directly or initiated in a specific country) -First application: reference date for the patent ("coming into force") -Form a "Patent family"</p><p>• Examination process for one application The situation so far</p><p>• Complete implementation in the back-office system -Integration of several so-far dispersed data-bases -First large-scale implementation of &lt;standOff&gt; (be patient!)</p><p>• Quite a few customisations -maintained in a reference ODD specification</p><p>-Re-use of TEI attributes at various places</p><p>• @type, @cert, @sortKey -Bibliographic references to patents -Complex classification mechanism (&lt;classCodeGroup&gt;)</p><p>• All in all a large scale demonstration of the TEI possibilities • Next steps Application: interlinear annotation</p><p>• Encoding interlinear annotation as inline content (in &lt;text&gt;) &lt;annotationBlock who="#SPK0" start="#T9" end="#T12" xml:id="au1"&gt; &lt;u xml:id="u1"&gt; &lt;seg xml:id="seg45" type="utterance" subtype="declarative"&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w43"&gt;Nee&lt;/w&gt; &lt;pc xml:id="pc3"&gt;,&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w44"&gt;hab&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w45"&gt;kein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w46"&gt;Führerschein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;/seg&gt; &lt;/u&gt; &lt;spanGrp type="en"&gt; &lt;span from="#T9" to="#T12"&gt;No, I don't have a driver's license.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;spanGrp type="pos"&gt; &lt;span from="#w43" to="#w43"&gt;NE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#pc3" to="#pc3"&gt;$,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w44" to="#w44"&gt;VAIMP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w45" to="#w45"&gt;PIAT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w46" to="#w46"&gt;NN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;/annotationBlock&gt; ISO 24624 -Transcription of Spoken Language, implementation in EXMARaLDA</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Standoff interlinear annotation</head><p>• Encoding interlinear annotation as stand-off markup -In &lt;standOff&gt; &lt;annotationBlock inst="#u1"&gt; &lt;spanGrp xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="en"&gt; &lt;span from="#T9" to="#T12"&gt;No, I don't have a driver's license.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;spanGrp xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="pos"&gt; &lt;span from="#w43" to="#w43"&gt;NE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#pc3" to="#pc3"&gt;$,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w44" to="#w44"&gt;VAIMP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w45" to="#w45"&gt;PIAT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w46" to="#w46"&gt;NN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;/annotationBlock&gt; -In &lt;body&gt; &lt;u xml:id="u1" who="#SPK0" start="#T9" end="#T12"&gt; &lt;seg xml:id="seg45" type="utterance" subtype="declarative"&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w43"&gt;Nee&lt;/w&gt;&lt;pc xml:id="pc3"&gt;,&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w44"&gt;hab&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w45"&gt;kein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w46"&gt;Führerschein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;/seg&gt;&lt;/u&gt; &lt;zone type="" corresp="#_theSurface" ulx="1253" uly="802" lrx="22" lry="29"/&gt;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Prototypical example</head><p>Dates in a named entity recognition context &lt;annotationBlock&gt; &lt;date xml:id="E4N1" from="1944-08-17" to="1944-08-25"&gt; 17 -25 août 1944&lt;/date&gt; &lt;interp ana="#E4N1" inst="#d1e173"/&gt; &lt;span xml:id="d1e173" from="#E4T6" to="#E4T10" /&gt; &lt;/annotationBlock&gt; Great advantage on readiness and programmatic treatment Issues (many)</p><p>• Which header do we need?</p><p>-Standoff annotation usually requires very restricted meta-data -If we adopt the TEI header, we need to make it more flexible…</p><p>• Should we have a convergence with biblFull (where profileDesc is missed, BTW, SF:533, deeply ambered)</p><p>-Stand-off annotations may be generated by humans and machines</p><p>• how to put &lt;author&gt; (editionStmt) and &lt;appInfo&gt; (encodingDesc) at the same place?</p><p>• How do we provide guidance concerning annotations?</p><p>-Mapping the OA model to precise TEI constructs? -Allowing a wide variety of possible vocabularies depending on the use case?</p><p>• TBX entries, MathML, full-text annotation (&lt;body&gt;?)</p><p>-Aligning with the various ISO standards: MAF, SynAF and SemAF series Next steps • Finalising the graft in the guidelines -Section in chapter 16 Linking, Segmentation, and Alignment?</p><p>• Don't give up the fight…</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>JOINING EFFORTS WITH OTHERS: TEI AND LMF</head><p>A divided landscape</p><p>• The TEI print dictionary chapter -Available since more than 20 years</p><p>• See http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/Vault-GL.html -Used in a wide variety of dictionary projects</p><p>• 6 entries just in http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/Projects/ • Disseminated at quick pace within the COS E-NEL network (credits: Toma Tasovac)</p><p>• ISO 24613:2008 Language resource management -Lexical markup framework (LMF)</p><p>-Shorter life span -Mostly implemented in NLP related activities</p><p>• Is it worth reconciling the 2?</p><p>-Yes: for the sake of combining a well-defined model with a rich XML infrastructure -A need for the TEI to have a terser model</p><p>• Curation, interchange, tools, automatic generation of TEI constructs</p><p>• Is it just possible.</p><p>-Yes: and now!</p><p>The need for a revision  -Sub-setting the TEI guidelines  • Usage, grammatical constraints, source, date, language, etc.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">•</formula><p>• A need for revision  The TEI is doing well -the hidden TEI</p><p>• Antonio Zampolli price by ADHO -Reflects that the TEI is pervading all fields in the (digital?) humanities</p><p>• TEI has become a natural component of a humanities project based on textual sources -Many small editions are flourishing everywhere -Now recommended or requested by funding organisations -Numerous training events (cf. DiXiT)</p><p>• Taken up by larger organisations -Academies, Dictionary projects, EPO… especially in Europe</p><p>Consolidating our conceptual model</p><p>• TEI as a rich space of elementary constructs -Attributes (classes), "entities", bibliographical and dictionary entries, etc.</p><p>• Multifarious document types for various communities -From scholarly editions to dictionaries, including computer mediated communication, scientific information, etc. -More precise guidelines for specific applications </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Community based workflow -Mailing list -GitHub -bugs and features • Recording all issues and decisions -Cf. ODD as a specification platform • Deliverables -Documentation -TEI guidelines (more than 500 elements) -Schemas -DTD, RelaxNG, W3C • Additional resources -Tools • Online customization: Roma • Online processing: OxGarage • Stylesheets (included in Oxygen) -Examples -TEI by Example Special Interest Groups (SIGs) • Computer-Mediated Communication (Michael Beißwenger) • Correspondence. (Peter Stadler and Joachim Veit) • Education (TBA) • Libraries (Stefanie Gehrke and Kevin Hawkins) • Manuscripts (Dot Porter and Gerrit Brüning) • Music (Raffaele Viglianti) • Ontologies (Oyvind Eide and Christian-Emil Ore) • Scholarly Publishing (Daniel O'Donnell) • TEI for Linguists (Piotr Baoski and Andreas Witt) • Text and Graphics (John Walsh and Martin de la Iglesia) • Tools (Serge Heiden) The TEI guidelines • Online documentation -Prose description organized in chapters -Specific documentation for each element -Access to all examples from the guidelines • Schema(s) -RelaxNG, W3C (, DTD) -Available online from the Roma interface -Delivered as packages (Ubuntu, Oxygen)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>-</head><label></label><figDesc>Search report, communications, decision, appeal, opposition -Patent documents may be revised at each stage • Necessity to have a single model for dealing with all stages and versions• The TEI appeared to be the optimal</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>--</head><label></label><figDesc>All scholarly publications (NPL) -All official communications WAKE UP STAND-OFF! The simple picture Inline annotation: Intertwined with the source text Stand off annotation: Source text is referenced from outside Embedded stand off annotation: Stand off annotations attached to the same document as the source Why embedded stand-off annotation? • In line (!) with the TEI philosophy • Each time the source document is seen as the reference organisational unit -Corpus management -Transmission workflow -Multiple annotation layers -Competing annotations • E.g. Manual vs. automatic annotation Standoff: A long-standing issue • The idea of standoff annotation is not new in general -Thompson &amp; McKelvie, 1997 • Standoff annotation has been a core concept in the TEI guidelines since the beginning -Cf. Chapter: Linking, Segmentation, and Alignment -Availability of &lt;anchor&gt;, &lt;span&gt;, &lt;interp&gt;, &lt;link&gt;, @ana • But: not integrated in the TEI architecture -Stand-off elements can appear anywhere in a TEI document -Usual trade-off between on-site vs. grouping (&lt;back&gt;) • The NLP community has also developed its own means -GraF (Ide &amp; Suderman 2007) , Paula (Zeldes et al. 2009), etc. • Need for a proper, and inclusive, treatment of standoff annotations in the TEI -Better integration, more guidance Embedded standoff: Basic concept • Building up an autonomous document containing primary source and additional annotations -Annotations are conveyed with their specific meta-data -Annotations have their specific place in the TEI document architecture -Standoff annotations may be recursively organized -Standoff annotations may point to textual as well as facsimile content -Well-defined elementary annotation units -Coherence with existing models (Open Annotation, ISO TC 37) should be ensured • Typical use-cases -Annotated corpora • Treebanks -Text mining • Named entity recognition, keyword/terms extraction -Human annotations on a document • critical editions, patent examination, peer review… • Strong relation with interlinear annotation Timeline • 2011: Paper by Thomas Schmidt in jTEI (https://jtei.revues.org/142) • August 2012: new tickets by Javier Pose (EPO) • January 2014: Workshop in Berlin -Draft of a first proposal -Setting-up a github environment • 2012-2016: ISO 24624 project (Editor: Thomas Schmidt) -Need for a annotation grouping component (&lt;annotationBlock&gt;) • May 2015: Council meeting in Ann Arbor -Several updates to the proposal -Stabilisation of element names • March 2016: TEI release 6.0.0 New element &lt;annotationBlock&gt; for interlinear annotation • August 2016: publication of ISO 24624 Transcription of related to the annotation, such as annotator, revisions of the annotations, availability Recursive construct: allows the organisation of annotations par method, annotator, campaign &lt;div&gt;-like component for structuring complex series of annotations Elementary annotation unit</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>--</head><label></label><figDesc>Main assets of ISO 24613 LMF -Comprehensive core model + series of annexes for additional modules -Perfectible XML serialisation… • Going towards a multi-part standard -Simplifying the editorial process (drafting, decision making, revising; various tempi) -Reflecting the needs of specific communities (modules, serialisation) Overview of the current plans • Resolution 2016-04.2 (WG 4) Multi-part development of LMF -Part 1: Core model -Part 2: MRDs -Part 3: Diachrony-Etymology -Part 4: TEI serialisation -Part 5: LBX serialisation (Part 4) A TEI serialisation for LMF • Objective Preventing re-inventing element that already exist -Eliciting constraints on the TEI model • Method Covering core model and a selected number of extensions</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>Part 3) The case of etymology • A flat model in the current TEI chapter -No sense of etymon: &lt;mentioned&gt; -No sense of etymological process • Typed and recursive &lt;etym&gt; -No grouping of etymon related information</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Time to complement and consolidate the existing practices -TEI as reference framework -ISO as a precise standardisation background • Various ongoing projets and groups -Clarin Standards committee, DARIAH WG Lexical Resources, TEI LingSIG -COST E-NEL WG2, EU Parthenos • Joining efforts -Towards a single information space • Basecamp, GitHub, Blog • Exchanging information -Increasing participation as experts • ISO-TEI in particular WHITHER TEI?</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Collaboration with ISO (standards), DARIAH (recommendations) • Reducing syntactic freedom in specific application domains, not in TEI as a whole -Complementing our stock: onomasiological constructs, standOff • Strong conceptual basis with pure ODD -For TEI and non TEI based application -Starting point for offering support to other dissemination formats (JSON, LOD) -Interfacing the trends -XML is likely to remain central for a long time for sustainable backoffice content Focusing, enlarging? • Enlarging our expert basis -Stronger role for SIGs -Close coordination with council -Bringing in more technical experts from outside • Institutional partnership -Archives, Clarin, DARIAH, MEI, Europeana • Further enforcement of the TEI guidelines • Sharing our technical platform -E.g. EAD maintenance-Thinking together the sustainability of TEI material• Repositories (Tapas)• The TEI already offers a strong basis for sustainability• Need for a stable communication framework -Lively conference and journal (jTEI) -Investing in the web site and the wiki MERCI !</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="2,0.00,160.50,541.87,379.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>hand of reviewers Patents -A variety of roles • Applicant/inventor/representati ve • Opponents • … and examiners Standards -Priority to the</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Authorship Workflow The European Patent Office</cell></row><row><cell>• Expert documents describing a specific scientific and technical progress with respect to the state of the art Publications -The essence of publishing • Importance of attribution Publications -Semi-formal • The European one-stop shop for patent • Traditional (vestigial?) concept of peer-review applications • Three main domains -Scholarly publications -Standardisation documents • Reflects the context and time of the research (project, affiliation, biography) • From author's initial manuscript • Examination of each application by experts from to publisher's version • Evolution in the role of each the field (examiners) -Patents • Some common characteristics -Authorship: the basis of scientific attribution • W3C: editors date -Certification: workflow, responsibilities, metadata leaders • Importance of initial submission -Network of references: relating to the state of the art • ISO: no authors but project Europe, etc. • One single reference document meaning expert group submissions: national, US, • ISO: WD, CD, DIS, FDIS, IS -Vocabulary: technical terms are essential to convey (or hide) • Consensus building =&gt; large • Coordination of multiple membership structure -Structure: usually a formal internal organisation version (e.g. prior art) • Review by patent examiners • Decision process reflecting -Based on existing patents as well as scholarly • The hidden institution Patents -Very formal Standards -Very formal publications (aka Non Patent Literature)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Remaining in the scope of the Print dictionary chapter • Extending scope if we feel there is a need from the potential TEI applications (e.g. syntax)</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>We are not bound to the existing chapter, even if we have to abide to the Birnbaum principle</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Gathering mapping proposals Once upon a time, the clergyman…</cell></row><row><cell>Component &lt;entry xml:lang="en"&gt; &lt;form type="lemma"&gt; Lexical Entry &lt;orth&gt;clergyman&lt;/orth&gt; &lt;gramGrp&gt;</cell><cell>TEI construct &lt;entry&gt;…&lt;/entry&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>Form &lt;pos&gt;commonNoun&lt;/pos&gt; Lemma &lt;/gramGrp&gt; &lt;/form&gt;</cell><cell>&lt;form&gt;…&lt;/form&gt; &lt;form type="lemma"&gt;…&lt;/form&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>Word Form &lt;form type="inflected"&gt; Syntactic Behaviour &lt;orth&gt;clergyman&lt;/orth&gt; &lt;gramGrp&gt;</cell><cell>&lt;form type="inflected"&gt;…&lt;/form&gt; ??</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">• Associating a definite TEI construct for each component of the LMF Meta-&lt;number&gt;singular&lt;/number&gt; &lt;etym&gt; &lt;/gramGrp&gt; model &lt;/form&gt; • Adding constraints when necessary -(e.g. @xml:lang mandatory on &lt;entry&gt;?) Data category ?? &lt;form type="inflected"&gt; TEI construct &lt;orth&gt;clergymen&lt;/orth&gt; -Complementing the TEI /PartOfSpeech/ &lt;pos&gt; &lt;gramGrp&gt; • Defining new constructs (or elements?) if necessary /Gender/ &lt;number&gt;plural&lt;/number&gt; &lt;gen&gt; &lt;/gramGrp&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>… &lt;/form&gt;</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>How far should we go here? &lt;/entry&gt;</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>-</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="12" xml:id="foot_0"><p>&amp;</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="13" xml:id="foot_1"><p>mai 2016 Plénière Termith -Nancy</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Automatic dictionary structure recognition</head><p>PhD theses by Mohamed Khemakhem (Inria, projet H2020 Parthenos) &lt;entry&gt; &lt;form type="lemma"&gt; &lt;orth&gt;pacotille&lt;/orth&gt; &lt;pron&gt;&lt;pc&gt;[&lt;/pc&gt;pakɔtij&lt;pc&gt;]&lt;/pc&gt;&lt;/pron&gt; &lt;gramGrp&gt;&lt;pos&gt;n.&lt;/pos&gt;&lt;gen&gt;f.&lt;/gen&gt;&lt;/gramGrp&gt; &lt;/form&gt; &lt;etym&gt;&lt;pc&gt;(&lt;/pc&gt;&lt;lang norm="es"&gt;esp.&lt;/lang&gt; &lt;oRef&gt;pacotilla&lt;/oRef&gt;&lt;pc&gt;)&lt;/pc&gt;&lt;/etym&gt; &lt;sense&gt; &lt;usg type="time"&gt;Autref.&lt;/usg&gt; &lt;pc&gt;,&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;def&gt;petit lot de marchandises que pouvaient embarquer les gens de l'équipage ou les passagers d'un navire&lt;/def&gt; &lt;pc&gt;.&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;/sense&gt; &lt;re&gt; &lt;form type="compound"&gt; &lt;orth&gt;De pacotille&lt;/orth&gt; &lt;/form&gt;&lt;pc&gt;,&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;sense&gt;&lt;def&gt;de peu de valeur, de qualité médiocre.&lt;/def&gt;&lt;/sense&gt; &lt;/re&gt; &lt;/entry&gt;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CRF (Conditional Random Fields) based data mining Fine grained recognition of the various component of an entry in a legacy dictionary</head><p>Using the TEI as reference output format (coordination with ENEL recommendations) Perspectives: Creating step by step a large-scale network (diachronic and synchronic) of our lexical patrimony</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
