<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1B2CCA4C0518F9A0551C6F9A3F69D500</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inria -a research organisation with a vision</head><p>Vision for a scientific information policy • Maximising the dissemination of our scientific assets (visibility and swift dissemination of knowledge), for a reasonable price • Constitution of a reliable and sovereign institutional corpus (documentation, preservation, access), with clear public governance principles • Contribution to shaping the scientific communication landscape in terms of editorial processes and usage made of scientific productions</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4,400</head><p>People Inria scientific information policy in concrete terms      IFIP: editorial management  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>--•</head><label></label><figDesc>Development limitations of pdf "Converting PDF to XML is a bit like converting hamburgers into cows. You may be best off printing it and then scanning the result through a decent OCR package." Michael Kay (http://lists.xml.org/archives/xml-dev/200607/msg00509.html) Inspired from: Duncan Hull Structuring content • GROBID: information extraction from PDF documents • Meta-data: title, authors, affiliations, abstracts • Bibliographical references (with crossref consolidation) • Standards-based representation • TEI (Text Encoding Initiative) as a reference format • State of the art performance(CRF models) • Cf. M. Lipinski, et al., 2013 • Used at EPO/ResearchGate/Mendeley/CERN/NASA • Integrated in HAL • Automatic meta-data extraction for author's deposit Sciencesconf-a conference management tool Services • Online conference management tool • Abstracts, full paper, peer review, conference program, registration Technologies • Modular services • Unique authentication system • Connection to HAL authorities • Upload to HAL Library support • Supervises the creation of a conference instance • Create conference series • Moderates the integration of the papers as a collection in HAL épisciences -an overlay journal platform Services • Overlay certification environment • Post publication peer review • "Traditional" reviewing environment • Invited editors -special issues Technologies • OAI-PMH interface with repositories • Publication: arXiv, HAL, One of the major scholarly society in Information &amp; Communications -Organized in technical committees and working groups • Objective: setting up a sustainable digital library -All volumes publishes as IFIP conferences -Visibility, trust, technical facilities • Publication agreement with Springer -Systematic publication in the AICT, LNBIP and LNCS series -3-year embargo before free online dissemination -Provision of meta-data (XML Springer) and author post-review manuscripts (PDF) • Note: XML Springer formats often contains full-text • For Inria: an experiment in ingesting and aggregating Standardized ingestion workflow • Towards a unified TEI-based format for scholarly papers -Cf. EU Peer project (massive ingestion of preprints) -Istex, OpenEdition, HAL, EPO -More flexible and extensible than JATS (e.g. full text)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>•--</head><label></label><figDesc>Objectives Designing a scholarly dashboard • Scientific profiles: publications and authors -Experimenting various data extraction mecanisms • Reference content from the HAL publication repositories -Meta-data: title, periods, authors, affiliations -Full-text: full-text indexing, conceptual search • Technical background -NERD and Grobid full text • Librarians are shaping the service with developpers -Identifying measured quantities in scientific documents -Value, unit, measured entity -Multiple search scenarios in a scholarly context Example (example 2, streptomycin) Plugging additional services -2 • Re-publishing content -Grobid-TEI as a pivot format in the publishing environment -Generation of multiple derived format • HTML • ePub • Braille • How far are we from this? -Improving the performances of Grobid (e.g. book) -Partially implemented in various initiatives • Revues.org • Istex • There again, a central role for the library staff -Identifying user expectations -Maintaining formats and transforms Conclusion • Digital sovereignty -Mastering scholarly content at all stages of the publication process -Mastering the whole scholarly process • Understanding where and when we need to resort to the private sector -Mastering interoperability by means of open formats -A general culture of openness • Focusing our efforts -More brain, budget etc. in shaping this digital turn -Stop loosing time in "negotiating" open access: let's just do it • Dedicated research activity on scholarly information management -TDM breakthroughs at the service of scientific information -Dealing with the quickly evolving digital context -Coupling service units with adequate research teams • Training future digital librarians -Formats, standards and related technologies -Data mining and visualisation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="22,342.81,311.15,354.00,203.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="24,119.76,200.93,569.47,331.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mapping</head><p>The mapping is a set of domain specific wrappers transforming the input/output from/to the internal data model. The internal data model is composed of:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HAL authors</head><p>Local attributes: surname, last name, title, email, etc Comparison using distances depending upon the type of the attribute: e. g. Person Name is computed using Dice Sorensen, Cosine similarity and Jaro Winkler.</p><p>Relation attributes: co-authorship, affiliations, popularity*, years of activity*, etc. Relations are computed using affiliation information Preliminary results are promising, F-1 score of 0.964</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural networks and physical systems with emergent collective computational abilities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">•</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hopfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New Review of Academic Librarianship</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2554" to="2558" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">2010. 1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EPISCIENCES -an overlay publication platform</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christine</forename><surname>Berthaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Capelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jens</forename><surname>Gustedt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claude</forename><surname>Kirchner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Loiseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3233/978-1-61499-409-1-78</idno>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://www.ebooks.iospress.nl/publication/36552" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ELPUB</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2014</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014-06">Jun 2014</date>
			<pubPlace>Thessalonique, Greece</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Scholarly Communication. Mehler, Alexander and Romary, Laurent. Handbook of Technical Communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>978-3-11-022494-8. &lt;inria-00593677</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>de Gruyter</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
