<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="fr">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">CENDARI Virtual Research Environment &amp; Named Entity Recognition techniques</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Patrice</forename><surname>Lopez</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Virtual Research Environment &amp; Named Entity Recognition techniques. Grenzen überschreiten -Digitale Geisteswissenschaft heute und morgen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Feb 2014</addrLine>
									<postCode>01577975</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Virtual Research Environment &amp; Named Entity Recognition techniques. Grenzen überschreiten -Digitale Geisteswissenschaft heute und morgen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Feb 2014</addrLine>
									<postCode>01577975</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexander</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Virtual Research Environment &amp; Named Entity Recognition techniques. Grenzen überschreiten -Digitale Geisteswissenschaft heute und morgen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Feb 2014</addrLine>
									<postCode>01577975</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Virtual Research Environment &amp; Named Entity Recognition techniques. Grenzen überschreiten -Digitale Geisteswissenschaft heute und morgen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Feb 2014</addrLine>
									<postCode>01577975</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Virtual Research Environment &amp; Named Entity Recognition techniques. Grenzen überschreiten -Digitale Geisteswissenschaft heute und morgen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Feb 2014</addrLine>
									<postCode>01577975</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><forename type="middle">Romary</forename><surname>Cendari</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Virtual Research Environment &amp; Named Entity Recognition techniques. Grenzen überschreiten -Digitale Geisteswissenschaft heute und morgen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Feb 2014</addrLine>
									<postCode>01577975</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">CENDARI Virtual Research Environment &amp; Named Entity Recognition techniques</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B96335AFBB7C8CE09903B70C43BA8304</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 28 Aug 2017 Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution| 4.0 International License</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access archive for the deposit and dissemination of scientific research documents, whether they are published or not. The documents may come from teaching and research institutions in France or abroad, or from public or private research centers. L'archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est destinée au dépôt et à la diffusion de documents scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="fr">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Overview</head><p>• Medieval culture</p><p>• World War I</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case study areas</head><p>The CENDARI project CENDARI has carried out multiple participatory design workshops in order for historians to articulate their needs and wishes regarding a digital research environment, and for the computer scientists to understand those needs. • two data spaces: personal and project-wide</p><p>• collecting notes (taken in e. g. archives)</p><p>• uploading files (e. g. scans of documents)</p><p>• recognition of Named Entities in notes</p><p>• visualization of found entities &amp; documents → foster exploration and analysis</p><p>• collaboration and sharing of notes &amp; documents (if wanted)</p><p>• enrichment of a common repository of historical information</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Historians' requirements and wishes</head><p>Dec. 12, 2013 Cendari VRE 4 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VRE prototype</head><p>Recognizing and resolving Named Entities has been mentioned by historians as being one of the most important features that would leverage the CENDARI VRE and distinguish it from other software currently used in the field. Named Entities are persons, organizations, places, dates, events, artifacts. The VRE will allow for</p><p>• manual tagging of entities</p><p>• automatic tagging of entities (with possible manual correction)  <ref type="bibr">-41/8-76 16.10.1918</ref> report of a shooting attack by bandits on an Ueberwachungs Patrouille in Lemberg. <ref type="bibr">64-41/8-92 17.4.1918</ref> report of a theft by soldiers of flour sacks from the train station in Ung. Hradisch </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dealing with entities</head><p>Statistical approaches are state-of-the-art in NER. They are accurate, provide high coverage and are portable when applied to new domains. However, the customization of such algorithms towards the historical domain raises several specific challenges:</p><p>• Lack of training data and reference/evaluation corpora</p><p>• Lack of knowledge resources (gazetteers, terminological databases). Existing gazetteers and terminological databases are only partially helpful for the historical researcher. They are more relevant for contemporary history.</p><p>• Multilinguality of sources and heterogeneous writing systems in use (for the World War I domain, especially Eastern European languages)</p><p>• Digitalization at an early stage: the documents to be processed are poorly integrated and normalized.</p><p>The gap between unstructured and semi-structured data on the one hand and semantic representation on the other is thus significantly larger than for fields such as biotechnology or chemistry where NER currently is most advanced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Problems in the historical domain</head><p>For contemporary English, we use statistical NER based on Conditional Random Fields (CRF), allowing for very accurate and fine-grained resolution (e. g. not only choosing entity type "person", but "military person").</p><p>For other languages, we are currently developing an original approach based on intensive exploitation of existing generalist knowledge bases:</p><p>1. A huge lexicon is assembled from Freebase and Wikipedia, containing entity names and translations into various languages.</p><p>2. Text in a target language is searched for entities from the lexicon. (The lexicon is large enough so that some will always be found.)</p><p>3. For unambiguous matches, machine learning is applied using language-independent features to find entities not in the lexicon.</p><p>4. Resolution of entities against the lexicon is done using measures of semantic relatedness. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Reichspost [date unclear] about several railway thefts undertaken by a gang calling itself "die grüne Brigade" in Galicia Mehrere Eisenbahndiebe bei einem Kampf getötet. Aus Krakau, 28.d wird Gemeldet:[....] daß ein Dieb bei einem Einbrüche Verwendung Einer Dynamitpatrone beide Füße verlor. Wie der "Gniec Krakowski" weiters meldet,wurde […...]" 64-41/8-76 16.10.1918 report of a shooting attack by bandits on an Ueberwachungs Patrouille in Lemberg. 64-41/8-92 17.4.1918 report of a theft by soldiers of flour sacks from the train station in Ung. Hradisch 64-42 10.1.1918 report from MilKmmdo in Zagreb on growing Desertion und Rauberunwesen in the area on the example of a certain Gličanov Gliša [scan] 2.7.1818 "meldet das Gemeindeamt Voganj: Seit einigen Tagen sind erpressungen in der Gemeinde Voganj an […..] wurde bei Tage von zwei Des. Avram Maleti bedroht,'dass man ihm die Schweine holen wird'Zu kamen sie abends und verlangten Br[.....] schaffen werden. Zum Dorfnotär E. Wolf kamen zwei Des. [….] mockups by Jean-Daniel Fekete 3 major components: • LEFT: Storage user data space / CENDARI shared data space • MIDDLE: Note-taking environment creation, modification &amp; use • RIGHT: Entity visualization overview, exploration &amp; use Simplicity: minimalistic design for ease of learning Gentle learning: typing in an editor is the only pre-required user knowledge Unification: all CENDARI services in one platform</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1918 report from MilKmmdo in Zagreb on growing Desertion und Rauberunwesen in the area on the example of a certain Gličanov Gliša [scan] 2.7.1818 "meldet das Gemeindeamt Voganj: Seit einigen Tagen sind erpressungen in der Gemeinde Voganj an […..] wurde bei Tage von zwei Des. Avram Maleti bedroht,'dass man ihm die Schweine holen wird'Zu kamen sie abends und verlangten Br[.....] schaffen werden. Zum Dorfnotär E. Wolf kamen zwei Des. [….] in the notes &amp; visualizations directly beside!</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The project brings together information and computer scientists with historians and existing historical research infrastructures (archives, libraries, other digital projects) to improve conditions for digital historical scholarship. CEN-DARI has engaged in extensive networking with the archives and libraries of Europe, especially those in Eastern Europe. CENDARI is a 4-year, European-Commission-funded project led by Trinity College Dublin, in partnership with 14 institutions across 8 countries.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">CENDARI Virtual Research Environment &amp;</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Named Entity Recognition techniques</cell></row><row><cell>Patrice Lopez</cell><cell>Alexander Meyer</cell><cell>Laurent Romary</cell></row></table><note><p>Inria (Institut national de recherche en informatique et en automatique) &amp; HU Berlin forename.surname @inria.fr with support from the Inria Aviz team (Jean-Daniel Fekete et al.) CENDARI (Collaborative European Digital Archive Infrastructure) is a research infrastructure project aimed at integrating digital archives and resources for research on medieval and modern European history.</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
