<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">4ADBFF078D8C63BAD700830B79B46B31</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stakeholders</head><p>• Cultural Heritage Institutions (big or small) -Main source of primary information for research in the humanities (physical and/or digital)</p><p>• Equipments (big and small...)</p><p>-Data production by researchers on CH objects</p><p>• Data hosting institutions -Warrant the stability, the visibility and the long time availability of the primary data • ISO, W3C, TEI comply to this principles • Important distinction:</p><p>-Horizontal standards (cross-domain: ex. XML) -vs. Vertical standards (specific to one domain: ex. ISO 24611 for morpho-syntactic annotations, EAD for archival collections)</p><p>Standards in the Arts and Humanities • Lacunae (or fragmentations) to overcome -E.g. Descriptive metadata for audio-visual data</p><p>• Library and archival standards to interoperate with            The standard scenario?</p><p>Digitizing source documents Further work on documents TEI -core principles (1)</p><p>• The TEI document as a digital surrogate of a physical source -A TEI document is always part of a digital library workflow </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HOW DO YOU MANAGE THIS?</head><p>TEI in a nutshell</p><p>• TEI namespace:</p><p>-xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"</p><p>• TEI documentation:</p><p>http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/</p><p>• TEI processor, Roma:</p><p>http://www.tei-c.org/Roma/</p><p>• TEI document model Application: interlinear annotation</p><p>• Encoding interlinear annotation as inline content (in &lt;text&gt;) &lt;annotationBlock who="#SPK0" start="#T9" end="#T12" xml:id="au1"&gt; &lt;u xml:id="u1"&gt; &lt;seg xml:id="seg45" type="utterance" subtype="declarative"&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w43"&gt;Nee&lt;/w&gt; &lt;pc xml:id="pc3"&gt;,&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w44"&gt;hab&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w45"&gt;kein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w46"&gt;Führerschein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;/seg&gt; &lt;/u&gt; &lt;spanGrp type="en"&gt; &lt;span from="#T9" to="#T12"&gt;No, I don't have a driver's license.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;spanGrp type="pos"&gt; &lt;span from="#w43" to="#w43"&gt;NE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#pc3" to="#pc3"&gt;$,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w44" to="#w44"&gt;VAIMP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w45" to="#w45"&gt;PIAT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w46" to="#w46"&gt;NN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;/annotationBlock&gt; ISO 24624 -Transcription of Spoken Language, implementation in EXMARaLDA</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Standoff interlinear annotation</head><p>• Encoding interlinear annotation as stand-off markup -In &lt;standOff&gt; &lt;annotationBlock inst="#u1"&gt; &lt;spanGrp xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="en"&gt; &lt;span from="#T9" to="#T12"&gt;No, I don't have a driver's license.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;spanGrp xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="pos"&gt; &lt;span from="#w43" to="#w43"&gt;NE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#pc3" to="#pc3"&gt;$,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w44" to="#w44"&gt;VAIMP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w45" to="#w45"&gt;PIAT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span from="#w46" to="#w46"&gt;NN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/spanGrp&gt; &lt;/annotationBlock&gt; -In &lt;body&gt; &lt;u xml:id="u1" who="#SPK0" start="#T9" end="#T12"&gt; &lt;seg xml:id="seg45" type="utterance" subtype="declarative"&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w43"&gt;Nee&lt;/w&gt;&lt;pc xml:id="pc3"&gt;,&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w44"&gt;hab&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w45"&gt;kein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;w xml:id="w46"&gt;Führerschein&lt;/w&gt; &lt;/seg&gt;&lt;/u&gt; &lt;zone type="" corresp="#_theSurface" ulx="1253" uly="802" lrx="22" lry="29"/&gt;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Prototypical example</head><p>Dates in a named entity recognition context &lt;annotationBlock&gt; &lt;date xml:id="E4N1" from="1944-08-17" to="1944-08-25"&gt; 17 -25 août 1944&lt;/date&gt; &lt;interp ana="#E4N1" inst="#d1e173"/&gt; &lt;span xml:id="d1e173" from="#E4T6" to="#E4T10" /&gt; &lt;/annotationBlock&gt; Great advantage on readiness and programmatic treatment Issues (many)</p><p>• Which header do we need?</p><p>-Standoff annotation usually requires very restricted meta-data -If we adopt the TEI header, we need to make it more flexible…</p><p>• Should we have a convergence with biblFull (where profileDesc is missed, BTW, SF:533, deeply ambered)</p><p>-Stand-off annotations may be generated by humans and machines</p><p>• how to put &lt;author&gt; (editionStmt) and &lt;appInfo&gt; (encodingDesc) at the same place?</p><p>• How do we provide guidance concerning annotations?</p><p>-Mapping the OA model to precise TEI constructs? -Allowing a wide variety of possible vocabularies depending on the use case?</p><p>• TBX entries, MathML, full-text annotation (&lt;body&gt;?)</p><p>-Aligning with the various ISO standards: MAF, SynAF and SemAF series Next steps</p><p>• Finalising the content model of &lt;annotationBlock&gt; -Completely open model? -Constrained with specific model classes? (OA) -Alternation between the two (or more) options</p><p>• Gathering reference example from existing implementations -Istex, Termith, EPO, IDS</p><p>• Finalising the graft in the guidelines -Section in chapter 16 Linking, Segmentation, and Alignment?</p><p>• Don't give up the fight…</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>JOINING EFFORTS WITH OTHERS: TEI AND LMF</head><p>A divided landscape</p><p>• The TEI print dictionary chapter -Available since more than 20 years</p><p>• See http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/Vault-GL.html</p><p>-Used in a wide variety of dictionary projects</p><p>• 6 entries just in http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/Projects/ • Disseminated at quick pace within the COS E-NEL network (credits: Toma Tasovac)</p><p>• ISO 24613:2008 Language resource management -Lexical markup framework (LMF)</p><p>-Shorter life span -Mostly implemented in NLP related activities</p><p>• Is it worth reconciling the 2?</p><p>-Yes: for the sake of combining a well-defined model with a rich XML infrastructure -A need for the TEI to have a terser model</p><p>• Curation, interchange, tools, automatic generation of TEI constructs</p><p>• Is it just possible.</p><p>-Yes: and now!</p><p>The need for a revision   -Sub-setting the TEI guidelines    The TEI is doing well -the hidden TEI  -Thinking together the sustainability of TEI material</p><p>• Repositories (Tapas)</p><p>• The TEI already offers a strong basis for sustainability</p><p>• A basis for data publications? Exploring new scholarly communication models</p><p>• Open Access -Open access to scholarly papers is on its way (nearly!) -Encouraging scholars to disseminate their research data in the same conditions</p><p>• Despite fears (plagiarism?) or unstable technical settings </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>--</head><label></label><figDesc>May depend on types of data and specific collections• Dissemination Technical requirements, citation rules, associated publications • Enrichments -Re-use, hosting and visibility of scholarly work -Aiming jointly at improving quality of digital resources Perspectives • Timeline -Charter outline -Setting up a round table with representatives of all types of stakeholders -Online prototype with first participants -Official kick-off in conjunction with the IFLA conference in 2017 • Making the charter a reference communication tool for CHI's and scholars -Strong collaboration needed with: Europeana, Clarin and E-RIHS -Support from the Parthenos and Iperion project STANDARDISATION IN DARIAH AND PARTHENOS Standards, standards, everywhere… • Standards: non legally binding documents produced by organisation ensuring -International consensus building (not a one person's/one group's work) -Communication (standards cannot be internal to an organisation) -Maintenance (evolution according to users' needs, technology change etc.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>---••-•--</head><label></label><figDesc>Read: http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/DS.html• TEI architecture: modules, classes • TEI vocabulary: more than 500 elements… -Read: http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html TEI as a standardization body (1) • Consensus building -Community based decision process • Maintenance Two releases per year • Publication -All TEI contents are available under the double CC-BY+BSD 2 clause license.TEI as a standardization body (2)• Organization Consortium of institutional and individual members -Conference, journal (jTEI)• The TEI at work -Board: administrative aspects -Technical council: coordinates the evolution of the TEI guidelines Standardization work Community based workflow -Mailing list -GitHub -bugs and features• Recording all issues and decisions -Cf. ODD as a specification platform• Deliverables -Documentation -TEI guidelines (more than 500 elements) -Schemas -DTD, RelaxNG, W3C• Additional resources -Tools • Online customization: Roma • Online processing: OxGarage • Stylesheets (included in Oxygen) -Examples -TEI by Example Special Interest Groups (SIGs)• Computer-Mediated Communication (Michael Beißwenger) • Correspondence. (Peter Stadler and Joachim Veit) • Education (TBA) • Libraries (Stefanie Gehrke and Kevin Hawkins) • Manuscripts (Dot Porter and Gerrit Brüning) • Music (Raffaele Viglianti) • Ontologies (Oyvind Eide and Christian-Emil Ore) • Scholarly Publishing (Daniel O'Donnell) • TEI for Linguists (Piotr Bański and Andreas Witt) • Text and Graphics (John Walsh and Martin de la Iglesia) • Tools (Serge Heiden) Varieties of TEI Conformance • Pure TEI-all subset -Most TEI projects • TEI subset with extensions -E.g. adding TBX terminologies in TEI• Non TEI document with TEI constructs (defined as an ODD)-EAG extensions in the EU Cendari project• Non TEI document defined by means of an ODD document -E.g. ISO 24616:2012 Language resources management --Multilingual information framework The central role of customization • Each TEI project starts with the definition of a customisation -Module selection -Sub-setting elements -Reducing possible values or content models -Adding, when necessary, new descriptive object • ODD as the technical platform for customization Consequences • Family of formats -Comparison of two TEI-based projects through their ODDs • Support for third-party projects -In-house maintenance of customization and documentation • E.g. DTAbF at the Berlin Brandenburg Academy of Sciences -Even non TEI application! • E.g. EAD n ODD • Does not prevent one from knowing the TEI components… -Most projects can live with just a subset of the TEI ontology • With the strong possibility to impact on the guidelines themselves -E.g. &lt;abstract&gt; TEI: RETURN TO THE FUTURE TEI: you're not alone… • The hidden TEI: scientific information at the European Patent Office • New components in the TEI: &lt;standOff&gt; • Working with others: ISO LMF SCIENTIFIC INFORMATION? Characterising scientific documents • Expert documents describing a specific scientific and technical progress with respect to the state of the art • Three main domains -Scholarly publications -Standardisation documents -Patents • Some common characteristics -Authorship: the basis of scientific attribution -Structure: usually a formal internal organisation -Vocabulary: technical terms are essential to convey (or hide) meaning -Network of references: relating to the state of the art -Certification: workflow, responsibilities, metadata Authorship Publications -The essence of publishing • Importance of attribution • Reflects the context and time of the research (project, affiliation, biography) • The hidden hand of reviewers Patents -A variety of roles • Applicant/inventor/representati ve • Opponents • … and examiners Standards -Priority to the institution • Consensus building =&gt; large expert group • ISO: no authors but project leaders • W3C: editors Workflow Publications -Semi-formal • Traditional (vestigial?) concept of peer-review • From author's initial manuscript to publisher's version • Evolution in the role of each version (e.g. prior art) Patents -Very formal • Review by patent examiners • Coordination of multiple submissions: national, US, Europe, etc. • Importance of initial submission date Standards -Very formal • Decision process reflecting membership structure • ISO: WD, CD, DIS, FDIS, IS • One single reference document The European Patent Office • The European one-stop shop for patent applications • Examination of each application by experts from the field (examiners) -Based on existing patents as well as scholarly publications (aka Non Patent Literature) • Some figures -Several thousands of examiners -200 million documents -2 billion annotations… The (simplified) patent life-cycle • Patent application in one or several patent offices -USPTO, Japan, EPO (directly or initiated in a specific country) -First application: reference date for the patent ("coming into force") -Form a "Patent family" • Examination process for one application -Search report, communications, decision, appeal, opposition -Patent documents may be revised at each stage • Necessity to have a single model for dealing with all stages and versions • The TEI appeared to be the optimal Intertwined with the source text Stand off annotation: Source text is referenced from outside Embedded stand off annotation: Stand off annotations attached to the same document as the source Why embedded stand-off annotation? • In line (!) with the TEI philosophy • Each time the source document is seen as the reference organisational unit -Corpus management -Transmission workflow -Multiple annotation layers -Competing annotations • E.g. Manual vs. automatic annotation Standoff: A long-standing issue • The idea of standoff annotation is not new in general -Thompson &amp; McKelvie, 1997 Standoff annotation has been a core concept in the TEI guidelines since the beginning -Cf. Chapter: Linking, Segmentation, and Alignment -Availability of &lt;anchor&gt;, &lt;span&gt;, &lt;interp&gt;, &lt;link&gt;, @ana • But: not integrated in the TEI architecture -Stand-off elements can appear anywhere in a TEI document -Usual trade-off between on-site vs. grouping (&lt;back&gt;) • The NLP community has also developed its own means -GraF (Ide &amp; Suderman 2007) , Paula (Zeldes et al. 2009), etc. • Need for a proper, and inclusive, treatment of standoff annotations in the TEI -Better integration, more guidance Embedded standoff: Basic concept • Building up an autonomous document containing primary source and additional annotations Annotations are conveyed with their specific meta-data -Annotations have their specific place in the TEI document architecture -Standoff annotations may be recursively organized -Standoff annotations may point to textual as well as facsimile content -Well-defined elementary annotation units -Coherence with existing models (Open Annotation, ISO TC 37) should be ensured • Typical use-cases Named entity recognition, keyword/terms extraction -Human annotations on a document • critical editions, patent examination, peer review… • Strong relation with interlinear annotation Timeline • 2011: Paper by Thomas Schmidt in jTEI (https://jtei.revues.org/142) • August 2012: new tickets by Javier Pose (EPO) • January 2014: Workshop in Berlin -Draft of a first proposal -Setting-up a github environment • 2012-2016: ISO 24624 project (Editor: Thomas Schmidt) Need for a annotation grouping component (&lt;annotationBlock&gt;) • May 2015: Council meeting in Ann Arbor -Several updates to the proposal -Stabilisation of element names • March 2016: TEI release 6.0.0 New element &lt;annotationBlock&gt; for interlinear annotation • August 2016: publication of ISO 24624 Transcription of Spoken</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>•--</head><label></label><figDesc>Going towards a multi-part standard -Simplifying the editorial process (drafting, decision making, revising; various tempi) -Reflecting the needs of specific communities (modules, serialisation) Overview of the current plans • Resolution 2016-04.2 (WG 4) Multi-part development of LMF -Part 1: Core model -Part 2: MRDs -Part 3: Diachrony-Etymology -Part 4: TEI serialisation -Part 5: LBX serialisation (Part 4) A TEI serialisation for LMF • Objective Preventing re-inventing element that already exist -Eliciting constraints on the TEI model • Method Covering core model and a selected number of extensions</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>Part 3) The case of etymology • A flat model in the current TEI chapter -No sense of etymon: &lt;mentioned&gt; -No sense of etymological process • Typed and recursive &lt;etym&gt; -No grouping of etymon related information</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Time to complement and consolidate the existing practices -TEI as reference framework -ISO as a precise standardisation background • Various ongoing projets and groups -Clarin Standards committee, DARIAH WG Lexical Resources, TEI LingSIG -COST E-NEL WG2, EU Parthenos • Joining efforts -Towards a single information space • Basecamp, GitHub, Blog • Exchanging information -Increasing participation as experts • ISO-TEI in particular WHITHER TEI?</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>-</head><label></label><figDesc>Code &lt;pron&gt;&lt;pc&gt;[&lt;/pc&gt;pakɔtij&lt;pc&gt;]&lt;/pc&gt;&lt;/pron&gt; &lt;gramGrp&gt;&lt;pos&gt;n.&lt;/pos&gt;&lt;gen&gt;f.&lt;/gen&gt;&lt;/gramGrp&gt; &lt;/form&gt; &lt;etym&gt;&lt;pc&gt;(&lt;/pc&gt;&lt;lang norm="es"&gt;esp.&lt;/lang&gt; &lt;oRef&gt;pacotilla&lt;/oRef&gt;&lt;pc&gt;)&lt;/pc&gt;&lt;/etym&gt; &lt;sense&gt; &lt;usg type="time"&gt;Autref.&lt;/usg&gt; &lt;pc&gt;,&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;def&gt;petit lot de marchandises que pouvaient embarquer les gens de l'équipage ou les passagers d'un navire&lt;/def&gt; &lt;pc&gt;.&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;/sense&gt; &lt;re&gt; &lt;form type="compound"&gt; &lt;orth&gt;De pacotille&lt;/orth&gt; &lt;/form&gt;&lt;pc&gt;,&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;sense&gt;&lt;def&gt;de peu de valeur, de qualité médiocre.&lt;/def&gt;&lt;/sense&gt; &lt;/re&gt; &lt;/entry&gt;CRF (Conditional Random Fields) based data mining Fine grained recognition of the various component of an entry in a legacy dictionaryUsing the TEI as reference output format (coordination with ENEL recommendations) Perspectives: Creating step by step a large-scale network (diachronic and synchronic) of our lexical patrimony • LAURENT ROMARY, MIKE MERTENS, ANNE BAILLOT, "DATA FLUIDITY IN DARIAH -PUSHING THE AGENDA FORWARD", MARCH 2016 (HTTPS://HAL.INRIA.FR/HAL-01285917/)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>TEXT ENCODING INITIATIVE: 30 YEARS OF ACCUMULATED WISDOM AND ITS POTENTIAL FOR A BRIGHT FUTURE 04</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">A quick historical overview TEI for digital scholarly work</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">• 1960's -GML (Generalized Markup Language) by IBM • 1970's &amp; 1980's -ANSI initiates project to develop a Standard text-• A trend towards digital curatorship</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">description language based on GML -Describing digital sources: meta-data</cell><cell>Text archives</cell></row><row><cell>Lou Burnard</cell><cell cols="2">Humanities Standards SGML Not intended -Understanding and representing the structure of • 1983 -SGML became an industry standard • 1986 -SGML (Standard Generalized Markup Language) becomes digital sources: content an ISO standard: ISO 8879:1986 -Enriching (annotations, links), versioning, • 1987 -TEI (Text Encoding Initiative) (immediately) for individual • 1990 -HTML 1.0 (HyperText Markup Language) disseminating</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">scholars • 1992 -TEI edition P3 (Michael Sperberg-McQueen and Lou • A wide user community Burnard, eds) -From individual scholars to large digitization • 1997/1998 -XML 1.0 (eXtensible Markup Language) (Tim Bray, Jean Paoli and Michael Sperberg-McQueen, eds) projects</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">04.04.2018</cell><cell>Seite 31</cell></row></table><note><p>• Thinking sustainable right from the onset -Our role as infrastructure THE .04.2018 Seite 28 In the beginning 1. Novembre 1987: Vassar College, Poughkeepsie</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>ALL YOU CAN ENCODE… Examples</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>•</cell><cell>Dear H. Everybody</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>is O.K. Mrs. Butler</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>from across the</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>street died last</cell></row><row><cell>• • •</cell><cell>• Source -surrogate -enrichment -publication • Recorded in the header; encoded in the content -Born digital documents may as well encounter a succession of changes/versions • The TEI document as an autonomous object in a DL workflow -Embedded meta-data + content • Favoring the semantics rather than the layout -Micro-structure: in-line annotation mechanisms -Larousse paragraphs/lists/figures/etc. -Meso-structure: divisions, • Dictionaries -Macro-structure: front-body-back -Towards Higher Ground • Document structure • Scholarly paper ePub, pdf, HTML, etc.) -Publication requires a transformation stage (XSLT; -The Little Riding Hood -(quasi) No presentational construct night. Too bad is not it? Goodbye • Simple encoded text S. W.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>-Multiple "hands": annotation • Dates, names, notes, references, foreign expressions, etc.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Remaining in the scope of the Print dictionary chapter • Extending scope if we feel there is a need from the potential TEI applications (e.g. syntax)</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>We are not bound to the existing chapter, even if we have to abide to the Birnbaum principle</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Gathering mapping proposals Once upon a time, the clergyman…</cell></row><row><cell>Component &lt;entry xml:lang="en"&gt; &lt;form type="lemma"&gt; Lexical Entry &lt;orth&gt;clergyman&lt;/orth&gt; &lt;gramGrp&gt;</cell><cell>TEI construct &lt;entry&gt;…&lt;/entry&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>Form &lt;pos&gt;commonNoun&lt;/pos&gt; Lemma &lt;/gramGrp&gt; &lt;/form&gt;</cell><cell>&lt;form&gt;…&lt;/form&gt; &lt;form type="lemma"&gt;…&lt;/form&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>Word Form &lt;form type="inflected"&gt; Syntactic Behaviour &lt;orth&gt;clergyman&lt;/orth&gt; &lt;gramGrp&gt;</cell><cell>&lt;form type="inflected"&gt;…&lt;/form&gt; ??</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">• Associating a definite TEI construct for each component of the LMF Meta-&lt;number&gt;singular&lt;/number&gt; &lt;etym&gt; &lt;/gramGrp&gt; model &lt;/form&gt; • Adding constraints when necessary -(e.g. @xml:lang mandatory on &lt;entry&gt;?) Data category ?? &lt;form type="inflected"&gt; TEI construct &lt;orth&gt;clergymen&lt;/orth&gt; -Complementing the TEI /PartOfSpeech/ &lt;pos&gt; &lt;gramGrp&gt; • Defining new constructs (or elements?) if necessary /Gender/ &lt;number&gt;plural&lt;/number&gt; &lt;gen&gt; &lt;/gramGrp&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>… &lt;/form&gt;</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>How far should we go here? &lt;/entry&gt;</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>-</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Usage, grammatical constraints, source, date, language, etc.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Before-after example</cell></row><row><cell>Old school</cell><cell>Structured</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;etym&gt; &lt;lang&gt;Ahd.&lt;/lang&gt; &lt;mentioned&gt;âband&lt;/mentioned&gt;,</cell><cell>&lt;etym type="inheritance"&gt; &lt;cit type="etymon" xml:lang="goh"&gt; &lt;oRef&gt;âband&lt;/oRef&gt; &lt;lang&gt;Ahd.&lt;/lang&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;lang&gt;mhd.&lt;/lang&gt;</cell><cell>&lt;/cit&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;mentioned&gt;âbent&lt;/mentioned&gt;; &lt;bibl&gt;zur Etym. s. Kluge Mitzka 18. Aufl.</cell><cell>&lt;etym type="inheritance"&gt; &lt;cit type="etymon" xml:lang="gmh"&gt; &lt;oRef&gt;âbent&lt;/oRef&gt;</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">unter ,,Abend'', ferner Schwäb. Wb. 1, • A need for revision • Pushing a fully fledged model &lt;lang&gt;mhd.&lt;/lang&gt; &lt;/cit&gt; 11ff. Schweizdt. Wb. 1,34ff.&lt;/bibl&gt; &lt;/etym&gt; &lt;/etym&gt; &lt;bibl&gt;zur Etym. s. Kluge Mitzka 18.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Aufl. unter ,,Abend'', ferner Schwäb. Wb.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1, 11ff. Schweizdt. Wb. 1,34ff.&lt;/bibl&gt;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>&lt;/etym&gt;</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Imagining what the certification of research data could be -Building upon what other research fields have accheives (e.g. genomics)</figDesc><table /><note><p><p>• Scholarly recognition -Ensuring acknowledgement for the work carried out on digital sources</p>• A necessity to anticipate an evolving landscape -</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CODE NAME: LIVING SOURCES</head><p>Data "journals"</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>and sources Submissions: we need more than data</p><p>• (Lexical) Data cannot be evaluated in isolation</p><p>-A certain scientific perspective on the material, whether observed or compiled</p><p>• A preface will be requested with all submissions -Scientific background  • Various publication status:</p><p>word list, wordform collection, word field, language particular dictionary, comparative dictionary, etc. -Correspond to various quality levels Stage 3 -Living commentary and growth of data • (Identified) third party contributions -Commentaries -Additional entries or features?</p><p>• Issue: validation by authors and editorial board?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ISSUES RELATED TO IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>Repository and services </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interoperability and Standards</head><p>• Through Living Sources, data is offered a second-life -Data will be searched, modified, crossed with other sources</p><p>• Interoperability is thus a central issue =&gt; standards</p><p>• Scientific freedom vs. Limitation provided by standards -Need of flexible representation formats or models</p><p>• Documenting one's own practices and data semantics is essential -Cf. ODD mechanisms with TEI resources -Importance of helping scholars to retrieve legacy data</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Citability of data</head><p>• Various levels of granularity -Complete submission seen as a scientific contribution -Preface, or any of its components -Full lexical resources, or any entry thereof, down to specific feature</p><p>• Various types of usage -Referencing -Further processing (cross dictionary search, sub-selection of data, etc.)</p><p>• Technical answers -Unique identifier for the full submission -Selection recipes (à la XQuery) also stored in the repository  • Certification -Should this be taken up by professional stakeholders ?</p><p>• Outreaching -Easy to achieve through powerful academic dissemination forums (e.g. linguist List)</p><p>• Importance of a community-based (public) infrastructure</p><p>A feasible endeavour  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
