<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="fr">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Gabay</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hervé</forename><surname>Bohbot</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Francesca</forename><surname>Frontini</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Giancarlo</forename><surname>Luxardo</surname></persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A7BF4D13D4A59C601C9A2061E3B08481</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 20 Jun 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access archive for the deposit and dissemination of scientific research documents, whether they are published or not. The documents may come from teaching and research institutions in France or abroad, or from public or private research centers. L'archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est destinée au dépôt et à la diffusion de documents scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="fr">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Automatically Encoding Encyclopedic-like Resources in TEI</head><p>Mohamed Khemakhem<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref>,2,3 , Laurent Romary <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr">4</ref> {name.surname@inria.fr} 1 Inria ALMAnaCH, Paris <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Centre Marc Bloch, Berlin 3 Paris Diderot University, Paris 4 BBAW -Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin Simon Gabay {surname.name@unine.ch} Université de Neuchâtel -Institut de littérature française Hervé Bohbot, Francesca Frontini, Giancarlo Luxardo {name.surname@univ-montp3.fr} Univ Paul Valéry Montpellier 3, CNRS, PRAXILING UMR 5267 Encyclopedic content exists in different forms of paper-based resources and remains to a very large extent not exploited given the limited alternatives to extract information from the corresponding digitized material. Where TEI has provided mechanisms for encoding such a content, recent works have yielded advanced techniques to apply these mechanisms automatically on raw resources, however clear recommendations for the encoding of such content is still lacking.</p><p>As current digitization projects concern encyclopedias, other projects are undertaken to digitize textual resources with heritage significance and with similar features in terms of layout and indexed access. In this paper we introduce new lexicographic models, customizing the TEI schema, we extend existing ones and we present their application on two categories of resources, currently under development to be made available for public use:</p><p>• Encyclopedic sections of early, out of copyright, versions of a reference French Dictionary (Petit Larousse Illustré), • Manuscripts auction catalogues, which are old resources for referencing and semantically describing manuscripts for sale.</p><p>The definition of these models is based on the significant similarities noticed at different levels of the described information in such entry-based resources. We have employed elements from the TEI dictionaries module to enable the segmentation of morphological and semantic information encompassed by respectively &lt;form&gt; and &lt;sense&gt; elements, already extracted by dedicated existing models in GROBID-Dictionaries 1 's architecture. In fact, each entry in both types of resources carries two main encyclopedic information. First, the name or the label of a concept, coupled with one or more of its extended form and coming sometimes with a brief description. Then, a second block comes to establish an exhaustive description of the concept and to present related information such as bibliography or pricing. In addition, we have used a customized version of the &lt;entry&gt; element to allow the generic encoding of entry numbering (see second excerpt in the table below).  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TEI encoding</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Ch.-L. de)&lt;/addName&gt;, &lt;desc&gt;le plus brillant général de cavalerie des guerres de la République et de l'EmpIre, né à Metz, tué à la bataille de Wagram&lt;/desc&gt; &lt;/form&gt; &lt;sense&gt; .-&lt;def&gt; &lt;bibl&gt;L. a. s. au général Dugua; 1 p. inf.&lt;/bibl&gt; &lt;num type="price"&gt;10 »&lt;/num&gt; &lt;/def&gt; &lt;note&gt;Superbe lettre sur la campagne d'Egypte. Il profite du départ du général Desaix pour lui donner des nouvelles. Desaix lui laisse le commandement de la colonne qui doit poursuivre Mourad-Bey, et qui se compose de 400 hommes de cavalerie, 4 pièces de canon et 160 dromadaires. Le général Boyer a, dans une petite affaire, tué 10 mameloucks et 40 arabes, etc.&lt;/note&gt; &lt;/sense&gt; &lt;/entry&gt;</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Excerpt from Dictionary Encyclopedic Section in Petit Larousse Illustré (1948)</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>&lt;entry&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;form type="lemma"&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;persName&gt;ABERDEEN&lt;/persName&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;addName&gt;(G. H. Gordon, comte</cell></row><row><cell>d')&lt;/addName&gt;&lt;pc&gt;,&lt;/pc&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;desc&gt;homme d'Etat anglais, né à</cell></row><row><cell>Edimbourg&lt;/desc&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;/form&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;pc&gt;.&lt;/pc&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;sense&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;def&gt;Premier ministre en</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>1852, il conclut avec la France une alliance contre la Russie (1784- 1860)&lt;/def&gt; &lt;/sense&gt; &lt;pc&gt;.&lt;/pc&gt; &lt;/entry&gt; ِ ◌Excerpt from a Manuscripts Auction Catalogue (1889)</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>&lt;entry&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;num&gt;49&lt;/num&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;form type="lemma"&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;surName&gt;Kourakin&lt;/surName&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;addName&gt;(le prince Alexis</cell></row><row><cell>B.),&lt;/addName&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;desc&gt; frère du précédent, homme d'Etat</cell></row><row><cell>russe.&lt;/desc&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;/form&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;sense&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;pc&gt;-&lt;/pc&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;def&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;bibl&gt;Billet auto sig., en francais, à M.</cell></row><row><cell>Monférand, 1 p, in-8.&lt;/bibl&gt; &lt;num type="price"&gt;2</cell></row><row><cell>»&lt;/num&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;/def&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;/sense&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;/entry&gt;</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>https://github.com/MedKhem/grobid-dictionaries/</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We employed the adapted and newly defined models to automatically process and label the encyclopedic information in a cascading fashion, as introduced in Khemakhem et al. 2017 and <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Khemakhem et al. 2018</ref>, by relying on the same sequence labeling machine learning technique.</p><p>We will present in-depth our progress in implementing morphological and semantic models and show through the results at each structuring level how such information could be uniformly encoded and automatically extracted from these resources.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Automatic Extraction of TEI Structures in Digitized Lexical Resources using Conditional Random Fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Luca</forename><surname>Foppiano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-09">2017. Sep 2017</date>
			<pubPlace>Leiden, Netherlands</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Enhancing Usability for Automatically Structuring Digitised Dictionaries. GLOBALEX workshop at LREC 2018</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Axel</forename><surname>Herold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-05">May 2018</date>
			<pubPlace>Miyazaki, Japan</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Presenting the Nénufar Project: a Diachronic Digital Edition of the Petit Larousse Illustré. GLOBALEX 2018 -Globalex workshop at LREC</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hervé</forename><surname>Bohbot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Francesca</forename><surname>Frontini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Giancarlo</forename><surname>Luxardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-05">2018. May 2018</date>
			<pubPlace>Miyazaki, Japan</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
