<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="fr">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">SSK by example. Make your Arts and Humanities research go standard</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marie</forename><surname>Puren</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Charles</forename><surname>Riondet</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dorian</forename><surname>Seillier</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lionel</forename><surname>Tadjou</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">SSK by example. Make your Arts and Humanities research go standard</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">C6C1A6BFD139133C440D83D7A1818B2B</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 25 Jul 2018 Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution| 4.0 International License</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access archive for the deposit and dissemination of scientific research documents, whether they are published or not. The documents may come from teaching and research institutions in France or abroad, or from public or private research centers. L'archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est destinée au dépôt et à la diffusion de documents scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="fr">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A standardized data model</head><p>The scenarios are described using the TEI format (Text Encoding Initiative). All the information displayed within the SSK proceed from TEI files :</p><p>• A scenario is a list of events (&lt;tei:listEvents&gt;) • Each step in a scenario is an event (&lt;tei:event&gt;)</p><p>• TEI files are all available on GitHub (https:// github.com/ParthenosWP4/SSK) • The documentation is also available (https:// parthenoswp4.github.io/SSK/SSKspec.html)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>THE SSK NEEDS YOU !</head><p>Start contributing to the SSK by adding new scenarios on GitHub and soon directly on the interface.</p><p>Make your Arts and Humanities research go standard.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SSK by example</head><p>Marie Puren, Charles Riondet, Laurent Romary, Dorian Seillier, Lionel Tadjou</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>https://ssk-application.parthenos.d4science.org/ssk/#/ ssk@inria.fr The Standardization Survival Kit The « research scenarios » The Standardization Survival Kit is a collection of research use cases (the « scenarios ») illustrating digital best practices in Digital Humanities and Heritage research. Gain efficiency, interoperability and sustainability by using standards ! Guidelines and tools are easier to understand and use when presented through examples. The SSK provides a variety of standardized procedures and resources in a meaningful context. The research scenarios help you identify the most useful material to help you carry out your research project, step by step. Browse research scenarios corresponding to your research project, follow the steps and find the most fitted resources &amp; standards ! PARTHENOS is funded by Hoziron2020 of the European Commission. The project started on 1 May 2015 and runs for 48 months.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
