<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="fr">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Diachronic Digital Edition of the Petit Larousse illustré</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Herve</forename><surname>Bohbot</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexandre</forename><surname>Faucher</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Francesca</forename><surname>Frontini</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Agata</forename><surname>Jackiewicz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Giancarlo</forename><surname>Luxardo</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Agnès</forename><surname>Steuckardt</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Diachronic Digital Edition of the Petit Larousse illustré</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1CC584A8A2100D4320106CF49238F012</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 13 Sep 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:02+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access archive for the deposit and dissemination of scientific research documents, whether they are published or not. The documents may come from teaching and research institutions in France or abroad, or from public or private research centers. L'archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est destinée au dépôt et à la diffusion de documents scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="fr">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>• The Petit Larousse illustré is the only French dictionary to be updated every year, since it was first published in 1905 (coined 1906). • Handy and affordable, with each edition selling several hundreds of thousands copies <ref type="bibr">(Pruvost, 2002)</ref>, one Petit Larousse may virtually be found in every French household. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>WEB site</head><p>Targeting both scientific (linguists, historians, lexicographers, social scientists) and general public.</p><p>Simple and advanced research criteria, user friendly interface, responsive design. Public release in July 2018 with 1906 to 1924 editions, then new data will be regularly added.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ontolex-Lemon RDF</head><p>Natural language processing applications and linking to other resources. Users: language technologists, computer scientists.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TEI XML</head><p>Reference digital edition format. For long-term preservation and expert querying. Les différents appareils qui ont été utilisés jusqu'ici peuvent être classés en trois catégories distinctes : les &lt;mentioned&gt;orthoptères&lt;/mentioned&gt;, les &lt;mentioned&gt;hélicoptères&lt;/mentioned&gt;, les &lt;mentioned&gt;aéroplanes&lt;/mentioned&gt;. &lt;/note&gt; &lt;/sense&gt; &lt;/entry&gt; <ref type="bibr">1948</ref><ref type="bibr">-1954</ref><ref type="bibr">1906</ref><ref type="bibr">-1947</ref><ref type="bibr">From 1955</ref> Nénufar project name stands for Nouvelle édition numérique de fac-similés de référence. This name was chosen after a typically French polemic between supporters and opponents of some orthographic modifications of the French language. Amongst others, it was proposed that the waterlily (Nymphaea L.), should be spelled nénufar instead of nénuphar, which was perceived by some conservative people as an aggression towards the language integrity… However, it was actually the original, forgotten spelling, as it could be seen in not so old and common dictionaries like Petit Larousse (see below). There was clearly a gap to be filled, in order to bring to light recent evolutions of the language.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Users: digital humanists, computational linguists. The use of TEI-LEX0 format(Banski et al., 2017)  will allow for a predictable structure and for the exploitation of ad hoc digitisation technologies such as GROBID-Dictionaries (Khemakhem et al., 2017) Nénufar project is headed by laboratoire Praxiling at Paul-Valéry University of Montpellier in collaboration with Inria. It is supported by the Délégation Générale à la Langue Française et aux Langues de France (an agency of French Culture and Communication Ministry) and the Huma-Num consortia CORLI and CAHIER. id='aviation' n='1906-001_1912-075'&gt; &lt;form type='lemma'&gt; &lt;orth&gt;AVIATION&lt;/orth&gt; &lt;pron&gt;(&lt;emph rend='italic'&gt;si-on&lt;/emph&gt;)&lt;/pron&gt; &lt;/form&gt; &lt;gramGrp&gt;&lt;pos&gt;n.&lt;/pos&gt; &lt;gen&gt;f.&lt;/gen&gt;&lt;/gramGrp&gt; &lt;etym&gt;(du &lt;lang expand='latin'&gt;lat.&lt;/lang&gt; &lt;mentioned&gt;avis&lt;/mentioned&gt;, &lt;gloss&gt;oiseau&lt;/gloss&gt;).&lt;/etym&gt; &lt;sense&gt; &lt;def&gt;Vol des oiseaux.&lt;/def&gt; &lt;/sense&gt; &lt;sense&gt; &lt;def&gt;Navigation aérienne.&lt;/def&gt; &lt;note type='encycl'&gt;-L'aviation désigne surtout la locomotion aérienne faite à l'aide d'un véhicule plus lourd que l'air. On a déjà fait de nombreuses tentatives à ce sujet, mais le problème n'est pas encore résolu.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>• Editions published prior to 1948 are public domain according to French laws, however, no open full text resource is currently available.</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Info: projet-nenufar@univ-montp3.fr</p><p>Data will be published under CC-BY license. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
