<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D58C3FD6648176A8F893FCA4DE32BD2D</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T14:59+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Why are we here today?</p><p>• Appel de Jussieu: http://jussieucall.org -"This Call is aimed at scientific communities, professional associations and research institutions to promote a scientific publishing open-access model fostering bibliodiversity and innovation without involving the exclusive transfer of journal subscription monies to APC payments."</p><p>• What it is about:</p><p>-Writing practices, peer-review procedures, editorial services on content, additional services (TDM...), business models </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OUR ORGANISATIONAL LANDSCAPE</head><p>A hitchhiker's guide to the French higher education and research landscape   • ADBU (Association des directeurs et personnels de direction des bibliothèques universitaires et de la documentation)</p><p>-Coordination of managerial staff in university libraries</p><p>• EPRIST (responsables de l'information scientifique et technique des organismes de recherche français) • ABES (Agence bibliographique de l'enseignement supérieur)</p><p>-Coordinating information flows for higher education institution (e.g. central catalogue, PhD theses deposit)</p><p>• OpenEdition -Publishing tools for human and social sciences: books, journals, blogs, events</p><p>• Persée -Portal of digitized legacy journals in human and social sciences</p><p>• Huma-Num -Data infrastructure for the social and human sciences</p><p>• CCSD -HAL! … and a couple of other things.</p><p>• Collaborating infrastructures working for the community as a whole</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HAL -A CENTRAL REPOSITORY INFRASTRUCTURE</head><p>The infrastructure at our service CCSD (Centre pour la Communication Scientifique Directe), a joint service unit of: -Article 30: Open access  • Various additional priorities, but note:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">• CNRS • Inria • INRA • Université de</formula><p>-The creation of an "Open Science" certification for postgraduate schools -The compilation of public datasets on -"ANR requires that the full text publications resulting from projects that it finances be deposited in open access either directly in HAL or via a local institutional archive"</p><p>• And they signed "Plan S" as well as the DORA declaration…</p><p>Application: HCERES on HAL</p><p>• Plans to require that assessment campaigns be based on publications available in HAL -Communication from Michel Cosnard, January 2018</p><p>• Publishes its own assessment reports on HAL:</p><p>https://hal-hceres.archives-ouvertes.fr -OK, no licences yet, more evangelization to come -Frontiers (17%), PLOS (19%)</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">A</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>• Too French… ?</p><p>• The obvious advantage of coordination -Cheap and efficient management of a central publication repository -Sharing publishing experiments -Keeping our hope in public infrastructures for research</p><p>• Should we join forces?</p><p>Merci pour votre attention ! "Scientific research is a common good that we must share with everyone."</p><p>Frédérique Vidal, July 2018</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Concrete measures to re-use saved Springer budget at Université de Lorraine: • SSH: Subscription to open and public platforms (OpenEdition,France; Erudit, Canada, Open Library of Humanities, UK) • STM: Sci-Post (physics), EDP Sciences (France), Epiga (overlay journal on Episciences.org) • Joining the Fair Open Access Alliance • Support to Directory of Open Access Journals -DOAJ, Coalition of Open Access Repositories -COAR, Sparc Europe • Note: favouring free for authors-free for readers approaches</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>ultimate PDF to XML tool "Converting PDF to XML is a bit like converting hamburgers into cows. You may be best off printing it and then scanning the result through a decent OCR package." Michael Kay (http://lists.xml.org/archives/xml-dev/200607/msg00509.html) Inspired from: Duncan Hull Sciencesconf.org -a conference management tool Services • Online conference management tool • Abstracts, full paper, peer review, conference program, registration • Over 6000 conferences so far Technologies • Modular services • Unique authentication system • Connection to HAL authorities • Upload to HAL Library support • Supervises the creation of a conference instance • Create conference series • Moderates the integration of the papers as a collection in HAL Episciences.org -an overlay journal platform Services • Overlay certification environment • Post publication peer review • "Traditional" reviewing environment • Invited editors -special issues Technologies • OAI-PMH interface with repositories • Publication: arXiv, HAL, CWI • Data: Nakala, Ortolang • Versioning • Cataloguing facilities Library support • Setting up new journals • Editorial support • Experimenting new usages: e.g. Published on 7 October 2016 • Two main articles:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>costs for electronic acquisitions from university libraries and research institutions,• article and book publishing charges, and • research funding for calls for projects and their beneficiaries.Application: ANR policy • Explicit reference to open access in the 2019 action plan (26 July 2018) -Abiding to the loi Pour une République numérique and the open science policy of 4 July 2018 • « l'ANR [..] demande que toutes les publications consécutives aux projets qu'elle finance, soient déposées en texte intégral dans une archive ouverte, soit directement dans HAL soit par l'intermédiaire d'une archive institutionnelle locale. » • http://www.agence-nationale-recherche.fr/PA2019</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>•-•</head><label></label><figDesc>QUICK ZOOM ON INRIA Inria -a research organisation with a vision Vision for a scientific information policy • Maximising the dissemination of our scientific assets (visibility and swift dissemination of knowledge), for a reasonable price • Constitution of a reliable and sovereign institutional corpus (documentation, preservation, access), with clear public governance principles • Contribution to shaping the scientific communication landscape in terms of editorial processes and usage made of scientific productions Deposit mandate on all scientific publications (in HAL, CC-BY) Condition to appear in annual research reports -Comprising articles in gold open access journals • Central budget for APCs -Management of a national dashboard of costs and journals • Forbidding hybrid open access • Engaging in developing new publication models -Editorial support to Episciences based journals -Investment and support to Software Heritage • Printed material as disposable goods -Creation of a central collection of reference works -On going digitization project (on HAL) Less than 10% leaks for OA payment i.e. paid directly by research teams • Very good control of hybrid OA only two leaks in 2017 • 80% come from the bio-informatics domain • Main publishers (2014-2017):</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="31,0.00,155.00,720.00,229.57" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Open Science fund • Investing in open publishing systems that</head><label></label><figDesc>remain under the control of the scientific community • In line with the Appel de Jussieu • preprints, short-format manuscripts, data articles, open peer review, etc.</figDesc><table><row><cell>1. Generalizing Open Access to National plan for Open Science publications</cell></row><row><cell>• Issued 4th July 2018 by Frédérique Vidal, Ministre • Roadmap</cell></row><row><cell>-Make open access mandatory when publishing articles and books de l'Enseignement supérieur, de la Recherche et resulting from government-funded calls for projects. de l'Innovation Strong underlying principles: -Create an</cell></row><row><cell>• 50% publicly funded research "Open science seeks to create an ecosystem in which</cell></row><row><cell>• Any version of the author's manuscript scientific research is more cumulative, better supported</cell></row><row><cell>by data and more transparent with faster and more • Maximum of 6 month (STM), 12 months (SSH) embargo universal access to results." -Article 38: TDM • Aligning with the Open Government Partnership • For legally acquired material • We are still waiting for the implementation guidelines… (OGP)</cell></row></table><note><p>-Support</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>the HAL national open repository</head><label></label><figDesc>Create the position of Chief Data Officer and the corresponding network within the relevant institutions.-Create the conditions for and promote the adoption of an Open Data policy for scholarly papers.</figDesc><table><row><cell>2. Structure research data and make it</cell></row><row><cell>available through Open Access</cell></row><row><cell>• Roadmap</cell></row><row><cell>-Make open access dissemination mandatory for research data resulting from government-funded projects.</cell></row><row><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>• Additional priorities</cell></row><row><cell>-Assessment based upon quality, not quantity -explicit reference to</cell></row><row><cell>the San Francisco Declaration on Research Assessment (DORA)</cell></row><row><cell>-Recommending open licensing for publications and data</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2014" xml:id="foot_0"><p></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2015" xml:id="foot_1"><p></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2016" xml:id="foot_2"><p></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2017" xml:id="foot_3"><p></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
