<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">SKOS and TBX vocabularies</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Detlef</forename><surname>Reineke</surname></persName>
							<email>detlef.reineke@ulpgc.es</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Las Palmas de Gran Canaria</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
							<email>laurent.romary@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Inria, team ALMAnaCH</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">SKOS and TBX vocabularies</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F8E436F38C3E698060572BD38098A98D</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The following list contains the complete set of core SKOS elements as listed in section 2 of the W3C SKOS reference (W3C 2009a, 2) and the SKOS extension for labels (SKOS-XL) as described in Appendix B. The definitions are taken from both the W3C SKOS reference and from the SKOS Primer (W3C 2009b) 1 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SKOS core elements</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">skos:altLabel</head><p>Definition: Assigns an alternative lexical label to a concept. Note: A concept can have two alternative lexical labels, but no preferred lexical label. This is consistent with the SKOS data model, and there are no additional entailments which follow from the data model. However, many applications will require a preferred lexical label in order to generate an optimum human-readable display.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">skos:broader</head><p>Definition: Asserts that one concept is broader in meaning (i. e. more general) than another concept in the same concept scheme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3">skos:broaderTransitive</head><p>Definition: Supports inferring a transitive hierarchy from asserted &lt;skos:broader&gt; statements.</p><p>1 For some SKOS elements the W3C SKOS reference and the SKOS Primer lack clear-cut definitions. For the sake of conciseness, we created definitions for these elements from the descriptions of these two bibliographical resources.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4">skos:broadMatch</head><p>Definition: Used to state a hierarchical mapping link to a concept that is broader in meaning (i. e. more general) than another concept in another concept scheme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.5">skos:changeNote</head><p>Definition: Documents fine-grained changes to a concept, for the purposes of administration and maintenance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.6">skos:closeMatch</head><p>Definition: Used to link two concepts in different concept schemes that are sufficiently similar that they can be used interchangeably in some information retrieval applications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.7">skos:Collection</head><p>Definition: Defines meaningful groupings of concepts. Note: Collections can be used to represent "arrays" in thesaurus terminology, in which the term "milk by source animal", for example, is a "node label" that, however, does not represent a label for a concept in its own right.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.8">skos:Concept</head><p>Definition: Represents an idea, notion, a unit of thought. Note: What constitutes a unit of thought is subjective, and this definition is meant to be suggestive, rather than restrictive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.9">skos:ConceptScheme</head><p>Definition: Represents a group of carefully complied vocabularies, such as thesauri or classification schemes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.10">skos:definition</head><p>Definition: Supplies a complete explanation of the intended meaning of a concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.11">skos:editorialNote</head><p>Definition: Supplies information that is an aid to administrative housekeeping, such as reminders of editorial work still to be done, or warnings in the event that future editorial changes might be made.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.12">skos:exactMatch</head><p>Definition: Used to link two concepts, indicating a high degree of confidence that the concepts can be used interchangeably across a wide range of information retrieval applications.</p><p>1.13 skos:example Definition: Supplies an example of the use of a concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.14">skos:hasTopConcept</head><p>Definition: Used to link a concept scheme to the SKOS concept(s) which are topmost in the hierarchical relations for that scheme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.15">skos:hiddenLabel</head><p>Definition: A lexical label for a resource, where a KOS designer would like that character string to be accessible to applications performing text-based indexing and search operations, but would not like that label to be visible otherwise. Note: Hidden labels may for instance be used to include misspelled variants of other lexical labels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.16">skos:historyNote</head><p>Definition: Describes significant changes to the meaning or the form of a concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.17">skos:inScheme</head><p>Definition: Links concept schemes and concepts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.18">skos:mappingRelation</head><p>Definition: Used to state a mapping relation between two concepts of two different concept schemes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.19">skos:member</head><p>Definition: Links a concept to a specific collection of concepts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.20">skos:memberList</head><p>Definition: Used together with &lt;skos:OrderedCollection&gt; to define an ordered collection of concepts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.21">skos:narrower</head><p>Definition: Asserts that one concept is narrower in meaning (i. e. more specific) than another concept in the same concept scheme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.22">skos:narrowerTransitive</head><p>Definition: Supports inferring a transitive hierarchy from asserted &lt;skos:narrower&gt; statements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.23">skos:narrowMatch</head><p>Definition: Used to state a hierarchical mapping link to a concept that is narrower in meaning (i. e. more specific) than another concept in another concept scheme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.24">skos:notation</head><p>Definition: Used to assign a notation as a typed literal in the object position of the triple, where the datatype URI denotes a user-defined datatype corresponding to a particular system of notations or classification codes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.25">skos:note</head><p>Definition: Property for general documentation purposes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.26">skos:OrderedCollection</head><p>Definition: Used to define an ordered collection of concepts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.27">skos:prefLabel</head><p>Definition: Assigns a preferred lexical label to a resource.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.28">skos:related</head><p>Definition: Enables the representation of associative (non-hierarchical) links between concepts. Note: &lt;skos:related&gt; can also be used to represent part-whole links that are not meant as hierarchical relationships.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.29">skos:relatedMatch</head><p>Definition: Used to state an associative mapping link between to a concept in another concept scheme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.30">skos:scopeNote</head><p>Definition: Supplies some, possibly partial, information about the intended meaning of a concept, especially as an indication of how the use of a concept is limited in indexing practice.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.31">skos:semanticRelation</head><p>Definition: Defines a special class of semantic relations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.32">skos:topConceptOf</head><p>Definition: Used to link top concepts to a concept scheme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SKOS extension for labels (SKOS-XL)</head><p>1.33 skosxl:altLabel Definition: Used as resource for alternative labels. The property is analogous to the property of alt:hiddenLabel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.34">skosxl:hiddenLabel</head><p>Definition: Used as resource for hidden labels. The property is analogous to the property of skos:hiddenLabel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.35">skosxl:Label</head><p>Definition: Defines a special class of lexical entities, which can be linked to each other.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.36">skosxl:labelRelation</head><p>Definition: Used as an extension point which can be refined for more specific labeling scenarios.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.37">skosxl:literalForm</head><p>Definition: Instantiates the literal form of the label.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.38">skosxl:prefLabel</head><p>Definition: Used as resource for preferred labels. The property is analogous to the property of skos:prefLabel.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">TBX data categories</head><p>The following subset of terminological data categories is derived from withdrawn ISO 30042:2008 (see Annex C), since the new version of ISO 30042 (2019) does not include specifications for terminological data categories anymore. The data category specifications used in this list were taken on-to-one from the repository DatCatInfo<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">2</ref> which is referenced from ISO 30042:2019. For closed data categories, the permissible picklist values are listed.</p><p>In attribute style TBX, the data category names are usually instantiated as a value of a type attribute and thus written in camel case style. Picklist values are written in normal style, since these values are usually instantiated as text content of one of the core structure elements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">abbreviatedFormFor</head><p>Definition: A link element used to identify a relation between any abbreviated form of a word or term and its full or expanded form.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">administrativeStatus</head><p>Definition: The status of a term with respect to its assignment to an administrative level within a certain working environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• admitted: A term rated according to the scale of a term acceptability rating as a synonym for a preferred term.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>legal term admn-sts: A term that is legally defined and used in legally binding documents.</p><p>• not recommended: A term rated according to the scale of a term acceptability rating as undesired.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>obsolete: A term that is no longer preferred or admitted. • preferred: A term rated according to the scale of a term acceptability rating as the primary term for a given concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>regulated term admn-sts: A term defined by law or government regulation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>standardized term admn-sts: A term that has been standardized by a standardizing body.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">animacy</head><p>Definition: The characteristic of a word indicating that in a given discourse community, its referent is considered to be alive or to possess a quality of volition or consciousness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• animate: Perceived as alive. • inanimate: Perceived as not living. • other animacy: Perceived as related to animacy, but without specific reference to the previous items.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">annotatedNote</head><p>Definition: Is not provided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">antonymConcept</head><p>Definition: A concept which constitutes the opposite of the concept represented by a second term.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">antonymTerm</head><p>Definition: A term or lexeme whose concept or sense constitutes the opposite of the concept represented by a second term or lexeme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7">applicationSubset</head><p>Definition: An identifier assigned to a terminology entry associated with a specific application.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8">associatedConcept</head><p>Definition: A concept that exhibits a relation to the subject concept that can be established on the basis of nonhierarchical thematic connections.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.9">audio</head><p>Definition: Sound, spoken words, music, or other audible representation used to illustrate or explain terms or concepts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.10">broaderConceptGeneric</head><p>Definition: A concept two or more levels of abstraction higher than subject concept in a generic hierarchical concept system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.11">broaderConceptPartitive</head><p>Definition: A concept two or more levels of abstraction higher than subject concept in a part-whole or meronymic hierarchical concept system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.12">businessUnitSubset</head><p>Definition: An identifier assigned to a term or terminological record indicating its association with a specific department, division, or other unit of an enterprise.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.13">characteristic</head><p>Definition: An abstraction of a property of an object or of a set of objects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.14">classificationCode</head><p>Definition: A set of symbols, with rules for their application, used to represent classes and their interrelations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.15">conceptOrigin</head><p>Definition: The institution, locale, culture, country, or other venue from which a concept covered by a terminological entry originates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.16">conceptPosition</head><p>Definition: The position of a concept in a concept system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.17">context</head><p>Definition: A text which illustrates a concept or the use of a designation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.18">contextType</head><p>Definition: The characterization of a context according to a set of theoretical or pragmatic types.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• associative context: A context that contains the minimum amount of conceptual information needed to associate a concept to a particular concept field or sense of a word.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• defining context:</head><p>A context that contains substantial information about a concept, but that does not possess the formal rigor of a definition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• explanatory context:</head><p>A context that provides a summary explanation of a concept. • linguistic context: Context that illustrates the function of a term or word in discourse, but that provides no conceptual information. • metalinguistic context: Context consisting of a discourse about the term or word as a sign in such a way that it is used in an autonomous way.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• translated context:</head><p>A contextual text chunk that has been translated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.19">coordinateConceptGeneric</head><p>Definition: A subordinate concept having the same nearest superordinate concept and same criterion of subdivision as some other concept in a given generic concept system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.20">coordinateConceptPartitive</head><p>Definition: A subordinate concept having the same nearest superordinate concept and same criterion of subdivision as some other concept in a given partitive concept system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.21">corpusTrace</head><p>Definition: A notation indicating the location of an external contextual resource.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.22">crossReference</head><p>Definition: A pointer field or record used in a data collection to direct the user to another related location, e.g., another record.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.23">customerSubset</head><p>Definition: Is not provided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.24">databaseType</head><p>Definition: Is not provided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.25">date</head><p>Definition: The point of time at which a transaction or event takes place.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.26">definition</head><p>Definition: A representation of a concept by a descriptive statement which serves to differentiate that concept from related concepts. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.27">definitionType</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.28">directionality</head><p>Definition: A property of equivalent terms or senses of words indicating whether a similar degree of equivalence exists when moving from a first language to a second language as when moving from the second language to the first.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• bidirectional: Qualifier used with bilingual equivalent terms or word senses to indicate that a similar degree of equivalence exists when moving from a first language to a second language as when moving from the second language to the first. • incommensurate: Condition where the relation between the term in the source language and the term in the target language as translations is imperfect and should be used with care. • monodirectional: Qualifier used with bilingual equivalent terms or word senses to indicate that equivalence exists only when moving from a first language to a second language and not when moving from the second language to the first.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>undetermined directionality: The relation between the term in the source language and the term in the target language as translations has not been determined.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.29">domainExpert</head><p>Definition: Subject field specialist who provides information for a terminological entry, such as a definition or target language equivalent.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.30">elementIdentifier</head><p>Definition: An alphanumeric string that serves as the unique identifier of a language resource entry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.31">elementWorkingStatus</head><p>Definition: A code indicating the level of completeness and accuracy of an element (field, record, entry) within a language rersource collection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• archive element: An element that has been removed from active use in a database, but is archived for the purpose of retaining database history. • consolidated element: A completed element that has received final approval (sign-off) by the responsible terminologist. • exported element: An element that has been exported to another database, databases or to an interchange format.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>imported element: An element that originated as the result of data exchange with another database. • starter element: A truncated or incomplete initial working element.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>working element: An element that is substantially complete, but that has not yet been approved by the terminologist responsible for the element.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.32">entailedTerm</head><p>Definition: A term that is defined in another terminological entry in the same lexicon, glossary, terminology or vocabulary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.33">entrySource</head><p>Definition: A database or format from which data are imported.</p><p>• push button: Static text and/or graphic element appearing on a generally rectangular GUI shape that causes an application to perform some action when clicked.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• radio button:</head><p>The static text label representing a single choice within a set of mutually exclusive choices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• slider:</head><p>The static text label associated with a GUI control that lets users set a value on a continuous range of possible values, such as screen brightness, mouse-click speed or volume.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• spin box:</head><p>The static text label associated with a text box that incorporates a special control feature consisting of a pair of up-down buttons, whereby the user can type a dynamic text value directly into the control box or use the buttons to increase or decrease the value.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• tab:</head><p>The static text title or label that appears on a GUI "file divider tag" used to provide navigation between pages or sections of information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• table text:</head><p>A column heading control, also known as a header control, which displays a heading in a table.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• text box:</head><p>The static text label used to identify the purpose for a GUI box where a user can enter and edit text.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>tool tip: The static descriptive text (label) associated with a small context window displayed when the user moves the pointer over a control. • user defined type: Type of term location not included in the standard value domain for /term location/ that has been created as an ad hoc term location type by a user.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The characterization of a definition according to a set of theoretical or pragmatic types.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Picklist values:</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>extensional definition: A description of a concept by enumerating all of its subordinate concepts under one</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>criterion of subdivison.</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>intensional definition: A definition which describes the intension of a concept by stating the superordinate</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>concept and the delimiting characteristics.</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>partitive definition: A definition based on the enumeration of the concepts that refer to the main parts of an object</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>covered by a superordinate concept in a partitive relation.</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>translated definition: A definition that has been translated from another language.</cell></row></table><note><p>Definition:</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>In 2009, the standardized terminological data categories were moved from ISO 12620:1999 to the wiki-based registry ISOcat and a subset of these data categories was included in ISO</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>30042:2008.  In 2017, the data categories were transferred from ISOcat to the data category repository DatCatInfo hosted by the Language Terminology/Translation and Acquisition Consortium.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>"abbreviated form" itself can constitute a closed data category.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The present document is a compilation of the SKOS vocabulary and TBX data categories used for an ongoing research on the comparison between the SKOS and TBX data models. The lists are derived from [W3C 2009a] and [W3C 2009b] for SKOS and [LTAC 2019] for TBX. References Language Terminology/Translation and Acquisition Consortium (LTAC). 2019. "DatCatInfo." http://www.datcatinfo.net. World Wide Web Consortium (W3C). 2009a. "SKOS reference." http://www.w3.org/TR/skosreference. World Wide Web Consortium (W3C). 2009b. "SKOS Primer." https://www.w3.org/TR/skos-primer.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.34">environmentSubset</head><p>Definition: An identifier assigned to a terminology entry indicating its association with a specific computer environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.35">etymology</head><p>Definition: Information on the origin of a word and the development of its meaning.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.36">example</head><p>Definition: Descriptive material that provides a sample of an object or entity defined in the entry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.37">explanation</head><p>Definition: A statement that describes and clarifies a concept and makes it understandable, but does not necessarily differentiate it from other concepts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.38">externalCrossReference</head><p>Definition: URL or other URI for a resource that is external to the database or exchange file.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.39">falseFriend</head><p>Definition: A term or lexeme in one language that only appears to have formal or semantic similarity with a term or lexeme in another language, but that does not represent the same concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.40">figure</head><p>Definition: A diagram, picture, or other graphic material used to illustrate a concept or group of concepts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.41">frequency</head><p>Definition: The relative commonness with which a term occurs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• commonly used: Said of a term that appears frequently. • infrequently used: Said of a term that does not appear frequently.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>rarely used: Said of a term that is almost never used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.42">geographicalUsage</head><p>Definition: Lexeme or term usage reflecting regional differences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.43">grammaticalGender</head><p>Definition: A grammatical category that indicates grammatical relationships between words in sentences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• feminine: Of, relating to, or constituting the gender that ordinarily includes most words or grammatical forms referring to females. • masculine: Of, relating to, or constituting the gender that ordinarily includes most words or grammatical forms referring to males. • neuter: Of, relating to, or constituting the gender that ordinarily includes most words or grammatical forms referring to objects that are not characterized as male or female. • other gender: A gender designation that differs from the common genders.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.44">grammaticalNumber</head><p>Definition: In many languages, the grammatical distinction that indicates the number of objects referred to by the term or word.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• dual: The form used in some languages to designate two persons or things.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>mass noun: Designation of a term or word that is not countable and cannot generally be used with the indefinite article or in the plural.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>other number: Designation used to classify number-related grammatical information that can differ from the standard European classifications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• plural:</head><p>The form of a term or word (usually of a noun) used to designate more than one object.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• singular:</head><p>The form of a term or word (usually of a noun) used to designate one object.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.45">grammaticalValency</head><p>Definition: The range of syntactic elements either required or permitted by a lexical unit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.46">homograph</head><p>Definition: A word that is spelled like another, but that has a different pronunciation, meaning, and/or origin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.47">hyphenation</head><p>Definition: The division of a word in writing, such as at the end of a line, according to a given set of rules.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.48">indexHeading</head><p>Definition: A term chosen to be used in an index to represent an item or a concept in a document.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.49">keyword</head><p>Definition: A word or group of words, possibly in lexicographically standardized, i. e., lemmatized, form, taken out of a title or of the text of a document characterizing its content and enabling its retrieval.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.50">language-planningQualifier</head><p>Definition: A qualifier assigned to a provisional term within a language planning or descriptive terminology environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• new term: A term that is in the introductory phase of the standardization or language planning process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>non-standardized term: A candidate term that has not yet been introduced to the standardization or language planning process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>proposed term: A term used on a provisional basis for a concept for which no satisfactory term exists. • recommended term: A term that has been recommended by a subject specialist.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.51">lemma</head><p>Definition: The base form of a word or term that is used as the formal dictionary entry for the term.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.52">lionHotkey</head><p>Definition: Is not provided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.53">morphologicalElement</head><p>Definition: Unit resulting from the division of words into their smallest meaningful parts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.54">normativeAuthorization</head><p>Definition: A term status qualifier assigned by an authoritative body, such as a standards body or a governmental entity with a regulatory function.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• admitted term: A term rated according to the scale of a term acceptability rating as a synonym for a preferred term. • legal term: A term that is legally defined and used in legally binding documents. • preferred term: A term rated according to the scale of a term acceptability rating as the primary term for a given concept. • regulated term: A term defined by law or government regulation. • standardized term: A term that has been standardized by a standardizing body. • superseded term: A term that is no longer preferred or admitted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.55">note</head><p>Definition: A statement that provides further information on any part of a language resource entry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.56">noteSource</head><p>Definition: The source of a note that is expressed in a &lt;admin&gt; element having the type attribute value 'annotatedNote'.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.57">originatingInstitution</head><p>Definition: An institution (i. e., company, government agency, etc.) treated as a source of information for the purpose of bibliographic documentation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.58">originatingPerson</head><p>Definition: An individual treated as a source of information for the purpose of bibliographic documentation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.59">otherBinaryData</head><p>Definition: Any foreign data not covered by the previous categories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.60">partOfSpeech</head><p>Definition: A category assigned to a word based on its grammatical and semantic properties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• adverb: Part of speech used to refer to a heterogeneous group of words whose most frequent function is to specify the mode of action of the verb.</p><p>• noun: Part of speech assigned to words that designate a person, place, action, property or thing etc., that may have morphosyntactic properties like number or case and syntactic combination like modification by an adjective or determination by a determiner.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>other part of speech: One of the many parts of speech not normally included in the value domain for part of speech in terminological resources. • verb: Element which, singly or in combination with other verbs is used as the minimal predicate of a sentence, cooccurring with a subject.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.61">placeholder</head><p>Definition: An XML element used to delimit a sequence of native stand-alone codes in a segment, i. e., a term or string.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.62">processStatus</head><p>Definition: The status of a lexical unit or term with respect to its advancement within the standardization process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• finalized: The status of a lexical unit or term that has completed the standardization process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>provisionally processed: The status of a lexical unit or term that has completed all but the final stages of the standardization process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• unprocessed:</head><p>The status of a lexical unit or term that has not yet begun the standardization process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.63">productSubset</head><p>Definition: An identifier assigned to a product to which a term is related.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.64">projectSubset</head><p>Definition: An identifier assigned to a project indicating that it is associated with a term, record or entry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.65">pronunciation</head><p>Definition: The representation of the manner by which a term or word is articulated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.66">proprietaryRestriction</head><p>Definition: A restriction placed on a term for the purpose of protecting the right of an organization to the exclusive use of the term.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• service mark: Any word, name, symbol, device, or any combination, used, or intended to be used, in commerce, to identify and distinguish the services of one provider from services provided by others, and to indicate the source of the services. • trademark: A restriction on term usage based on the fact that the term is a device (such as a brand name) pointing distinctly to the origin or ownership of merchandise to which it is applied and legally reserved for the exclusive use of the owner as maker or seller.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>trade name: The name or style under which a concern does business.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.67">quantity</head><p>Definition: The value associated with a concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.68">range</head><p>Definition: The relationship between a set of limits within which a quantity is measured, as expressed by stating the lower and upper range values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.69">register</head><p>Definition: Classification indicating the relative level of language individually assigned to a lexeme or term or to a text type.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• bench-level register: The register of terms used in applications-oriented as opposed to theoretical or academic levels of language. • in-house register: The register of terms that are company-specific and not readily recognized outside that environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• neutral register:</head><p>The register appropriate to general texts or discourse. • slang register: An extremely informal register of a word, term, or text that is used in spoken and everyday language and less commonly in documents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• technical register:</head><p>The register appropriate to scientific texts or special languages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• vulgar register:</head><p>The register of a term or text type that can be characterized as profane or socially unacceptable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.70">relatedConcept</head><p>Definition: A concept that has an associative relation to another concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.71">relatedConceptBroader</head><p>Definition: A concept that is roughly broader at some level with respect to a related or associative concept, but without there comprising any clear-cut reference to a defined generic or partitive system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.72">relatedConceptNarrower</head><p>Definition: A concept that is roughly narrower at some level with respect to a related or associative concept, but without there comprising any clear-cut reference to a defined generic or partitive system of concepts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.73">reliabilityCode</head><p>Definition: A value from one to ten reflecting the reliability of a term or term-related information, whereby 1 reflects the least possible degree of reliability and 10 reflects the highest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.74">responsibility</head><p>Definition: An identifier assigned to the individual associated with a database management transaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.75">sampleSentence</head><p>Definition: A sentence composed (frequently by a terminologist or language planner) to illustrate the use of a word or term in context in cases where contextual information is unavailable, such as for a new term-concept pair.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.76">searchTerm</head><p>Definition: A term entered in a term entry for purposes of retrieval.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.77">securitySubset</head><p>Definition: An in-house security classification of a term.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• confidential: Security qualifier indicating that only authorized users can access an entry. • public: Security qualifier indicating that all users in a system can access an entry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.78">see</head><p>Definition: A pointer field used in a terminology or lexical collection as a direction from one location that does not contain information to the location(s) where information can be found.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.79">sequentiallyRelatedConcept</head><p>Definition: An associative relation based on spatial or temporal proximity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.80">shortFormFor</head><p>Definition: A linking element used to identify a relation between a short form and its full or expanded form.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.81">sortKey</head><p>Definition: A character string used for sorting and merging operations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.82">source</head><p>Definition: A complete citation of the bibliographic information pertaining to a document or other resource.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.83">sourceIdentifier</head><p>Definition: The information in a language resource entry which indicates the source documenting the lexical or terminological data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.84">sourceType</head><p>Definition: In multilingual and translation-oriented language resource or terminology management, the kind of text used to document the selection of lexical or terminological equivalents, collocations, and the like.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• background text: In multilingual and translation-oriented language resource or terminology management, a text written in the source language that provides linguistic and domain related information about the subject of the source text or texts being translated.</p><p>• parallel text: In multilingual and translation-oriented language resource or terminology management, a text written in the target language that provides either text-typological or linguistic and domain related information about the subject of the source text or texts being translated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.85">spatiallyRelatedConcept</head><p>Definition: A relation of dependence between concepts referring to objects based on their relative positions in space.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.86">subjectField</head><p>Definition: A field of special knowledge.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.87">subordinateConceptGeneric</head><p>Definition: A concept in a generic relation having the broader intension.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.88">subordinateConceptPartitive</head><p>Definition: A concept in a partitive relation viewed as one of the parts making up the whole.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.89">subsetOwner</head><p>Definition: An identifier assigned to the individual responsible for administering a subset of lexical or terminological records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.90">superordinateConceptGeneric</head><p>Definition: A concept in a generic relation having the narrower intension.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.91">superordinateConceptPartitive</head><p>Definition: A concept that has a partitive relation with the subject concept, and represents the sum of the parts; a comprehensive concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.92">syllabification</head><p>Definition: The division of a word reflecting its articulation by syllables, i. e., by uninterrupted units of pronunciation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.93">table</head><p>Definition: An array of data arranged in columns and rows used in documenting, explaining, or describing a concept within a terminology collection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.94">temporalQualifier</head><p>Definition: An attribution of a term or lexeme with respect to its use over time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• archaic form: A term or lexeme no longer in ordinary use, though retained for special purposes. • obsolete form: A term or lexeme which is no longer in common use.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• outdated form:</head><p>A term or lexeme that has fallen from fashion, but the meaning of which is readily recognizable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.95">temporallyRelatedConcept</head><p>Definition: A concept related to the subject concept through a sequential relation involving events in time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.96">term</head><p>Definition: A verbal designation of a general concept in a specific subject field.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.97">termElement</head><p>Definition: Any logically significant portion of a larger term.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.98">termLocation</head><p>Definition: Type of graphic feature on a GUI associated with a text string defined as a term in a localization-oriented terminology database.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• check box: The static text label associated with a square box used to set or clear a particular value or property in a graphic user interface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• combo box:</head><p>A commonly-used graphical user interface widget, comprising a combination of a drop-down list or list box and a single-line textbox, allowing the user to either type a value directly into the control or choose from the list of existing options.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• combo box element:</head><p>The dynamic text typed into the open text field associated with a combo box.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• dialog box:</head><p>The title text of a GUI interface box containing command buttons and other options through which users can carry out a particular command or task.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• group box:</head><p>The title or label of a GUI box containing a set of controls. • informative message: A short communicative text generated by a computer application or system and displayed by the interface intended to inform the user of errors, system status or the like.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• interactive message:</head><p>A communicative text generated by a computer application or system and displayed by the interface that requires or prompts a response of some sort from the use.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• menu item:</head><p>An individual text element used in a menu bar or drop-down menu list to represent a specific command for a computer application.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• progress bar:</head><p>The static text label associated with a horizontal GUI feature designed to indicate the progress or completion of a task by filling an "empty" bar with a contrast color, sometimes associated with an indication of estimated elapsed time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.99">termProvenance</head><p>Definition: Classification of a term according to the methodology employed in creating the term.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• loan translation: A term whose elements have been literally translated from the elements of a term in a foreign language. • neologism: A newly coined term. • transdisciplinary borrowing: A term taken from another subject field. • translingual borrowing: A term taken from a foreign language and perhaps naturalized.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.100">termStructure</head><p>Definition: The structure of the components of a term, indicated using square brackets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.101">termType</head><p>Definition: An attribute assigned to a term.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Picklist values:</head><p>• abbreviated form 3 : A term, appellation, or lexeme resulting from the omission of any part of the full term or appellation.</p><p>• abbreviation: An abbreviated form resulting from the omission of words or letters from the full form. • acronym: An abbreviated form resulting from the combination of initial letters or syllables (from each or some of the elements) of the full form and pronounced syllabically like a word. • clipped term: An abbreviated form resulting from the truncation of a part of a simple term. • contraction: An abbreviated form resulting from the shortening of a word, syllable, or word group by omission of a sound or letter and in some languages, the inclusion of an apostrophe. • initialism: An abbreviated form resulting from the combination of initial letters or syllables (from each or some of the elements) of the full form and pronounced letter by letter. • short form: An abbreviated form resulting from the omission of words from the full form. • appellation: A designation that represents an individual concept. • collocation: A recurrent word combination characterized by cohesion in that the components of the collocation must co-occur within an utterance or series of utterances, even though they do not necessarily have to maintain immediate proximity to one another. • common name: A synonym for an international scientific term that is used in general discourse in a given language. • entry term: A term that heads a terminological entry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>equation: An expression used to represent a concept based on a statement that two mathematical expressions are, for instance, equal as identified by the equal sign (=), or assigned to one another by a similar sign. • formula: Figures, symbols or the like used to express a concept briefly, such as a mathematical or chemical formula.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>full form: A term, appellation, or lexeme in its complete presentation (where there exists an abbreviated form). • idiom: A group of words in a fixed order that have a particular meaning that is different from the meanings of each word understood on its own. • internationalism: A term that has the same or nearly identical orthographic or phonemic form in many languages. • international scientific term: A term that is part of an international scientific nomenclature as adopted by an appropriate scientific body. • logical expression: An expression used to represent a concept based on mathematical or logical relations, such as statements of inequality, set relationships, boolean operations, and the like.</p><p>• part number: A unique alphanumeric designation assigned to an object in a manufacturing system. • phraseological unit: Any group of two or more words that are frequently expressed together and that consist of more than one concept, whereby individual words usually function in more than one grammatical category (part of speech) within the syntax of a sentence. • quasi-synonym: A term or lexeme that represents the same or a very similar concept as another term or lexeme in the same language, but for which interchangeability is limited to some contexts and is inapplicable in others. A phraseological unit in a language that expresses the same semantic content as another phrase in that same language. • transcribed form: A form of a term or lexeme resulting from an operation whereby the characters of one writing system are represented by characters from another writing system, taking into account the pronunciation of the characters converted. • transliterated form: A form of a term or lexeme resulting from an operation whereby the characters of an alphabetic writing system are represented by characters from another alphabetic writing system. • variant: A term, appellation, or lexeme in its alternative orthographic presentation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.102">thesaurusDescriptor Definition:</head><p>The term in a thesaurus that can be used to represent a concept in a document or in a request for retrieval.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.103">timeRestriction</head><p>Definition: The indication of a period of time during or since which a term was or has been subject to specified usage. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.104">transactionType</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.105">transferComment</head><p>Definition: Note included in a lexical entry or term entry providing information on the degree of equivalence, directionality or other special features affecting equivalence between a lexeme or term in one language and another lexeme or term in a second language.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.106">unit</head><p>Definition: A relationship to a reference value as defined by an authoritative body; a quantity measured.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.107">usageCount</head><p>Definition: The number of times an entry has been accessed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.108">usageNote</head><p>Definition: A note containing information on the usage of the associated word or term.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.109">video</head><p>Definition: Recorded visual images used to represent or illustrate terminological or conceptual information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.110">xAudio</head><p>Definition: Is not provided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.111">xGraphic</head><p>Definition: External graphic file.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.112">xMathML</head><p>Definition: A mathematical concept expressed in MathML.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.113">xSource</head><p>Definition: Is not provided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.114">xVideo</head><p>Definition: Is not provided.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
