<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Documenting application of lasers in conservation / restauration</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marta</forename><surname>Castillejo</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mikel</forename><surname>Sanz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Documenting application of lasers in conservation / restauration</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F74B94FF7505EFE4D0D30F24431F0EAE</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body/>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preserving 3D digital objects</head><p>The long-term preservation of 3D digital objects raises some critical issues. Indeed, firstly, different kind of data can be archived: the original files depending on the method used to digitize; the final version, depending on the goal (simple acquisition or modelisation) and any relevant information (text, images, pdf , scenarios ...) added for a better comprehension of the 3D object. Secondly it is important that metadata accompany the archive to ensure that the 3D object will be human-readable in the long-term. These metadata have to be completed in distinct files. The 3D consortium of Huma-Num developed a tool, aLTAG3D to easily produce metadata file for the full 3D archive. Lastly, a place to preserve 3D data in the long term has to be found. Many solutions exist, depending on the countries. In France, there are solutions such as the 3D conservatory for 3D data research for mid-term preservation, and the CINES in the continuity for long-term preservation. Enrich the 3D object with annotation and/or description based on existing Europeana format for metadata.</p><p>Bundle every needed file in an archive file and add related metadata. Use an application such as aLTAG3D in order to make the add of information easier, to reduce duplication and to generate an archive compliant with the long-term storage service.</p><p>Submit the packet to a long-term storage service, preferably an official academic public permanent structure (like CINES in France for instance). A standardized data model</p><p>The scenarios are described using the TEI format (Text Encoding Initiative). All the information displayed within the SSK proceed from TEI files :</p><p>• A scenario is a list of events (&lt;tei:listEvents&gt;) • Each step in a scenario is an event (&lt;tei:event&gt;)</p><p>• TEI files are all available on GitHub (https:// github.com/ParthenosWP4/SSK) • The documentation is also available (https:// ssk.readthedocs.io/en/latest/)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>THE SSK NEEDS YOU !</head><p>Start contributing to the SSK by adding new scenarios on GitHub and soon directly on the interface.</p><p>Make your Arts and Humanities research go standard.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SSK by example</head><p>Laurent Romary, Damien Biabiany, Klaus Illmayer, Marie Puren, Charles Riondet, Dorian Seillier, Lionel Tadjou</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
