<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="fr">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">TEI Encoding of a Classical Mixtec Dictionary Using GROBID-Dictionaries</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jack</forename><surname>Bowers</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">EPHE -École Pratique des Hautes Études</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">ACDH -Austrian Center for Digital Humanities</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
							<email>mohamed.khemakhem@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Paris Diderot</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Paris 7</addrLine>
									<postCode>UPD7</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">CMB -Centre Marc Bloch</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">BBAW -Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
							<email>laurent.romary@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Inria-ALMAnaCH -Automatic Language Modelling and ANAlysis &amp; Computational Humanities</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">EPHE -École Pratique des Hautes Études</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">ACDH -Austrian Center for Digital Humanities</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Paris Diderot</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Paris 7</addrLine>
									<postCode>UPD7</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">CMB -Centre Marc Bloch</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">BBAW -Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">TEI Encoding of a Classical Mixtec Dictionary Using GROBID-Dictionaries</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">686C08133A518B70BB1B2B588697B0BB</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 6 Aug 2019 Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution| 4.0 International License</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Mixtec</term>
					<term>TEI</term>
					<term>GROBID-Dictionaries</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access archive for the deposit and dissemination of scientific research documents, whether they are published or not. The documents may come from teaching and research institutions in France or abroad, or from public or private research centers. L'archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est destinée au dépôt et à la diffusion de documents scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="fr">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction to the Resource</head><p>This paper presents the creation of a TEI dictionary of the earliest lexical resource 1 of a Mixtec language: the Vocabulario published by the Dominican fray Francisco Alvarado in the year 1593 2 . This resource was automatically converted from PDF format to a structured TEI dictionary using application of GROBID-Dictionaries <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Khemakhem et al. 2017</ref><ref type="bibr">, Khemakhem et al. 2018a</ref><ref type="bibr">, Khemakhem et al. 2018b</ref><ref type="bibr">, Khemakhem et al. 2018c</ref>), an open source machine learning system for automatically structuring print dictionaries in 1 Not including the codices which were pictographic and not specific to any local variety of Mixtec. Though the author did not represent all the features of the language such as tone, nasalization among other features is resource is thus the first with any representation of the phonetic characteristics of a Mixtecan Language <ref type="bibr">(Jansen &amp; Perez Jiménez, 2009</ref>). 2 This document was likely compiled from the few existing resources at the time, namely the Doctrina en Lengua Mixteca by fray Benito Hernández published in 1567 and 1568 respectively from sources compiled in Teposcolula Mexico <ref type="bibr">(Jansen &amp; Perez Jiménez, 2009)</ref>. digital format into TEI (Text Encoding Initiative). The PDF source used in the transformation is from a re-organized and modernized version of the historical dictionary published by <ref type="bibr">Jansen and Perez Jiménez (2009)</ref>. The TEI dictionary produced contains roughly 26,600 entries and related entries.</p><p>The Mixtec variety sampled by Alvarado to create this vocabulary was that of Yucu Ndaa (Teposcolula) dzaha dzavui<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">3</ref>, which according to the sources is thought to have been used as a lingua franca of the Mixteca region at the time and the language is presently in the field of Mixtecan commonly referred to as "Classical Mixtec" or "Colonial Mixtec" <ref type="bibr">(Jansen &amp; Perez Jiménez 2009)</ref>.</p><p>The vocabulary was produced by the Orden de los Predicadores (O.P.) aka. the Dominican Order, who wanted to learn the language as part of the evangelization efforts in order to be able to communicate with Mixtecs in their own language for the purposes of conversion. In this same year a grammar was published by fray Antonio de los Reyes (also of the Teposcolula -Yucu Ndaa variety) 4.   There are several inter-related potential uses of the output of this endeavor<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">5</ref> for philological, linguistic, anthropological purposes including: 1) the creation of a machine searchable data set for the study of the Yucu Ndaa variety itself and/or the historiographical and philological issues related to the collection and specifics of the vocabulary collected; 2) create open, highly structured resource for other Mixtecan lexical projects; 3) combining the first two to potentially create a more cohesive body of pan-Mixtecan resources and a set of vocabulary for cross Mixtecan comparison; 4) the TEI format can easily be exported into other formats (e.g. tab separated plain text, etc.) for non-TEI users, i.e. the format is fully extensible.</p><p>And in line with the above, this endeavor was undertaken in order to integrate the contents of this historical resource into a TEI-based language documentation project dealing with Mixtepec-Mixtec (ISO 639-3: mix) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bowers &amp; Romary, 2017</ref><ref type="bibr">, 2018a</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">, 2018b)</ref>, an under-resourced indigenous language native to the Juxtlahuaca district of Oaxaca Mexico<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">6</ref> . Mixtepec-Mixtec (spoken in the Juxtlahuaca district of Oaxaca) like Teposcolula is in the "Mixteco Alto" region and the linguistic relation between modern Mixtepec-Mixtec and historical variety Yucu Ndaa is quite clear in a significant portion of the vocabulary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">OCR Technology and Indigenous Language Dictionaries</head><p>In recent years there have been growing efforts to apply OCR to digitize indigenous language resources, which is increasingly necessary as language communities are seeking to make the limited materials they have more widely available and to avoid situations where paper copies of content is not only inaccessible but is at risk of complete loss if physical copies fall victim to any number of potential man-made or natural disaster.</p><p>Maxwell &amp; Bills (2017) discuss the application of OCR methods in creating a structured, machine readable XML lexicon for indigenous language resources including: Tzeltal-English, Muinane-Spanish and Cubeo-Spanish dictionaries. Additionally, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ranaivo-Malançon et al. (2017)</ref> discusses the conversion of Melanau-Mukah-Malay and Iban-Malay indigenous language dictionaries from PDF sources into HTML files which was then parsed using a Python HTMLParser to extract the dictionary content to be saved as comma-separated plain text files.</p><p>More advanced approaches using machine learning techniques have seen since few years. The most successful one that showed enough potential for scalability and adaptation is the cascading parsing of print dictionaries implemented in GROBID-Dictionaries <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Khemakhem et al. 2017</ref><ref type="bibr">, Khemakhem et al. 2018a</ref><ref type="bibr">, Khemakhem et al. 2018b</ref><ref type="bibr">, Khemakhem et al. 2018c</ref>). The technique is based on Conditional Random Fields (CRF) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Lavergne et al. 2010</ref>) which allow, along with dedicated libraries for manipulating PDF documents, an end-to-end extraction of lexical structures into TEI compliant resources. Being language agnostic and the extensibility of GROBID-Dictionaries have motivated our present work to speed up the process of building a structured resource for the historical Mixtec language resource.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Different Versions of the resource</head><p>In both the automatic structuring process used to create the TEI dictionary and in the specifics of the content, the history of the organization of the lexical resource plays a significant role. While the original dictionary created by Alvarado was Castillian -Mixtec, the version by <ref type="bibr">Jansen &amp; Perez Jiménez (2009)</ref> was transformed to be Mixtec -Castillian. Below is an example of the original Castillian -Mixtec entry structure taken from the PDF version with the original structure created by Mesolore. This lexicon not only is Castilian based, but is organized in a way in which an entry often contains multiple Mixtec forms, have unclear indicators of grammatical information, the components of the Mixtec items are not appropriately delimited, in some cases they were not consistently spelled, and finally in many cases the Mixtec forms had other senses that were placed in separate entries. Thus, the original content was not a userfriendly resource.</p><p>Aceptar persona. Yodzacainuundi yositoninondita, f. coto, yotniño nuundita, yonaquai nuundita, yonaquaicahandisita.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>: Dictionary structure prior to the restructuring of <ref type="bibr">Jansen &amp; Perez Jiménez (2009)</ref> Jansen &amp; Perez Jiménez (2009) split up the contents of this into five separate entries and applied several normalizations to the orthographic representation to both produce a more uniform convention. These changes both improve the organization of the Mixtec content and more clearly reflect the linguistic structure. The results of which are shown below<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">7</ref> : yodza cay noondi: deshollejar; abajar la cabeza para mirar algo profundo; aceptar persona; anillo poner en el dedo; echar los ojos en algo; inclinarse bajando la cabeza para mirar hacia abajo; poner los ojos en algo para hurtarlo; poner los ojos en algo que parece bien yosito ninondita, futuro coto: aceptar persona yotniño nuundita: aceptar persona yona quay nuundita: aceptar persona yona quay cahandi sita: aceptar persona The changes made in the aforementioned source, particularly the use of bold type for the Mixtec forms, the addition of a colon ":", semi-colon ";", and comma "," delimiters between form and sense, different senses, and separate glosses in a single sense respectively rendered the contents much more amenable to the application of the GROBID as the contents of entries are much more clearly demarcated. Issues specific to GROBID will be discussed in more depth in the following section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">GROBID-Dictionaries</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">System Overview</head><p>GROBID-Dictionaries <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Khemakhem et al. 2017</ref><ref type="bibr">, Khemakhem et al. 2018a</ref>) is a machine learning infrastructure for parsing and structuring digital dictionaries based on CRF models <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Lavergne et al. 2010)</ref>. The infrastructure has been tested with digitized and born digital dictionaries in several languages, and is still under development. In the following section, we present the part of the tool's up to date architecture reflecting the logical (lexicographic) structure of the present dictionary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Cascading CRF models for Lexical Information Parsing</head><p>The lexical information extraction in GROBID-Dictionaries relies on a cascade parsing of the structures in an input dictionary. At each parsing level a CRF model, being trained on samples of the target dictionary, has the goal of predicting a set of labels representing TEI structures. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref> we present the architecture of different models and labels recognized by the system in the case of the present dictionary. As a reminder, a text cluster recognized by a CRF model could be either directly wrapped into a valid TEI structure -represented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref> with angle brackets -or into a pivot XML element -represented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref> without brackets. Pivot elements are implemented when a TEI construct is typed, such as &lt;form&gt; element that could be typed with either "lemma" or "inflected", or as for definitions which are serialized in TEI using &lt;def&gt; construct. We have used pivot elements just for the training stage which are then rendered in the final output as a valid TEI construct. &lt;pc&gt; is present at almost all segmentation levels as marking up such information is useful for the machine learning model to learn field limits in a continuous sequence of tokens. A simple find/replace postprocessing can remove such valid TEI tags if needed.</p><p>Compared to what has been already achieved in <ref type="bibr">Khemakhem et al. (2018a)</ref>, several improvements have been carried out to cover more lexical features encountered both in this dictionary as well as in other samples of similar lexical description depth:</p><p>1. Forms in lexical entries are differentiated into lemma and inflected 2. Form model parses morphological and grammatical information of different forms replacing the old model which was designed to extract the main information related to the lemma 3. After being extracted and segmented into sub-senses, if semantic nesting needs to be reflected, senses can be parsed by a SubSense model to recognize definitions, usage, grammatical information and translation equivalents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Experiment</head><p>In training the different models required in the architecture we have encountered several challenges related to the logical and physical (typographic) structure of the dictionary. We detail in this section the major obstacles, the implemented solutions, the impact on the annotation process and the results of the experiment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Automatic Parsing: Features and Challenges</head><p>The logical structure of the dictionary has been affected by the fact that dictionary had been re-compiled from an earlier version, which as mentioned above, greatly improved the quality and organization of the resource in many ways. While the dictionary looks fairly simple in structure, due to a mixture of issues related to the original vocabulary collection in combination with some conventions in the updated formatting which are not clearly specified by <ref type="bibr">Jansen and Jiménez Perez (2009)</ref>, it contains some complexities which pose some serious obstacles to parsing, most of these features are described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.1">Forms and related entries</head><p>While thanks to the revisions by <ref type="bibr">Jansen and Jiménez Perez (2009)</ref> the form section is nicely delimited from the sense by the use of the bold type, there are nonetheless quite a few different features present in that section with unique conventions for demarcation.</p><p>The most common supplemental feature in the forms is the inclusion of an inflected form (which is only a single part of the verb phrase), which is delimited by the combination of a comma, followed by the grammatical feature in italic type.</p><p>yosico ini tnahandi, futuro cuico: aficionados estar dos In the entry huau ndaha/ saha the form ndaha is "hand" while saha is "foot", thus the content is a related entry and is only part of the full form of the second lexical entry (as the lexical items for knuckles in Classical Mixtec are equivalent to "hand knuckles" and "foot knuckles"). In the entry below, it appears that there are alternate terms which translate into Spanish as en buen tiempo ("in good time") and these alternative phrases are separated by the first comma with the grammatical feature (either verbal tense or mood) preceding the inflected form.</p><p>quevui iñe huaha, quevui iñe huii, futuro cuiñe: en buen tiempo In only a few instances, where the entry itself is an inflected form of another entry this information is stated in square brackets within the form (bold) portion of the entry. However, this content is mixed between the feature (below imperativo), Spanish de, and then the Mixtec form (below yosa cahindi). These instances are actually duplicates of existing entries.</p><p>qua cahi [imperativo de yosa cahindi]: ir por algo generalmente </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.2">Sense information</head><p>In entries with multiple gloss-like definitions but which are to be considered a single sense, commas separate the contents<ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">8</ref> : quevui yahui: feria, mercado In some cases, the entry is divided into multiple senses (which themselves have one or more gloss), these separate senses are delimited by semicolons.</p><p>ñuhu nisitu: cavada tierra; labrada tierra There are cases of exceptions to these, for instance, which the comma usually delimits different glosses, in a few examples, they are used in a normal grammatical way, delimiting clauses. In the following example, the definition is fofa cosa "soft thing" and the content after the comma states "such as dirt".</p><p>ñuhu tisaha: fofa cosa, como tierra In many entries there is supplemental information about the sense given by the original author which generally specifies some aspect of the usage. This is represented in the <ref type="bibr">Jansen and Jiménez Perez (2009)</ref> version in round brackets.</p><p>ama: bien está (otorgando); sí Likewise, there are some entries with supplemental information which is grammatical in nature which is also placed in round brackets but is distinguished from the usage information with italics.</p><p>amana: ¿cuándo? (adverbio interrogativo), ¿en qué tiempo?</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">12</ref>: Example of grammatical information in sense However, there are certain cases in which there is grammatical information as well as a translation in the round brackets. Though the structure is distinct in that within the brackets, the grammar information is in italics delimited by a colon and the Spanish translation is to the right of the colon, there are not enough instances to train the system to automatically recognize this.</p><p>ca nayndo saha qhundo: llevar alguna cosa (imperativo: llevarás esto) In some entries Jansen and Jiménez Perez (2009) added notes of where the sense is metaphorical in nature, these also are represented in round brackets within the sense section. The number of these instances is also not sufficient for the system to recognize and structure this content.</p><p>ña tuvui nini dzavua yuqua iyondi: vivir pobre (por metáfora); pobre estar </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.4">Other issues</head><p>Hyphenated content which is present in the source due to line breaks and additional varied use of brackets for various lexical content are also present in the data source and contain too few instances to provide enough training data annotations for ML to create the desired output. Such content (as well as those mentioned above which lack sufficient quantities required for successful training) are structured in the TEI output either manually, semimanually, or automatically using XSLT and much of which will be described in a later section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Annotation</head><p>Covering instances of all the aforementioned observations in few pages for the annotation is a very hard task. And given the multi stage annotations, where the annotation is focused at each level on marking up all possible variations of specific structures, the number of the required pages to be annotated can grow exponentially.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Page Sampling Process</head><p>As a random sampling was not an option in the case of this dictionary, we tried to cover the variation of logical and physical structures by selecting pages that represent the maximum of challenges. We selected just a few pages containing related entries as they are sparsely distributed and we also had to give up the annotation of some structures such as "morphological variants" given their few number and inconsistent typographic representation. More useful information about language, comparison, transcription, etc. in prose section, we decided to ignore in the scope of this experiment.</p><p>We have selected and annotating 14 pages from different spots of the dictionary: 10 for training and 4 for evaluation. We detail the annotated instances for each model, except for the first one dealing with the prediction of main regions of a page which has less lexical importance to the scope of this work, in the following </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Results and Discussion</head><p>The results of the first two models, Dictionary Segmentation and Dictionary Body Segmentation reached an almost perfect result -above 98 F1 score. In the following table we detail the performance of the rest of the models on the field level in which the evaluation takes into consideration the prediction of all token of field and not only single tokens. We don't show the evaluation of the Grammatical Group model as it has only one label. The evaluation shows a high performance of the models in predicting lexical structures with the exception of related entries, grammatical information, sense usages within sense and orthography of inflected forms.</p><p>In the case of related entries, the training and evaluation datasets combined contain just 32 instances representing 2 logical representations (collocates and non-collocates) and 4 physical variations (with/without brackets and with/without commas). We consider the quantity of instances used for training is not sufficient for the Lexical Entry model to learn the distribution of such a structure.</p><p>For usage and grammatical information blocks, both structures are represented within senses as textual sequence wrapped in a round brackets. The only physical difference evident is the italics used to mark the grammatical information. An in-depth investigation has shown that such a visual variation has not been translated consistently in the layout information associated with each token of the document and being extracted by the PDF utilities libraries in GROBID-Dictionaries. Therefore, the SubSense model remains unable to differentiate these two physically similar structures. In the case of &lt;part&gt; label, more annotated instances seem to be needed in the training dataset to strengthen the predictions of the Form model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">TEI structure of output</head><p>Because this resource is being converted to TEI in order to be integrated with the TEIbased project on the contemporary Mixtepec-Mixtec variety 9 , the Classical Mixtec dictionary structure is designed to match the former as much as possible. The exception to this is that due to the inexact nature of the Spanish glossing the default element containing the Spanish is the definition element &lt;def&gt;, whereas is the Mixtepec-Mixtec TEI dictionary they are represented as pure translations. Note that while the ISO 639-3 language code is applied to the Mixtepec-Mixtec entry and the Spanish 639-2 tag is applied to the translations of the Classical Mixtec entry, there are no ISO or other any other standardized language codes for 'Classical Mixtec', nor is there any documented modern Mixtec variety attributed to Teposcolula.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Basic entry structure</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Inflected forms</head><p>The entries with inflected forms are shown below in the TEI output. Note that since these are mostly multi-word expressions verb phrases.</p><p>yosico ini tnahandi, futuro cuico: aficionados estar dos  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Post-editing: Modifications and enhancements</head><p>In terms of the source to target structure, the GROBID process was able to create a conversion of the PDF form of the resource into TEI which represented the majority of the features present in the dictionary. However, in the case of several features, further manual and semi-manual encoding enhancements were necessary in order to create a more dynamic and refined structure. These modifications were necessary due to either: a lack of sufficient token required for the machine learning process or to make it more compatible with the Mixtepec-Mixtec TEI corpus. In this section they are described.</p><p>Other key enhancements made to the output include the following:</p><p>• Spanish ISO 639-2 language tag added to all &lt;def&gt; elements • Unique id's (@xml:id) are added to each &lt;entry&gt; and &lt;re&gt; which are based on the Spanish value (with underscores and token numbers added as needed) • English translations are being added according to certain categories (at least for those which are sufficiently clear, as not all items can easily be translated) • Domain tag (&lt;usg type="domain"&gt;) is added in certain entries (some of the vocabulary in the source which are initially given &lt;usg type="hint"&gt; can be changed to domain) • Record of normalizations and assumed phonetic equivalencies made by <ref type="bibr">Jansen and Jiménez Perez (2009)</ref> are manually added in the header.</p><p>Below we discuss the formatting of content which was not sufficiently structured by GROBID and/or which needed additional structuring to bring it in line with best practice in TEI.</p><p>In the examples we show both the output of GROBID and the revised TEI structure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Related entries</head><p>In most cases related entries were correctly identified as such by GROBID, however because there are a number of different types of related entries most of which lack sufficient instances to train the system automatically recognize and encode then in detail, these items are manually refined in TEI.</p><p>tay huasi cana / cay idzi yuhu: mozo que comien-za a barbar </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Collocate phrases in the form</head><p>In a small number of cases, there is collocate information included in the form. In TEI this is encoded using the &lt;colloc&gt; element.</p><p>caa ndodzo ninondi (nuu sito): echado estar (en la cama) </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Modern Spanish Translations</head><p>There were a number of modernized Spanish translations added by <ref type="bibr">Jansen and Jiménez Perez (2009)</ref> which were placed in square brackets.</p><p>da queyeni: aprisa; incontinenti [luego]; y luego; luego a la hora; temprano </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Inflected forms</head><p>In certain cases, even though the source did not have a given feature explicitly labeled, what they did include could be used to infer, and then add key features in order to enhance the content and bring it in line with general lexicographic practice. One area where this was possible is where there were inflected forms.</p><p>yosico ini tnahandi, futuro cuico: aficionados estar dos In these entries with the feature futuro, there are two inferable features: first, that the entry is a phrase, (mostly which do not seem to have had simple lexicalized items in Mixtec), second, that given that the feature futuro is a feature of tense, that the part of speech verb can be inferred. The example below shows how these features are represented in the revised TEI structure by adding the @type="phrase" to &lt;entry&gt;, adding &lt;pos&gt;verb&lt;/pos&gt; to the entry level, and by changing the generic &lt;gram&gt; to &lt;tns&gt; in the inflected future form10. This enhancement process is done using XSLT. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">Addition of original prologue</head><p>As there were different PDF versions created of this resource, some of them included content from the original that were not included in the others. Notably in the version of <ref type="bibr">Jansen &amp; Perez Jiménez (2009)</ref> the original prolog content published in the original were not included, this content was added manually and is easily represented in the TEI output. yosa ndehe ichi: fenecer, acabar el que muere (por metáfora)  While at present not enough of the Classical Mixtec language yet to provide full analyses of the majority of the instances of metaphor, this information is nonetheless encoded in the TEI structure as per the recommendations of <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Bowers &amp; Romary (2016)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bowers et al. (2018)</ref>. A partial structured analysis is provided for the phrase "yosa ndehe ichi" of which only the portion ichi 'path' is discernable and which is represented as an etymon within the &lt;etym&gt; block in TEI. At a later stage, researchers who are more familiar with the language can enhance this content as needed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Later steps</head><p>A logical and needed future endeavors would be to create a searchable TEI version of the grammar of the language published in 1593 Arte en Lengva Mixteca by fray Antonio de los Reyes. Given that this resource is a grammar and not a dictionary-like text, this would not be a job for GROBID but another, general OCR tool. The text in the PDF available is of low quality and it is likely that significant manual work would be necessary to carry out. Furthermore, according to Mesolore, much of the Alvarado Classical Mixtec vocabulary was based on entries in the 'Molina Vocabulario' Castilian-Nahuatl dictionary (1571), a Castillian-Zapotec dictionary compiled by Juan de Cordova in the Valley of Oaxaca (1578), and Antoni de Nebrija's Castillian-Latin Dictionarium (1553). Thus, many of these resources have common content and it would be a natural and beneficial next step to create TEI versions of these resources to expand all of the benefits described with regard to the current Classical Mixtec vocabulary to these other indigenous languages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Conclusion</head><p>GROBID can handle the vast majority of the work needed to create a highly structured TEI dictionary from the PDF resource. However due to certain issues pertaining to the source document, its structure and the sample size of certain structures, in creating a maximally representative version of the content significant further manual and semimanual work is required. Given the richness of the resource, to accurately carry out these enhancements it is essential that they are carried out by humans who understand the details only accessible through a detailed study.</p><p>Converting this resource into TEI brings the data into a highly structured extensible machine-readable format which can be systematically searched, extracted and exported into other data formats using simple XQuery and/or XSLT.</p><p>In creating this iteration of the historical resource, we have continued the work of previous endeavors (specifically <ref type="bibr">Jansen &amp; Perez Jiménez, 2009)</ref> who have worked to make this resource available to researchers and importantly to Mixtec communities. As this work was carried out in order to integrate the important resource to an ongoing linguistic and lexicographic project dealing with the Mixtepec-Mixtec variety, we hope to demonstrate how the Alvarado resource can be used as both an etymological and comparative cross-reference between different varieties of Mixtec as well as how TEI is a highly beneficial data format.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Revised version of entry shown above, separated into four separate entries in Jansen &amp; Perez Jiménez (2009)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Parts of GROBID-Dictionaries' architecture activated for parsing the Mixtec dictionary</figDesc><graphic coords="7,79.30,71.55,419.50,250.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Entry with inflected (future) form cuicoThere are several different conventions used in related entries and variant forms, none of which have enough instances sufficient for automatic recognition and structuring:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Entry with variant term for part of phrase huaha ~ huii</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Entry whose form is an inflected form of a separate (related) entry</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: Entry with two glosses of a single sense</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: Entry with two distinct senses</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10: Entry showing comma delimiting separate glosses of same sense</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 11 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11: Example of usage information in sense</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 13 :</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Figure 13: Example of grammatical information and translation of inflected form in sense</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 14 :</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Figure 14: Example of metaphor specified in sense information</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 15 :</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Figure 15: Left partial TEI dictionary entry for nchika 'plantain' in Mixtepec-Mixtec; Right view of (unenhanced) structure of the historically related form in Classical Mixtec</figDesc><graphic coords="14,110.63,138.25,228.72,213.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>FigureFigure 17 :</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Figure 16: Entry with inflected form</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 18 :</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Figure 18: TEI encoding of entries with multiple senses and multiple definitions</figDesc><graphic coords="15,86.25,359.55,439.44,233.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 19 :</head><label>19</label><figDesc>Figure 19: Entry with related entry in source</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure 21 :</head><label>21</label><figDesc>Figure 21: Collocate of headword in source</figDesc><graphic coords="17,70.55,424.27,479.37,78.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Figure 23 :</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Figure 23: Entry with modernized Spanish translation in source</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Figure 25 :</head><label>25</label><figDesc>Figure 25: Entry with inflected form in source</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Figure 26 :</head><label>26</label><figDesc>Figure 26: GROBID output (left) with revised TEI structure of phrasal entry with inflected form (right)</figDesc><graphic coords="19,96.83,70.55,418.34,199.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Figure 27 :</head><label>27</label><figDesc>Figure 27: Left a PDF version of part of the original prologue and right its TEI encoding</figDesc><graphic coords="19,255.90,461.61,274.05,129.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Figure 29 :</head><label>29</label><figDesc>Figure 29: TEI (partially enhanced) encoded entry for metaphorical term 'yosa ndehe ichi'</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>table :</head><label>:</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Form</cell><cell>787 &lt;orth&gt;</cell><cell>269 &lt;orth&gt;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>31 &lt;part&gt;</cell><cell>11 &lt;part&gt;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>31 &lt;gramGrp&gt;</cell><cell>11 &lt;gramGrp&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>SubSense</cell><cell>905 &lt;def&gt;</cell><cell>319 &lt;def&gt;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>32 &lt;usg&gt;</cell><cell>11 &lt;usg&gt;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>7 &lt;gramGrp&gt;</cell><cell>8 &lt;gramGrp&gt;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>9 &lt;translation&gt;</cell><cell>2 &lt;translation&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>Model</cell><cell>Training</cell><cell>Evaluation</cell></row><row><cell>Dictionary Body</cell><cell>572 &lt;entry&gt;</cell><cell>270 &lt;entry&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>Segmentation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Lexical Entry</cell><cell>572 &lt;sense&gt;</cell><cell>269 &lt;sense&gt;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>572 &lt;lemma&gt;</cell><cell>270 &lt;lemma&gt;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>28 &lt;inflected&gt;</cell><cell>10 &lt;inflected&gt;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>10 &lt;re&gt;</cell><cell>4 &lt;re&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>Sense</cell><cell>856 &lt;subSense&gt;</cell><cell>302 &lt;subSense&gt;</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Page Sampling Statistics</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Field Level Evaluation of the Lexical Models</figDesc><table><row><cell>Model</cell><cell>Label</cell><cell>Precision</cell><cell>Recall</cell><cell>F1</cell></row><row><cell>Lexical Entry</cell><cell>&lt;inflected&gt;</cell><cell>90</cell><cell>90</cell><cell>90</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>&lt;lemma&gt;</cell><cell>99.26</cell><cell>99.26</cell><cell>99.26</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>&lt;pc&gt;</cell><cell>98.94</cell><cell>99.29</cell><cell>99.12</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>&lt;sense&gt;</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>100</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>&lt;re&gt;</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Sense</cell><cell>&lt;subSense&gt;</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>100</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>&lt;pc&gt;</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>100</cell></row><row><cell>Form</cell><cell>&lt;gramGrp&gt;</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>90.91</cell><cell>95.24</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>&lt;orth&gt;</cell><cell>98.18</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>99.08</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>&lt;part&gt;</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>63.64</cell><cell>66.67</cell></row><row><cell>SubSense</cell><cell>&lt;def&gt;</cell><cell>91.84</cell><cell>95.3</cell><cell>93.54</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 28: Entry for metaphorical term 'yosa ndehe ichi' as formatted in source PDF</figDesc><table><row><cell>Due to a lack of sufficient quantity for training, these items had to be manually identified</cell></row><row><cell>and annotated as follows:</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;entry xml:id="yosa_ndehe_ichi"&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;form type="lemma"&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;orth&gt;yosa ndehe ichi&lt;/orth&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;/form&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;sense&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;def xml:lang="es"&gt;fenecer&lt;/def&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;def xml:lang="es"&gt;acabar el que muere&lt;/def&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;/sense&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;etym type="metaphor"&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;seg type="desc"&gt;por metáfora&lt;/seg&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;cit type="etymon"&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;form&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;orth&gt;ichi&lt;/orth&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;/form&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;def xml:lang="es"&gt;camino&lt;/def&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;/cit&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;/etym&gt;</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;/entry&gt;</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_0"><p>In the present day, there are dozens of Mixtec varieties with different levels of mutual intelligibility, estimates range from 52 (Simons &amp; Fennig 2018) to 85 distinct varieties (Instituto Nacional de Lenguas Indígenas 2015).</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Both the source of the documentJansen &amp; Perez Jiménez (2009)  and Mesolore provide excellent overviews of issues relevant to the study and understanding of the contents of the vocabulary and thus those seeking a more extensive description thereof, should consult these studies.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Note these benefits discussed are on top of the essential work done by(Jansen &amp; Perez  Jiménez 2009)  who made the resource much more user friendly in implementing a number of normalizations, altering the entries to Mixtec -&gt; Spanish, provided an indepth discussion of the source, its context and provided a vision of the resource as a potential basis for pan-Mixtecan etymological and philological comparison. We share this vision and assert that the application of TEI enables the use of the resource as a machine and human readable database.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_3"><p>Mixtepec-Mixtec is an Otomonguean language spoken by roughly 9,000 -10,000 people, and in addition to the native communities in Mexico, it is also spoken by communities of several people living in California, Oregon, Washington, Florida and Arkansas in the United States.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_4"><p>Note in Figure2, the Spanish gloss of the entry yodza cay noondi contains content that was not in the original shown in Figure1; this was apparently taken from elsewhere in the in the original dictionary as yodza cay noondi was been given as the gloss for multiple Spanish terms. One of the major achievements ofJansen &amp; Perez Jiménez (2009)  was the consolidation of this information.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_5"><p>Despite the structuring, there are many cases in which the use of the sense delimiter ";" does not seem to delimit strictly distinct senses.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="9" xml:id="foot_6"><p>For an in depth detailing of the structure and content in the Mixtepec-Mixtec TEI dictionary, seeBowers and Romary (2018a)   </p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="10" xml:id="foot_7"><p>The reason that we did not train GROBID to automatically annotate the feature futuro as &lt;tns&gt; is that there are some instances of imperative forms listed in the same way. Thus, each of these features is further treated using XSLT specifically targeted, with the imperative forms being output in TEI as: &lt;gram type="mood"&gt;.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Vocabulario en Lengua Mixteca. Hecho por los Padres de la Orden de Predicadores</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Alvarado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>De</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1593">1593</date>
			<publisher>En México: Con Licencia, en casa de Pedro Balli</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deep Encoding of Etymological Information in TEI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bowers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4000/jtei.1643</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1643" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Language Documentation and Standards in Digital Humanities: TEI and the Documentation of Mixtepec-Mixtec</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bowers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 7th Conference of Japanese Association for Digital Humanities</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kawase</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting>the 7th Conference of Japanese Association for Digital Humanities<address><addrLine>Kyoto, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Doshisha University</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="23" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bridging the gaps between digital humanities, lexicography and linguistics: a TEI dictionary for the documentation of Mixtepec-Mixtec</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bowers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dictionaries: Journal of the Dictionary Society of North America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>a)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bowers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Encoding Mixtepec-Mixtec Etymology in TEI. Presented at the TEI Conference and Members</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Tokyo, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Voces del Dzaha Dzavui (mixteco clásico)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E R G N</forename><surname>Jansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pérez Jiménez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Análisis y Conversión del Vocabulario de fray Francisco de Alvarado</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1593">2009. 1593</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Colegio Superior Para La Educatión Integral Intercultural de Oaxaca</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic extraction of TEI structures in digitized lexical resources using conditional random fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Foppiano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of eLex 2017 conference</title>
		<meeting>eLex 2017 conference<address><addrLine>Leiden, Netherlands. Leiden, Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Enhancing Usability for Automatically Structuring Digitised Dictionaries. GLOBALEX Workshop at LREC 2018. Presented at Miyazaki, Japan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Herold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>a). Retrieved from ⟨hal-01708137v2⟩</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatically Encoding Encyclopedic-like Resources in TEI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gabay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bohbot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Frontini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Luxardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The annual TEI Conference and Members Meeting</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018 b)</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatically Encoding Encyclopedic-like Resources in TEI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gabay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bohbot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Frontini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Luxardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The annual TEI Conference and Members Meeting</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018 c)</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Endangered data for endangered languages: Digitizing print dictionaries. Proceedings of the 2nd Workshop on the Use of Computational Methods in the Study of Endangered Languages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lavergne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Cappé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Yvon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maxwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bills</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>the 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010. 2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="91" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Practical very large scale CRFs</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mesolore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.mesolore.org/tutorials/learn/9/Introduction-to-the-Alvarado-Vocabulario" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019-04-24">24 April 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://site.inali.gob.mx/Micrositios/estadistica_basica/estadisticas2015/estadisticas2015.html" />
		<title level="m">Proyecto de indicadores sociolingüísticos de las lenguas indígenas nacionales</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-07-05">2015. 5 July 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transforming Semi-Structured Indigenous Dictionary into Machine-Readable Dictionary</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ranaivo-Malançon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Saee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Othman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F W</forename><surname>Busu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Telecommunication, Electronic and Computer Engineering (JTEC)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3-11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ARTE EN LENGVA MIXTECA COMPUESTA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>De Los</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://books.google.at/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=Vbh9oGk-YKwC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA4&amp;dq=%22Arte+en+Lengua+Mixteca%22+Antonio+de+lo s+Reyes&amp;ots=yPfYu574TP&amp;sig=S3ro_9u4ZAp1-7wGnPVoA4WPS4U</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1593-04-15">1593. 15 April 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
