<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Bridging the gap between SKOS and TBX</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Detlef</forename><surname>Reineke</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Bridging the gap between SKOS and TBX</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A97B581592A795C01B2DEA065852BF04</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 8 Dec 2019 Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution| 4.0 International License</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Data exchange</term>
					<term>knowledge organization</term>
					<term>SKOS</term>
					<term>terminology</term>
					<term>TBX</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract xml:lang="fr">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access archive for the deposit and dissemination of scientific research documents, whether they are published or not. The documents may come from teaching and research institutions in France or abroad, or from public or private research centers. L'archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est destinée au dépôt et à la diffusion de documents scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Over the last decades, the representation of specialized vocabulary in digital format has been on the agenda of several communities that have mostly been working independently from one another:</p><p>• Initiated by the need to provide indexing terms for cataloguing, the library community made an initial attempt at defi ning standards for the representation of thesauri [see 1 <ref type="bibr">and 2]</ref>, seen as a set of specialized lexical items organized within a tree-based representation. Infl uenced by further developments in conceptual representations <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, this has led to the development of so-called knowledge organization systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and of SKOS as a linked open data model for lexical information <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. • The translation and technical writing communities have also heavily invested in developing methods and tools to maintain mono-and multilingual terminologies and have thus produced a whole family of standards to facilitate their management [see 6, 7, 8, 9, and 10, among others].</p><p>However, there has been hardly any signifi cant effort to build interfaces for exchanging concept-orientated data between the aforementioned communities. To the best of our knowledge, the only exceptions have been an auspicious mapping proposal by Reineke <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> for data exchange between TBX and RDF/XML and an attempt by the W3C group on Best Practices for Multilingual Linked Open Data to map TBX onto OntoLex [see 12 <ref type="bibr">and 13]</ref>. However, the results of the latter are quite unsatisfactory, since OntoLex is essentially a semasiological (word-to-sense) model which, by defi nition, cannot be naturally mapped onto the concept-to-term model of TBX. As a consequence, the mapping mainly consists of inserting TBX components into various unrelated places in the OntoLex format. The present article compares the two trends described above, focusing on SKOS and TBX, which, in our view, are both concept-orientated applications that will have to interoperate closely in the future. When referring to SKOS, we focus on the vocabulary listed in the SKOS reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, section 2 (SKOS Namespace and Vocabulary) and Appendix B (SKOS eXtension for Labels). TBX is tantamount and limited here to the attribute style as defi ned in ISO 30042 <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. The terminological data categories and their respective specifi cations are replicated from the data category repository DatCatInfo <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Both the SKOS and the TBX vocabularies discussed in this article are referenced using notations that point to the respective specifi cations compiled into a single, more reader-friendly resource available at https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01883377v3/document. As for typography, in running text, markup style is used for SKOS elements (&lt;skos:Concept&gt;), terminological data categories are indicated between forward slashes (/defi nition/).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Overview of data models</head><p>In the language industry, two general classes of data models prevail when providing lexical or terminological information. Semasiological models (or word-to-sense models) are organized with the word as the entry point to a lexical representation, from which further descriptions are derived. This is the model of traditional human-readable dictionaries, where the various senses of a lexical item are grouped</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bridging the gap between SKOS and TBX</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detlef Reineke and Laurent Romary</head><p>This article provides an in-depth comparison and proposal for mapping between Simple Knowledge Organization System (SKOS) and TermBase eXchange (TBX), two important exchange standards within the knowledge and terminology landscape. The attempt to develop an interface or conversion routine between SKOS and TBX is rooted in a strong demand in the language and knowledge industries for resource leverage and based on the premise that the two formalisms are governed by similar data models, namely the description of concepts (rather than words). Thema | Bridging the gap between SKOS and TBX together within a dictionary entry. Onomasiological models (or concept-to-term models) on the other hand, consider senses, more precisely concepts, as the organizing principle of the terminology database, so that terminological information units are attached to the concepts that they refer to.</p><p>As previously stated, SKOS and TBX both provide concept-orientated data models. However, there remain considerable differences as far as the overall data organization, data granularity and styles are concerned. In the following sections, we focus on the characteristics of the two models, illustrating the analysis with examples using XML serialization. Other serializations are possible although this would not alter the underlying principle of what we want to demonstrate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SKOS</head><p>SKOS was conceived to represent net-like multilingual knowledge organization systems, and thus to meet the demands of the Semantic Web and controlled vocabularies such as thesauri, classifi cation schemes, taxonomies, or subject-heading systems. It is built upon RDF and RDFS and offers a very fl at data model with basically only one formal level for storing data related to a specifi c concept.</p><p>In SKOS, a concept can be essentially represented and described through labels, semantic relationships, and docu-mentary notes. More precisely, the following components form the core of a SKOS entry:</p><p>• &lt;skos:Concept&gt; is the single entry node to the entry structure; • linguistic segments attached to the concept are represented by means of several possible relations: &lt;skos:prefLabel&gt;, &lt;skos:altLabel&gt;, and &lt;skos:hiddenLabel&gt;; • additional documentary segments are attached to the concept with a variety of relations, such as &lt;skos:defi nition&gt;, &lt;skos:note&gt;, or &lt;skos:example&gt;; • inter-concept relations allow the creation of a network of concepts, such as &lt;skos:broader&gt;, &lt;skos:broaderTransitive&gt;, &lt;skos:narrower&gt; or &lt;skos:related&gt;.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> illustrates a graphical representation of a typical SKOS concept entry. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> demonstrates an XML serialization of the sample SKOS represented by the graph in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, including two additional languages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TBX</head><p>TBX, expressed by default in XML style, is the successor of the SGML-based terminology exchange format MARTIF Bridging the gap between SKOS and TBX | Thema <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> which both emerged from terminology management needs within the translation/localization (and even technical writing) industry. TBX was launched as a result of the EU project SALT <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, then further developed by LISA <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> and fi nally adopted to become ISO 30042 in 2008. TBX is based on the terminological metamodel, a strongly hierarchical data model described in ISO 16642 (see Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>), that allows for a very fi ne-grained description of terminological data.</p><p>As mentioned above, the metamodel refl ects the principle of concept orientation, i. e. in a terminology database or terminological data collection (TDC) a concept entry (CE) describes a single concept. Starting from the top, the meta-model provides two high-level containers: a container for global information (GI) that applies to the complete terminology database (name of the terminology database, copyright information, history, etc.); and a container for complementary information (CI) such as complete bibliographical data sets or binary data, that is only documented once and then referenced from the respective concept entries.</p><p>Concept entries can be further structured by using additional language sections (LS) for instantiating languages and language-specifi c information. Each language section can include zero or more term sections (TS) for documenting terms and term-specifi c information, and individual words of a multiword term or morphemes of a single-word term can be described in the term component section (TCS).</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> illustrates a simplifi ed version of the TBX core structure with the corresponding terminological metamodel levels in parentheses. For the sake of readability, the mandatory attributes for the TBX core structure elements have been omitted.</p><p>In attribute style, almost all terminological data categories are instantiated as values of a type attribute that is associated with a core-structure element, such as &lt;descrip&gt;, &lt;admin&gt;, etc. (for example, &lt;descrip type="subjectField"&gt; $&lt;/descrip&gt;). This mechanism provides suffi cient fl exibility for data exchange between different data models or terminology database defi nitions whilst ensuring a maximum of stringency for automated conversion.</p><p>The example in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref> (on page 22) represents a concept entry in TBX for the concept circuit-breaker, including information relevant to the subject fi eld, a defi nition and its source, references to the superordinate and various subordinate concepts, and the terms representing the concept in four languages, their respective sources and term-specifi c information such as status and part of speech.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mapping the two worlds</head><p>The most relevant mapping scenarios between SKOS and TBX concern information related to the concept itself,  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Concepts</head><p>As we have seen, the two models are based on an onomasiological approach to the association between labels/terms and senses/concepts. As a result, they both organize their core informational content with the concept as the entry point. However, when looking at how both models organize their underlying conceptual systems, we can already identify a clear-cut difference in perspective.</p><p>The SKOS data model, taking its origins in the notion of thesaurus, puts the emphasis on the vertical (or hierarchical) organization of concepts as a KOS. By defi nition, a SKOS document instance describes an ontology that is articulated along a central generic-specifi c relation. In contrast, the data model implemented in TBX is more horizontal and based upon the idea of a conceptual space underlying a given subject fi eld. The emphasis here is on the differentiation between concepts, which refl ects the semantics of the terms used in this fi eld. Consequently, even if &lt;concept Entry&gt; and &lt;skos:Concept&gt; are the obvious elements to be matched when mapping the two models, it is important to bear the difference in mind when comparing them more precisely.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Concept relations</head><p>In SKOS, the means for describing relationships between concepts is limited to three properties: broader, narrower and related. The SKOS Primer states that "skos:broader and skos:narrower enable the representation of hierarchical links, such as the relationship between one genre and its more specifi c species, or, depending on interpretations, the relationship between one whole and its parts" [see 18, 2.3]. In the traditional sense, this defi nition implies that the abstraction level between a genre and its species is equal to one. The examples given in the SKOS Primer underline this approach, as depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>:</p><p>If abstraction levels greater than one for broader and narrower concepts come into play, SKOS proposes the additional properties &lt;skos:broaderTransitive&gt; and &lt;skos:narrowerTransitive&gt; (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>) which are generally destined to infer statements for reasoning purposes.</p><p>In contrast, TBX supports a wider variety of data categories that allow for the creation of comprehensive and fi negrained concept systems. As demonstrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref>, the relations between concepts can be specifi ed by indicating their logical nature (generic, partitive, related), their relative position (superordinate, subordinate, coordinate, broader, narrower) or other kinds of properties (temporally, spatially or sequentially related). These properties   Special attention should be drawn to the fact that TBX introduces a distinction with regard to hierarchically organized concepts depending on the number of abstraction levels that exist between different concepts. Data categories of the type /superordinate*/, for example, are defi ned in general terms (see 2.90 and 2.91) without specifying the number of abstraction levels, whereas data categories of the type /broader*/ are defi ned as concepts "two or more levels of abstraction higher than subject concept [sic.] in a generic hierarchical concept system" (see 2.10 and 2.11). Despite the lack of explicitness concerning the specifi cation of the number of abstraction levels for /superordinate*/ and /subordinate*/, we consider that, in order for data category defi nitions to be consistent, the conclusion which has to be drawn from the /broader*/ defi nition is that /superordinate*/ and /subordinate*/ can only refer to an abstraction levels as being equal to one. In consequence, /broader*/ and /narrower*/, on the one hand, and &lt;skos:broader&gt; and &lt;skos:narrower&gt;, on the other hand, can be considered as false friends. Hence, &lt;skos:broader&gt; and &lt;skos:narrower&gt; should be mapped to /superordinate*/ and /subordinate*/ data categories; &lt;skos:broaderTransitive&gt; and &lt;skos:narrowerTransitive&gt; should be mapped to /broader-Concept*/ and /skos:narrowerConcept*/ respectively.</p><p>The one-to-one mapping of non-hierarchical relations can be easily achieved between &lt;skos:related&gt; (see 1.28) and / relatedConcept/ (see 2.70). However, if the entry structure of the terminology database requires further specifi cation of the relation type, then the source database of the SKOS document instance or the SKOS document instance itself need to be adapted or transformed accordingly.</p><p>The &lt;skos:*Match&gt; element family is used for mapping between SKOS concept systems (see 1.4, 1.6, 1.12, 1.23, and 1.29) and therefore usually does not constitute a concern for the present SKOS &lt;&gt; TBX mapping analysis. However, if SKOS document instances contain several con-cept schemes, a preliminary analysis and determination of the preferred concept scheme or concepts should be made and the resulting prioritization should be implemented in the corresponding SKOS &gt; TBX transformation stylesheet. In the reverse direction, &lt;skos:*Match&gt; does not need to be addressed, since an optimal terminology database does not include duplicates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Domain or subject fi eld</head><p>The difference is immediately refl ected in the way concept systems are grounded in the two models. In TBX, concept entries are systematically associated with a subject fi eld (&lt;descrip type="subjectField"&gt;$&lt;/descrip&gt;). The subject fi eld, being a text description, does not imply any kind of structure except that terms are deemed unambiguous (monosemic) within a given fi eld.</p><p>In SKOS, concepts are considered as autonomous units that may be linked to a concept scheme (&lt;skos:ConceptScheme&gt;) that encompasses all the concepts that are members of the same underlying KOS. In particular, there is, in theory, no constraint as to the width of the thematic coverage of a concept system. It may range from a simple group of concepts used to describe very local ontologies to very generic large-coverage ontologies [see 19] with no sense of term univocity or term prioritization within the corresponding fi eld of knowledge. However, the SKOS designers recommend that no two concepts should have the same preferred lexical label in a given language when they belong to the same concept scheme [see 18, 2.2.1]. Yet, despite the recommendations given in these guidelines, it can be observed in large vocabularies such as IATE <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> or the UNESCO thesaurus <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> that these theoretical specifi cities tend to be dimmed down: subject fi elds and concept schemes appear to be used in quite similar ways in terms of expressing domains, and numerous terms are described under various concepts in both cases.</p><p>Therefore, when mapping between SKOS and TBX, one should be aware of the possible discrepancy between subject fi elds and concept schemes, even if, at fi rst sight, they seem to express a similar reference system for the underlying concepts.</p><p>Unlike TBX, SKOS provides an explicit access to entry points of subject fi eld hierarchies using &lt;skos:Concept  Thema | Bridging the gap between SKOS and TBX Scheme&gt;, &lt;skos:hasTopConcept&gt;, &lt;skos:TopConceptOf&gt;, and &lt;skos:inScheme&gt; for hierarchization as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">10</ref>.</p><p>For larger databases covering several domains, SKOS offers &lt;skos:collection&gt; in conjunction with &lt;skos:notation&gt; and &lt;skos:member&gt; to build or merge these domain hierarchies into one single SKOS document instance as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">11</ref>.</p><p>TBX lacks explicit entry points to concept systems. They could only be inferred by (manually) searching for fi rst level notations if available or by climbing up data categories pointing to preferred terms of superordinate concepts. Neither does TBX (yet) support sophisticated means for subject fi eld classifi cation. A workaround for mapping SKOS domain hierarchies to TBX could consist in using multiple "subject fi eld" instances and specifying hierarchies with text content, as illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">12</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Defi nitions</head><p>&lt;skos:defi nition&gt; is always a child element of &lt;skos: Concept&gt; (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">13</ref>). In TBX, however, defi nitions can be instantiated at the concept level or the language level (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">14</ref>). This fl exibility derives from the fact that terminology databases are usually designed for different use cases. In technical writing/authoring (in a monolingual Bridging the gap between SKOS and TBX | Thema environment), for instance, or in translation environments using a pivot language, defi nitions are frequently allocated to the concept level, whereas in translation environments without pivot languages defi nitions happen to appear at the language level in their respective languages.</p><p>As a consequence of the above, when mapping from TBX to SKOS, defi nitions are not problematic, since the instantiation of concept-related information in SKOS is restricted to a single level. In the reverse mapping scenario, however, the decision where to allocate a defi nition cannot be resolved without prior (human) disambiguation, even though there might be some indications that could lead to the assumption that the content of &lt;skos:defi nition&gt; could be mapped either to the concept or the language level in TBX. Let us suppose, for example, that there is one &lt;skos:defi nition&gt; per language, so we might assume that these defi nitions should be placed at the language level in TBX. Or imagine a SKOS instance with only one &lt;skos:defi nition&gt; per concept without any xml:lang attribute. We might conclude that these defi nitions should typically be mapped to the concept level in TBX. Nevertheless, it should not be forgotten that these considerations remain mere speculations as long as the TBX use case has not been previously specifi ed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Labels and terms</head><p>Intuitively, there should be a one-to-one mapping between the notions of labels and terms in the SKOS and TBX models respectively, since, with the broad onomasiological perspective, they both constitute linguistic representations that can be used to express the encompassing concept. However, when looking more closely at semantics in SKOS and TBX, some differences arise regarding the precise role they play.</p><p>Considering the label elements in the SKOS model from a general point of view, their role is focused on denotation, that is of being lexical expressions (single or multi word units) associated with the corresponding SKOS concept. They are also described along two single dimensions:</p><p>• the language of the label, expressed by means of the xml:lang attribute; • the status of the label with regard to its relation to the concept, differentiating between preferred (&lt;skos:pref Label&gt;), alternative (&lt;skos:altLabel&gt;) and so-called hidden labels (&lt;skos:hiddenLabel&gt;).</p><p>In TBX, terms come with a more elaborate semantic set of descriptive features. The central idea that should be stressed here is term autonomy, which states that all the descriptive components of a term, comprising the term itself, should be grouped together with a dedicated reifi ed object. Typically, this reifi cation is refl ected by the occurrence of a specifi c term section component in the terminological metamodel and the corresponding &lt;termSec&gt; element in TBX. Term autonomy allows terms to be described along a variety of possible dimensions:</p><p>• linguistic characteristics (part of speech, grammatical gender, etc.); • discursive context (register, usage, etc.); • term relations (abbreviation, equivalent, etc.); • administrative characteristics (status, project, customer, source, etc.); • management task (origination, modifi cation, approval, etc.).</p><p>As can be seen, the only intersection of SKOS label properties and TBX term-specifi c data categories is the information related to the status of labels and terms. (see 1.27), can be easily mapped one of the two permissible TBX picklist values, that is "preferred" or "preferred term" (see The existence of more than one tion here is due to the fact that TBX uses a more differentiated approach and classifi es the term status information depending on whether the term pertains to a working environment (/administrativeStatus/, see 2.2) or to a normative environment (/normativeAuthorization/, see 2.54). Therefore, when transforming a SKOS document instance into TBX, this differentiation needs to be considered. The same applies to &lt;skos:altLabel&gt;, a property for alternative labels (see 5.2.1), and its natural counterparts, the two values "admitted" for /administrativeStatus/ and "admitted term" for /normativeAuthorization/. A transformation from TBX to SKOS presents a minor challenge in this regard as long as the working environment is not of importance.</p><p>&lt;skos:hiddenLabel&gt; is to be used for labels that should only be accessible to applications for indexing or search operations, such as misspelled variants or other lexical labels, but which are not be visible otherwise (see <ref type="bibr">1.15)</ref>. In this context, TBX provides some further specifi cation apart from the working environment to which a term may pertain. In TBX, the data categories /administrativeStatus/ and /normativeAuthorirzation/ make it possible to instantiate the values "obsolete" and "superseded term" respectively, meaning terms that are "no longer preferred or admitted" -which matches part of the &lt;skos:hiddenLabel&gt; defi nition. However, the SKOS property "invisible" is not inherent in either TBX data category value defi nitions, and for good reason -obsolete or superseded terms may still need to be visible in authoring and translation environments as negative examples to be avoided during authoring or translation. Also, in some terminology databases, obsolete or superseded terms are maintained for documentary reasons.</p><p>Similarly, the &lt;skos:hiddenLabel&gt; property "misspelled variants" has no semantic counterpart in TBX. As a matter of fact, misspelled variants are not usually included in terminology databases. Nonetheless, if &lt;skos:hiddenLabel&gt; instantiates labels for indexing and search operations in the fi rst place (including misspelled variants), /searchTerm/ (see 2.76) could be an alternative, as depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">16</ref>.</p><p>Mapping from TBX to SKOS is less discretionary; preferred, admitted, and obsolete/superseded terms can be easily mapped to their corresponding counterparts &lt;skos: prefLabel&gt;, &lt;skos:altLabel&gt;, and &lt;skos:hiddenLabel&gt;. Other types of TBX term status information such as "legal", "regulated" or "standardized" have no equivalent in SKOS.</p><p>SKOS instances may also include explicit relations between labels of one single concept, for instance, between a full form (sulphur hexafl uoride circuit-breaker) and an abbreviated form of the label (SF6 circuit-breaker) or between a label and its translation. The fi rst case is useful as long as more than two labels are provided for one concept in a given language; the second use case makes sense when the labels do not imply total synonymy, so that equivalencies between the labels in the corresponding languages need to be established. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">17</ref> illustrates a link between two English labels by fi rst defi ning the labels as fi rst-order RDF resources which can then be linked by a &lt;skosxl:labelRelation&gt; statement.</p><p>In TBX, relations between terms of a concept in different languages can be described using /transferComment/ (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">18</ref>). However, /transferComment/ allows documenting different kinds of information (degree of equivalence, directionality, etc.; see 2.105), so, consequently, some further context information should be provided during transformation (such as "Equivalent French term:") in order to refi ne the data.</p><p>As stated, the SKOS formalism illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">17</ref> for linking terms in different languages can also be used to link an abbreviation with the corresponding full form of a label.  TBX provides specifi c data categories for these scenarios, as in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">19</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>As we have seen, the mapping rules we suggest only make sense if some constraints are implemented when designing one type of data source or the other -or, at least, when such constraints are not in place, that we can anticipate where information may be lost or represented with less felicity.</p><p>The major mapping problem lies in the difference between SKOS and TBX regarding the depth of the information description and the instantiation fl exibility. TBX is a clear-cut, in-depth exchange format with high instantiation fl exibility, whereas SKOS provides a relatively fl at, rigid, and partially ambiguous description formalism. Consequently, the difference in the diversity of instantiable information units does not affect data integrity when mapping from SKOS to TBX, but generally leads to data impoverishment when mapping from TBX to SKOS. Laurent Romary is senior researcher at Inria (team ALMAnaCH, Paris, France). He is currently chair of ISO/TC 37 "Language and terminology" and involved in the development of various standards related to lexical data and language resources.   </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Graphical representation of a concept entry in SKOS</figDesc><graphic coords="3,51.08,99.20,484.87,304.39" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Simple SKOS instance representing two concepts</figDesc><graphic coords="4,61.76,100.70,234.07,251.83" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :Figure 4 :</head><label>34</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Terminological metamodel (adapted from ISO 16642:2017, 10)</figDesc><graphic coords="4,59.54,497.42,235.27,186.07" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: TBX document instance documenting one concept</figDesc><graphic coords="5,51.08,99.32,235.39,275.59" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Broader and narrower relationship in SKOS</figDesc><graphic coords="5,303.38,230.42,233.41,56.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Transitivity of concept relationships in SKOS</figDesc><graphic coords="5,300.56,390.56,235.33,252.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: Concept relationships in TBX</figDesc><graphic coords="6,59.60,146.78,235.33,108.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: Subject fi eld instantiation in SKOS and TBX</figDesc><graphic coords="6,309.08,658.46,235.33,58.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 10 :Figure 12 :Figure 13 :Figure 14 :</head><label>10121314</label><figDesc>Figure 10: SKOS concept schemes</figDesc><graphic coords="7,51.08,143.96,235.39,235.27" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>&lt;skos:prefLabel&gt;, a property assigned to a resource for being the preferred label that represents the concept DE | EN | FR Terminologiearbeit -wozu? Why Terminology? La terminologie, dans quel but ? DE | EN | FR Term inolo giea rbei t -woz u? Why Term inolo gy? La term inolo gie, dans quel but ? Kostenfreie Terminologiebroschüre Der Deutsche Terminologie-Tag e. V. hat eine Informationsbroschüre mit grundlegenden Argumenten für Terminologiearbeit in Unternehmen und Organisationen herausgegeben. Die dreisprachige Broschüre im handlichen DIN-A6-Format kann kostenfrei und in begrenzter Menge bei der Geschäftsstelle des DTT bestellt werden. in l l ie iearb arbe it ei -woz woz u? u? Ter Termin minolo ologie i arb arbeit eit woz Ter Termin inolo ologiearbeit Why Term inolo gy? log iea rb eit -wo zu ? W hy Te rm ino log y? La ter mi no log ie, da ns qu el bu t ? Anzeige dttev.org</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 16 :Figure 17 :</head><label>1617</label><figDesc>Figure 16: Mapping misspelled variants from SKOS to /search-Term/</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 15 :</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Figure 15: Term status instantiation in SKOS and TBX</figDesc><graphic coords="9,51.08,323.96,235.39,68.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Kontaktadresselaurent.romary@inria.fr</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 19 :</head><label>19</label><figDesc>Figure 19: Link between the full form of a term and its abbreviation in TBX</figDesc><graphic coords="10,302.12,616.64,76.15,92.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information and documentation -Thesauri and interoperability with other vocabularies -Part 1: Thesauri for information retrieval</title>
		<idno>ISO 25964-1:2011</idno>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Geneva</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>ISO</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information and documentation -Thesauri and interoperability with other vocabularies -Part 2: Interoperability with other vocabularies</title>
		<idno>ISO 25964-2:2013</idno>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Geneva</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>ISO</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">XML Topic Maps: creating and using topic maps for the Web</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jack</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sam</forename><surname>Hunting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley Professional: Boston</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trends and issues in establishing interoperability among knowledge organization systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lei</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marcia</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lois</forename><surname>Mai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chan</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Society for information science and technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">World Wide Web Consortium (W3C). 2009a</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/skos-reference" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SKOS reference</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<idno>ISO 16642:2017</idno>
		<title level="m">Computer applications in terminology -Terminological markup framework</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Geneva</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>ISO</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Management of terminology resources -Data category specifi cations</title>
		<idno>ISO 12620:2019</idno>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Geneva</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>ISO</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<idno>ISO 26162:2019</idno>
		<title level="m">Management of terminology resources -Terminology databases -Part 1: Design</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Geneva</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ISO</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<idno>ISO 26162:2019</idno>
		<title level="m">Management of terminology resources -Terminology databases -Part 2: Software</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Geneva</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ISO</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Management of terminology resources -TermBase eXchange (TBX)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Geneva</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30042</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>ISO</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TBX between termbases and ontologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Detlef</forename><surname>Reineke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00950862v2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Terminology and Knowledge Engineering 2014 proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.w3.org/community/ontolex/wiki/Speci-fication_of_Core_Model" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">OntoLex -Specifi cation of Core Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Best Practices for Multilingual Linked Open Data community group, Guidelines for Linguistic Linked Data Generation: Multilingual Terminologies (TBX)</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.w3.org/2015/09/bpmlod-reports/multilingual-terminolo-gies" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Language Terminology/Translation and Acquisition Consortium (LTAC)</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.datcatinfo.net" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ISO 12200:1999 Computer applications in terminology -Machinereadable terminology interchange format (MARTIF) -Negotiated interchange</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Geneva</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>ISO</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TBX: A terminology exchange format for the translation and localization industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><surname>Melby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Terminology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hendrik</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kockaert</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frieda</forename><surname>Steurs</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam/ Philadelphia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Benjamins</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="393" to="424" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An abstract model for the representation of multilingual terminological data: TMF -Terminological Markup Framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://hal.inria.fr/inria-00100405" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">TAMA 2001 -Sharing Terminological Knowledge, Sharing Multilingual Content. Proceedings of the 5th TermNet Symposion</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">World Wide Web Consortium (W3C). 2009b. &quot;SKOS Primer</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/skos-primer" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning of OWL class descriptions on very large knowledge bases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sebastian</forename><surname>Hellmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jens</forename><surname>Lehmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sören</forename><surname>Auer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal on Semantic Web and Information Systems (IJS-WIS)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://iate.europa.eu" />
		<title level="m">Interactive Terminology for Europe (IATE)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>European Union (EU)</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">UNESCO Thesaurus</title>
		<ptr target="http://vocabularies.unesco.org/browser/thesaurus" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<publisher>UNESCO</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
