<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D8F7B6939E263FF5B8A07B1F8B671144</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:02+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>How can science be more open ?</head><p>• Combining individual and collective initiatives</p><p>• Adopting an early dissemination strategy for all the components of a research project</p><p>• Open science should be part of the research methods themselves</p><p>• Open science must be a component of the strategy of all HER institutions</p><p>• Relation to reporting, assessment, communication</p><p>• Opening the debate on digital sovereignty</p><p>• Who owns the content? Who is responsible for its curation? Who hosts the content?</p><p>• Should not open science be based upon reliable and sustainable public infrastructures?</p><p>• Bringing open science on the political agenda     </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Open science in practice</head><p>Open science and open access But, but, but … why don't you speak of the real open acces plaforms, Academia, ReasearchGate</p><p>• "One more word about ResearchGate/Academia.edu and why using these platforms will never be equal to proper self-archiving"</p><p>• https://dariahopen.hypotheses.org/878</p><p>• "The Day I Removed my Publications from Academia &amp; Research Gate"</p><p>• https://icietla.hypotheses.org/114</p><p>• The central question: can you rely on non public services to deploy you open science policy?</p><p>Open science and data management</p><p>• Opening/sharing research data is impossible without prior data management</p><p>• Central questions related to data format, hosting, reuse conditions</p><p>• Mandatory deliverable by many funding agencies (e.g. ERC)</p><p>• Beyond DMPs -data management practices associated to research processes Towards a virtuous environment for experimental data management (and more)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preparatory phase</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimentation phase</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dissemination phase</head><p>Action points at each stage of the research process</p><p>• Preparatory phase</p><p>• Project proposal (funding proposal, access request to the facility)</p><p>• Data management plan • Anticipating on the reuse conditions: hand-shake between the different stakeholders</p><p>• The data reuse charter as a central instrument</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Experimentation phase</head><p>• Digital laboratory notebooks (e.g. Jupyter): documenting all steps in the data life cycle</p><p>• Data creation, transformation, graphics etc.</p><p>• Identifying at each stage the relevant participants (PI, researcher, technical staff, tarinees etc.)</p><p>• Long term documentation of the process: http://ssk.huma-num.fr/#/</p><p>• Transient data hosting: metadata, qualification (e.g. future data selection process)</p><p>• Dissemination phase</p><p>• Archiving and publishing all intermediary documents (with openness constraints)</p><p>• Final selection and clean up of data sets that should be preserved (with openness constraints)</p><p>Cf. Mooc (in English) Recherche reproductible : principes méthodologiques pour une science transparente</p><p>The data reuse charter: a tool for agreeing on reuse</p><p>• Objective and context</p><p>• Establishing a hand-shake mechanism between the various stakeholders involved in the creation of a data set</p><p>• Researcher, cultural heritage institution, instrument, data hosting infrastructure</p><p>• Work initiated as a collaboration between several major EU organisations</p><p>• DARIAH, CLARIN, E-RIHS, APE, Europeana</p><p>• https://datacharter.hypotheses.org</p><p>• Organised as a series of 6 principles • Method</p><p>• Self declaration from each party</p><p>• Can be global to an institution, agreed for a project, specific to an artefact or a data set</p><p>• Availability of questionnaires to guide the design of declarations The DARIAH campus data reuse charter</p><p>• Introduction presenting the DARIAH campus vision</p><p>• "Fostering open access to scholarly resources, as well as collaboration and fair data-sharing practices among a diverse range of actors involved in knowledge creation in the Arts and Humanities" • "as a mutual declaration of goodwill, the charter allows us to clarify our expectations regarding the interaction between content creators, users and curators"</p><p>• An explicit statement for each of the 6 principles • An annex (work in progress…) specifying the technical details</p><p>• Metadata profiles, formats and standards used for the various contents DARIAH campus: data reuse declaration -1</p><p>• Reciprocity</p><p>• "learners ((re)users) are encouraged to share their feedback but also contribute new training materials" "contact information of both authors (together with other contributors) and commenters/reviewers will be made explicit"</p><p>• Interoperability</p><p>• "training materials will be made accessible in open formats"</p><p>• "share metadata in a standardized format to ease harvesting our content"</p><p>• "We make available the content of our hosted learning resources (written in Markdown, a lightweight markup language) available through a GitHub repository"</p><p>• Citability</p><p>• [We] "make our recommended citation model explicit for each training resource shared via DARIAH-Campus"</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Old school open science: open access to scholarly publications • An essential step before going deep sea • Simpler from an editorial and technical point of view • The baseline of scholarly communication • Difficulties: • Access (paywalls) • Costs (subscriptions or Article processing charge -APCs -combined in hybrid journals) • Reuse -e.g. restrictions to text and data mining • Sovereignty: fragmented corpus of under-accessible, heterogeneous scholarly productions • Unavailable to researchers, communities, institutions, funders • Lack of sustainability • Food for thought: example of the institutional policy at Inria • Deposit mandate in HAL (linked to annual reporting), including articles published in natively open journals (with APC) • Centralised budget for APCs -general ban of the hybrid model • OpenAPC • Un-subscribing from non-essential portfolios (Coquetry: Nature, Junk: Springer LNCS) and reinvestment in open platforms (e.g. Episciences)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,253.35,142.35,453.30,255.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,54.21,16.49,529.71,504.83" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Having it part of governmental and funding agencies strategies • Funding requirements: cf. H2020 policies (open access, data management plans), and now ANR (Agence Nationale de la Recherche -French funding agency) • Showing by doing: ex. HCERES (French assessment agency) =&gt; https://hal-hceres.archives-ouvertes.fr</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Taking into account the legal context… What does the law say? General principles • Note: more precise information available from the DARIAH working group Ethics and Legality in the Digital Arts and Humanities (ELDAH) • Research data must be open by default</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Integrated into the Code des relations entre le public et l'administration (livre III, titre II)</figDesc><table><row><cell>• Intellectual property, personal data, strategic or transfer related information</cell></row><row><cell>• Specific cases of cultural organisation: libraries, museums, archives</cell></row><row><cell>• European and French (sorry…) legal background</cell></row><row><cell>• Loi n° 78-753 du 17 juillet 1978, CADA (Commission d'accès aux documents administratifs)</cell></row><row><cell>• Directive 2003/98/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 17 November 2003 on the re-use of public sector information (PSI)</cell></row><row><cell>• Revised in 2013 (DIRECTIVE 2013/37/UE)</cell></row><row><cell>• Loi dite Valter du 28 décembre 2015 relative à la gratuité et aux modalités de la réutilisation des informations du secteur public</cell></row><row><cell>• Loi pour une République numérique -7 octobre 2016</cell></row></table><note><p>•</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Openness</head><p>• "Open Educational Resource (OER)"</p><p>• "openly and freely available under a Creative Commons CC-BY 4.0 license"</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Stewardship</head><p>• "workflows to ensure the long-term availability of the training materials hosted on DARIAH-Campus"</p><p>• Trustworthiness</p><p>• "we recognize the diverse contributor roles (author, editor, contributor) to clearly document who participated in the production process in order to ensure its traceability"</p><p>Before we we go further…</p><p>• The message once again: open science is just science done right</p><p>• Sharing a culture of sharing</p><p>• There are various tools to do so, at different stages of the research process</p><p>• DMPs, Data reuse charter, Laboratory notebooks, SSK, publication repositories</p><p>• For those in the TEI landscape, all this seems obvious</p><p>• Let us see why…</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The TEI as an open science project</head><p>The Text Encoding Initiative for the dummies</p><p>• The TEI is an XML application:</p><p>&lt;p&gt;&lt;persName&gt;Tome Geek&lt;/persName&gt; went to &lt;placeName&gt;Paris&lt;/placeName&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</p><p>• The TEI is there for (humanities, but not only) scholars (but also professionals) to encode a variety of cool things:</p><p>• Prose, theatre, poetry, dictionaries (yeah!), manuscripts etc.</p><p>• The TEI guidelines provides a vocabulary of 580 elements, a documentation, schemas, tools (e.g. compiler, stylesheets) • The TEI is a consortium of individual and institutional members • The TEI is above all a lively community (cf. TEI list) • It has a thing called ODD, which always sounds mysterious but is mega cool…</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The TEI guidelines: an open standard</head><p>• What is a standard?</p><p>• The three pillars of a standard: consensus building, public availability, systematic review</p><p>• What is an open standard?</p><p>• Freely available schemas and documentation (AAMOF all TEI stuff is online) • Clear licencing: CC-BY and BSD 2 clauses</p><p>• Opening up the standardisation process itself The TEI model as a paragon of well-managed research data</p><p>• Never loose track of your documentation: embedded meta-data -open metadata</p><p>• The TEI offers a reference framework for documenting a digital document</p><p>• Source -contributions -versions -publication • See next slide: the &lt;teiHeader&gt; is complex, but essential for proper digital object management</p><p>• The integration of the header within the document itself is a central concept for information tracing</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Semantic encoding: what you tag is what you mean -open semantics</head><p>• The TEI vocabulary is conceived to make the encoding of content as transparent to the underlying semantic as possible</p><p>• Proximity to the scholarly objectives and needs</p><p>• Beyond syntax: the written guidelines (prose, examples) are often more important than the schema</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• The next stage: Embedded annotations -open commentaries</head><p>• Developing the &lt;standOff&gt; element to provide the same level of requirement on the process of document annotation (human -automatic)</p><p>• Remaining issues: providing a real documentation with the header Impacting on future practices -fair citing of contributors</p><p>• The TEI has introduced a strong culture for documenting contributors to a document</p><p>• Specific elements: &lt;author&gt;, &lt;editor&gt;, &lt;funder&gt;, &lt;principal&gt;, &lt;sponsor&gt; • Generic &lt;respStmt&gt; element</p><p>• Citing everyone from student to PI</p><p>• Essential for a proper attribution of the work done • Richer than any "text" citation (cf. &lt;publicationStmt&gt;)</p><p>• An emerging trend </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ODD in a nutshell</head><p>• ODD: an instance of the Literate programming model (Knuth 1984)</p><p>• One specification comprises</p><p>• The formal definition =&gt; from which one can derive, e.g., a RelaxNG schema • The prose documentation =&gt; html, pdf, docx, ePub etc.</p><p>• ODD is a TEI vocabulary =&gt; open models • The TEI guidelines are expressed in ODD • You can derive TEI customisations from the guidelines using ODD</p><p>• Basis for any project documentation • Customisations can be further "chained"</p><p>• You can also specify non-TEI vocabularies in ODD Publications can be part of the TEI ecosystem!</p><p>• An obvious member of the TEI document landscape (cf. Holmes and Romary 2010)</p><p>• A publication is a text document + stuff: precise metadata, structure, references • Customisation facilitates adaptation to specific publication objects (articles, book, slides)</p><p>• Natural continuum with other sources (primary -secondary source continuum)</p><p>• Used in various projects and tools • What about JATS?</p><p>• Narrow niche (lack of interoperability with other textual sources), bad standardisation management (sigh…), shaky design (vague TEI plagiarism) -Vergiss es!</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consequences for TEI-based projects</head><p>• The various ways to be in line with the TEI technical and cultural background:</p><p>• Show the source: always show the scholarly perspective behind a nice looking website • Show your ODD: describe the (scholarly) reasons behind the specific data model you've designed • Show your software: you never know, it can be useful to one of your followers • Going further: showing the process • Stages, versions, incomplete digitisation or encoding etc.</p><p>• And public hosting! • Beyond citation, post your data reuse charter declaration (in TEI?)</p><p>Outline of a possible TEI-centered data reuse charter declaration</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Reciprocity</head><p>• Reciprocal provision of corrections, enrichments, annotations</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Interoperability</head><p>• All content is conformant to the TEI guidelines</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Citability</head><p>• Engagement of citing all sources • Provision of a reference citation format in the teiHeader's</p><p>• Openness</p><p>• Provision of the ODD • Provision of the source content in TEI</p><p>• Stewardship</p><p>• [depending on the project and the available infrastructure]</p><p>• Trustworthiness • Online presence (Kudos to @ttasovac)</p><p>• Applying the TEI principles • Dictionaries and copyright</p><p>• The future is bright, except for the content</p><p>• Dealing with the legacy world • Problem to be solve</p><p>• Providing a completely transparent and open description of the underlying content</p><p>• applying standards when describing standards</p><p>• Solution</p><p>• The TEI as the description language (&lt;event&gt;!)</p><p>Let's have a ride… </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SSK -lessons learnt</head><p>• The TEI has been an essential tool in the specification and deployment of the SSK</p><p>• Underlying data modelling possibilities • Transparency of descriptions • Ease of maintenance (GitHub)</p><p>• Citation made easy</p><p>• Towards new realms for the TEI </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
