<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">34FFB299CD76B95E164274802510BE6D</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Understanding the role of scholarly journals</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Registration</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dissemination</head><p>Peer review</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Archival record</head><p>The current scholarly journal landscape is locking the whole process as one single workflow Main functions of scholarly journals <ref type="bibr">(Mabe, 2010)</ref> • Registration: used to claim priority</p><p>• Dissemination: receiving feedback, getting fame</p><p>• Peer review: canvassing content to fit into the expected model</p><p>• Archival record: obliviating a personal management of publication assets</p><p>Consequences on scholars' attitude/objectives:</p><p>Issues with the current scholarly system</p><p>• Ambiguity of the term publication</p><p>• Making something public</p><p>• Cf. use of online documents in patent examination</p><p>• Having it peer-reviewed</p><p>• "How many publications do you have?"</p><p>• Reflected in the terminology: preprint -postprint • Raises a lot of critical IP issues</p><p>• Who has the rights on a given document? Author vs. publisher</p><p>• Variety of peer-reviewed (or not) objects</p><p>• Journal paper, conference proceedings, books, book chapters, blog posts, data sets, educational objects (cf. DARIAH campus) etc.</p><p>• What counts as a "publication"?</p><p>• The scholarly publishing business</p><p>• Price and copyright • Open access publishing has not necessarily contributed to improving the landscape</p><p>• Bias towards publishing more (not just predatory journals), to earn more, not to improve science</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General issues related to peer review</head><p>• A slow and inefficient process?</p><p>• Time to publica-on • Subjec-vity and biased judgement • Small number of reviewers, one stop shop for being accessible</p><p>• ORen leads to desk rejec5on (by editor, prior to any peer review)</p><p>• Conserva-sm</p><p>• Journal topics, editorial cau5ousness, level of exper5se ("I don't understand this new idea")</p><p>• Leads to cascading submissions and possibly to research invisibility</p><p>• Benjamin List, director at the Max Planck Ins.tut für Kohlenforschung in Mülheim an der Ruhr, Germany, and the editor-in-chief of Synle&amp;.</p><p>• "When it works -and that's much of the -me -peer review is a wondrous thing. But all too o^en, it can be an exercise in frustra-on for all concerned. Authors are on tenterhooks to learn of poten-ally career-changing decisions. Generous peer-reviewers are overwhelmed. And editors are condemned to doggedly sending reminders weeks a^er deadlines pass."</p><p>• Source: (List, 2017)</p><p>Escaping the increasing journal desperation</p><p>• Tough figures  <ref type="formula">2015</ref>) reported that across a range of journals, the supply of submitted papers exceeded reviewer availability by between 15 and 249%</p><p>• 63.4 million hours were devoted to peer review, of which 18.9 million hours were undertaken by the top 5% of contributing reviewers</p><p>• (Villar, 2019) "why not practise immediate acceptance, too?"</p><p>• "is it time to consider whether a paper needs review on submission in the first place?"</p><p>• "[I]t seems that the strong coupling between journals and peer review as a requirement to protect scientific integrity seems to undermine the very foundations of scholarly inquiry."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Decoupling publication and peer review with PPPR</head><p>General principles of post publication peer review</p><p>• By definition: providing an assessment mechanism after a scholarly document has been "published", i.e. made publicly available • Two basic building blocks</p><p>• A publication repository where the document is made available (host) • A certification platforms that allows reviewers to carry out their assessment (overlay service)</p><p>• Beyond these basic concepts, a variety of approaches</p><p>Various forms of PPPR -1</p><p>• Un-peer-reviewed material vs already reviewed material</p><p>• PPPR as the first assessment process Various forms of PPPR -2</p><p>• Levels of formality (free vs. channelled PPPR)</p><p>• Formally invited reviewers, after publication of the un-reviewed article • Volunteer reviewers, after publication of the un-reviewed article</p><p>• Credits associated to potential reviews</p><p>• E.g. Science Open, The Winnover</p><p>• Cf. commenting system already existing in traditional journals</p><p>• Comments on a 3rd party site (e.g. Blog or dedicated commenting platform)</p><p>• Towards a free commenting space</p><p>• PubPeer, Pubmed Commons, ResearchGate, Academia</p><p>Channelled peer-review as a process</p><p>• "journals could institute periodic post-publication review, in which the journal would solicit formal review of the article, focusing on how well its methods and results have held up, given the research that has been published in the intervening period. Such reviews would provide valuable historical perspective." (T.A. Gibson, Nature-Correspondance, 2007)</p><p>• Note: PPPR seen as an opportunity to question the traditional peerreview process</p><p>A disruptive view on scholarly publishing?</p><p>• Contributes to getting a disruptive view on publishing in any case…</p><p>• Beyond "open access"</p><p>• Services</p><p>• Better identification of the services needed for scholarly publication • Better specification of the workflows/interfaces between them (cf. COAR initiative)</p><p>• Better compensation models for peer reviewers</p><p>• Better tracing, better acknowledgements (cf. Publons),</p><p>• Business models</p><p>• Contributing to associating precise costs to services:</p><p>• to hosting, certification, long-term archiving • Cf. PEER project economic report</p><p>• Getting a better estimate of what we pay with commercial offers</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Caveats</head><p>• Theoretical decoupling?</p><p>• E.g. F1000, myScienceWorks (not to mention RG or Academia)</p><p>• Not so disruptive because not so novel… So in a way, this is not new…</p><p>• Papers presented at a conference before publishing a journal full version, or an edited book • Comments from colleagues, scholarly correspondence  • Ensuring an open scholarly debate (see Pubpeer) The controversies over anonymity in post-publication peer review"</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>We see the point where open science and post publication peer review may come into the game Back to basics: the role of scholarly publication (Tennant et al. 2019) • Makes science public • Ensures the quality of science • Defines anteriority of results • Makes articles searchable/findable • Archives for the future Melanie Imming, Jon Tennant. (2018). http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.128557 Do the current scholarly publication mechanisms fulfil these requirements? The scholarly publishing tension (Tennant et al. 2019) (A) TradiVonal peer review publishing workflow. (B) Preprint submission establishing priority of discovery.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Cf. "LMF and TEI crosswalks": hVps://hal.inria.fr/hal-00762664v4 • LeWers to the Editor • Formal reviews as publicaYons • Recensions in the SSH domain • Comments on a blog post Challenges for post-publication peer review • Ensuring participation • Limited corpus of papers gaining interest, bias towards controversial ones (cf. Science Open, The Winnower) • Traditional reviewers' selection proves more efficient • Controlling reviewers' expertise • Science Open requires reviewers to have five articles in ORCID, PubMed Commons requires one article in PubMed. • No check of expertise in the field of the commented article • Preventing the fragmentation of discussions</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>•PubPeer•</head><label></label><figDesc>'gotcha' mentality • Encouraging online junk… or fostering responsibility (online persona) .1 Practices, evaluation and mapping: Methods, tools and user needs. http://openup-h2020.eu/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/OpenUP_D3.1_Peer-review-landscape-report-1.pdf Post (peer-reviewed) publication peer review Conceived for the biological domain • Objective of the creators: develop critical thinking • Workflow • Based upon already published papers (DOI, entry in ArXiv as identification means) • Open comments à la Amazon =&gt; automatic notification of authors • Possible answers from authors • Commenters remain anonymous • Not part of the initial design, but as a request from younger scholars • Shift in practices: whistle blowing and/or harassment • Cf. Torny, 2018: "Pubpeer: vigilante science, journal club or alarm raiser?</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,132.28,313.58,417.19,186.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,668.49,-0.00,292.78,540.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="14,3.62,130.33,550.00,390.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="28,614.98,298.03,341.17,240.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="36,179.68,207.87,636.30,216.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="44,90.60,101.53,780.00,438.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="48,79.09,156.53,750.78,349.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="49,113.24,154.91,773.12,354.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>• A general issue of social networks: comments on the article itself (if that feature is available), in PubPeer, on PubMed Commons, on Research Gate, on blogs, on Twitter, on F1000Prime…</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Failed attempts -PubMed Commons</head><p>• Platform launched in 2013 (NIH's National Library of Medicine (NLM))</p><p>• Posting comments on any published paper indexed by PubMed (Registered users)</p><p>• "responsible post-publication peer review,"</p><p>• Comments that can be viewed by anyone accessing the paper</p><p>• Closes door in 2018:</p><p>• Low levels of engagement</p><p>• Alternate venues for public discussion</p><p>• PubPeer, journals' sites (BMJ, PLOS, eLife)</p><p>• "it just wasn't really useful, let alone essential"</p><p>Cf. Dolgin, 2018</p><p>Post publication peer-review of authors' manuscripts The baseline: a publication repository     • Long-term archiving</p><p>• Advantages for the user      • Article submission in F1000 repository ("publication") • Peer review by invited referees </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Episciences -lessons learnt</head><p>• Variable acceptance of the post-publication peer-review model</p><p>• Candidate journals may be frightened by the feature</p><p>• Sustainability</p><p>• Decoupling the sustainability of content from that of the certification platforms</p><p>• Towards even more certification models</p><p>• Open peer review, author's initiative, community review</p><p>• "Transitioning" from the existing journal eco-system</p><p>• Candidate journals are reassured to feel "at home"</p><p>• Raises a few questions</p><p>• Community and traditional review in parallel</p><p>• Authors ask friends to provide feedback during the review process</p><p>• Multiple branding The Peer Community in (PCI) project</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>How does this work?</head><p>Source: https://peercommunityin.org "We would value the recommendations seriously and may even use them for handling without further peer review (only peer review by handling editors)" etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PCI and journals</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Generalising PPPR plaGorms</head><p>The COAR initiative Modelling Overlay Peer Review Processes with Linked Data Notifications (Walk, 2020)</p><p>• An initiative by COAR (cf. Pubfair)</p><p>• Cf. report: Next Generation Repository (NGR)</p><p>• Resource-centric network (metadata and content)</p><p>• Connected with resource-oriented networked services Where do we stand?</p><p>• Building blocks of a generalized architecture for PPPR</p><p>• Covering a wide variety of scholarly objects</p><p>• Contributing to the evolution of peer review</p><p>• Decoupling prevents peer review from being a go/no-go activity • Scholarly relevance seen as a long term activity</p><p>• Lessons for DARIAH</p><p>• Understanding</p><p>• Looking at existing platforms, matching features to SSH needs</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Recommending</head><p>• As part of DARIAH's open science policy (e.g. preprints, early publication of results)</p><p>• Experimenting</p><p>• Data journals, assessment of educational material (DARIAH campus)</p><p>• Need for a cultural revolution?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Merci pour votre aIenJon</head><p>Some references • Mark Ware and Michael Mabe, 'The STM Report: An Overview of Scientific and Scholarly Journal Publishing', 2015.</p><p>• "Why Figshare? Choosing a New Technical Infrastructure for 4TU.ResearchData." 2020. Open Working (blog). August 18, 2020. https://openworking.wordpress.com/2020/08/18/whyfigshare-choosing-a-new-technical-infrastructure-for-4tu-researchdata/.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
