<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Automating Artl@s -extracting data from exhibition catalogues</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Gabay</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">université de Genève</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Barbara</forename><surname>Topalov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">université de Genève</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Caroline</forename><surname>Corbières</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Paris-Saclay (France)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lucie</forename><surname>Rondeau Du Noyer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">université de Genève</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Béatrice</forename><surname>Joyeux-Prunel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">université de Genève</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">INRIA-ALMANACH (France)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Automating Artl@s -extracting data from exhibition catalogues</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">252CF58B050CE8E0F9F41ABACDC86AA7</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T14:59+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Catalogues, which have been published for centuries, are an extremely precious resource for scholars. Using the Artl@s database as an example, where exhibition catalogues are transformed into a georeferenced database, we question the possibility of an (almost) automatic transformation of pdfs into semantically annotated data. To do so, we present and analyse the graphic organisation of exhibition catalogues, before exploring a possible modeling into TEI (involving possible enhancement of the guidelines).</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Databases for art history usually focus on images, and are primarily made by or for museums to display collections (or inventories). 1 Other databases do not focus on the work of art itself, but on a corpus about the work of artsuch as databases used for provenance research 2 or by collectors monitoring the market 3 . The BasArt database of the Artl@s project 4 belongs to the second category as it aims at recording exhibitions all over the world since the invention of exhibition catalogues in the 17th century (Paris, Salon de l'Académie, 1673) 5 . BasArt is essential for art history, not only because it makes available one of the most widely used sources in the discipline, at a global scale and over several centuries, but also because it makes it possible to globalise the horizons of research and to move on to unusual quantitative, spatial, and transnational analyses, without specific knowledge in digital technologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Joyeux-Prunel and Marcel 2015)</ref>.</p><p>If data has long been entered manually, by simply copying the content that in the exhibition catalogues describes the works exhibited, we are now designing a new workflow, based on GROBID dictionaries technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Khemakhem 2020)</ref>, to semi-automate the task, that is to say to retrieve the content from pdf digitisation of the catalogues, describe it semantically, in order to transform the XML-TEI output of this new workflow into the structured BasArt postGIS database. As our database is structured to deal with catalogues from very different periods of time, and from very diverse locations and languages, we intend to take advantage of the tasks involved in designing a semi-automated retrieving chain -in particular, the description necessary to train recognition algorithms -, to produce research on the history of the form of exhibition catalogues over time and space, and according to the language. The project's ambition is also to enable broader developments that will be useful for other projects dealing with comparable resources and corpora -such as auction catalogues, collection directories, or catalogues raisonnés.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Exhibition catalogues</head><p>In order to semantically describe catalogues, we need to analyse their form. This form has a history, which meets the history of the inventory, whose description is a challenge for anyone who wishes to model their structure, but also try to generalise this modeling to any type of similar documents. The inventorium (inventory) can be considered as an early form and the origin of the catalogue. This list of a set of objects forming a collection was originally built by recording collection items in the very order in which they were stored or displayed <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Barbier, Dubois, and Sordet 2015)</ref>. That is why in France, as early as the Middle Ages, inventories were primarily used to associate a given object to the place where it was preserved. The inventory is first and foremost a practical tool: it is meant to find and identify an object. Inventories also have a scientific/epistemic interest insofar as the classification of objects echoes the classifications of the natural sciences, especially in the case of curiosities cabinets <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Findlen 1996)</ref>. The practice of classifying allows comparison: "Unlike the inventory, the catalogue organises a set of data and arranges them by object, so as to make them comparable with each other." <ref type="bibr">(Recht 1996, p. 23)</ref>.</p><p>With the advent of printing, and the ability to publish inventories for a wider audience, the form of the inventory became semi-industrialised for a few particular types: the catalogues raisonnés of an artist's work, the inventory of a private collection or a museum, the dealer's catalogue, the auction catalogue, the exhibition catalogue. It is with this type of printed data that we believe we can develop a semi-automated pipeline for content retrieval. This process begins with the example of exhibition catalogues.</p><p>Generally the content of an exhibition catalogue is quite regular : informa- tion about the event exhibition, its title, date, supposed location, its organisers; a list of the exhibitors -first and last name, sometimes completed by biographical detail, a year and place of birth and an address. Most exhibition catalogues complete these lists of artists with a list, for each exhibitor, of the works exhibited (Joyeux-Prunel and Marcel 2015). Whereas this content is not always represented in the same way in the book-catalogue, it is actually organised according to a limited number of possibilities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">A Stable Layout, Over Time and Place</head><p>In the documentation we have gathered (c. 1000 catalogues since the 18 th c., mainly from Western countries), the most recurrent format displays the following information: name of the artist (here, highlighted in red), information about the artist (blue) and a list of the works exhibited (yellow) with potentially additional information (green).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Type 1</head><p>Salons, yearly municipal exhibitions and academy exhibitions which were held regularly since the 18th century, usually published catalogues with a very stable layout over time:      Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>: Tentoonstelling van schilder-en andere werken…, 1852, p.12.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Type 2</head><p>A secondary structure coexists with the latter one -a structure that first presents the number and the title of the work, followed by the name of its author. The order is relatively opposite to that described above. This second type of layout, following the exhibition order, has been used for the Exhibition of the Royal Academy in London since 1780, but it can be found in other countries (e.g. Canada). It has been extremely stable over time too.    We assume for the moment that these two types may have corresponded to different areas of cultural influence -on the one hand the influence of the Parisian Salon catalogue model, on the other that of a more Anglo-Saxon model. It is likely that another factor explaining these differences is simply that catalogues by work order assume a more commercial character, where it is the work for sale that is presented, and not the artist. This hypothesis is supported by the presence of Type 2 in many gallery catalogues in the early 20 th c.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Beyond exhibition catalogues</head><p>According to the two types presented supra, entries can be grouped under superentries, which potentially transmit general properties to entries that they include such as the location of the work in the exhibition (gallery 1, red wing…), or more importantly artistic forms (paintings, sculpture, architecture…). These two types can be found in similar documents, the structure of which is very similar to exhibition catalogues: bibliographies <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Lindemann, Khemakhem, and Romary 2018)</ref>, dictionaries <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Khemakhem, Herold, and Romary 2018)</ref>, auction catalogues <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Gabay, Rondeau Du Noyer, and Khemakhem 2020)</ref>, and phone directories <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Khemakhem, Brando, et al. 2018)</ref>.  Such data has been recently identified as "encyclopedic-like" <ref type="bibr">(Khemakhem, Romary, et al. 2018)</ref>, i.e. entry-based data for which a dedicated retrieval tool has been developed: GROBID dictionaries (Khemakhem 2020). Thanks to the latter, PDF files are automatically structured and annotated in XML-TEI files, which is used as a pivot format to ease encoding refinements via regexes.</p><p>The current TEI guidelines<ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">6</ref> propose elements allowing research to encode various kinds of lists (&lt;list&gt;, &lt;listPerson&gt;, &lt;listPlaces&gt;, &lt;listObject&gt;…) and their content (&lt;item&gt;, &lt;person&gt;, &lt;place&gt;, &lt;object&gt;…). However, some scholars have noted that encoding a catalogue as a "mere list" was not sufficient if some of its entries feature analytical or descriptive content <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Nelson 2016)</ref>. Therefore, following the work on dictionaries with TEI-lex 0 (Romary and Tasovac 2018) on the &lt;entry&gt; element, we would like to propose to the TEI Consortium the creation of a &lt;catalogueEntry&gt; element. The behaviour of this TEI markup would be similar to &lt;entry&gt;, transforming &lt;form&gt; and &lt;sense&gt; elements into &lt;catalogueDesc&gt; and &lt;catalogueItem&gt;. A possible encoding would therefore be the one presented infra.</p><p>The stakes of this type of classification are both to allow a clearer description of the content, and the possibility of spreadsheet-type retrievals, where the dependencies of a sub-entry on its entry would be maintained (in particular in the repetition of the entry for each line of the sub-entry in the case of an export in csv). This type of processing is ideal for a pivot to databases, more easily handled by users interested in quantitative and cartographic visualisation as is the case for the Artl@s project. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Catalogue de l'exposition annuelle du musée de Rouen, 1860, p. 19.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,133.77,124.80,343.71,99.37" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Catalogue de l'exposition… de Rouen, 1853, p. 4.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,133.89,535.52,164.98,88.99" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Catalogue de l'exposition… de Rouen, 1862, p. 26.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,312.38,541.58,164.98,76.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Catalogue… exposés à Nancy, 1843, p. 3.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,278.01,325.89,199.35,52.07" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Société des artistes indépendants, 1921, p. 17.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Esposizione Inter-nazionale… di Venezia, 1910.Figure 7: Bienal de São Paulo, 1951, p. 54.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,197.47,412.83,206.23,50.62" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Esposizione Inter-nazionale… di Venezia, 1910.Figure 7: Bienal de São Paulo, 1951, p. 54.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: The Exhibition of the Royal Academy, 1785, p. 1.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,133.89,136.76,171.86,64.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10: The Exhibition of the Royal Academy, 1831, p. 6.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,319.25,137.06,158.11,64.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 11 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11: The Exhibition of the Royal Academy, 1907, p. 8.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,133.89,248.97,171.86,64.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 12: The Exhibition of the Royal Academy, 1975, p. 10.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,319.25,248.53,158.11,65.36" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 13 :</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Figure 13: Type 1 Figure 14: Type 2</figDesc><graphic coords="5,187.63,542.12,64.37,113.39" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 15 :</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Figure 15: Annuaire-Almanach de l'industrie, 1901, p. 2883 compared to the Catalogue de l'exposition annuelle du musée de Rouen, 1860, p. 19.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,190.42,209.98,285.28,82.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 16 :Figure 17 :</head><label>1617</label><figDesc>Figure 16: Catalogue de feu M. de Bruyères Chalabre,1833, p. 102 Figure 17: Annuaire des imprimeurs et des libraires, 1841, p. 135</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 18 :</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Figure 18: TEI encoding of a catalogue entry.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,133.77,197.59,343.71,240.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>http://mandragore.bnf.fr/html/accueil.html</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>For instance http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/provenance/search.html or https: //ventesdantiques.inha.fr</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>https://fr.artprice.com/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_3"><p>https://artlas.huma-num.fr</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_4"><p>According to<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Guiffrey 1869</ref> </p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_5"><p>https://tei-c.org/guidelines</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data and code</head><p>The ODD, the specification and an example can be found at the following address: https://github.com/katabase/Catalogues.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">De l&apos;argile au nuage : une archéologie des catalogues IIe millénaire av</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Barbier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sordet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bibliothèque Mazarine, 13 mars-13 mai</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-C.-Xxie</forename><surname>Siècle</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Paris; Genève, Bibliothèque de Genève; Paris; Genève</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Bibliothèque Mazarine-Éditions des Cendres Bibliothèque de Genève</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015. 18 septembre-21 novembre 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">429</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1 vols</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Possessing nature : museums, collecting, and scientific culture in early modern Italy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Findlen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>978-0-520-20508-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Studies on the history of society and culture</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="432" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>University of California press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berkeley Los Angeles London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Country: US ill. 23 cm. Bibliogr</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selling autograph manuscripts in 19th c. Paris: digitising the Revue des Autographes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gabay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">Rondeau</forename><surname>Du Noyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Atti del IX Convegno Annuale AIUCD. La svolta inevitabile: sfide e prospettive per l&apos;Informatica Umanistica. AIUCD2020. Quaderni di Umanistica Digitale</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Milan, Italy</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Associazione per l&apos;Informatica Umanistica e la Cultura Digitale</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="118" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Collection des livrets des anciennes expositions depuis 1673 jusqu&apos;en 1800</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guiffrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://catalogue.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cb33308085f" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1869">1869</date>
			<publisher>Liepmannssohn et Dufour</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Paris; Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>visited on 06/01/2021</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exhibition Catalogues in the Globalization of Art. A Source for Social and Spatial Art History</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Joyeux-Prunel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Marcel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://docs.lib.purdue.edu/artlas/vol4/iss2/8" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Artl@s Bulletin</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2264-2668</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Standard-based Lexical Models for Automatically Structured Dictionaries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>INRIA</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fueling Time Machine: Information Extraction from Retro-Digitised Address Directories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Brando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>JADH2018</idno>
		<ptr target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01814189" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">Sept. 2018. 2018</date>
			<publisher>JADH</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Tokyo, Japan</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Leveraging Open Data. visited on 09/11/2019</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhancing Usability for Automatically Structuring Digitised Dictionaries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Herold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01708137" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">GLOB-ALEX workshop at LREC 2018. Miyazaki, Japan</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-05">May 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Automatically Encoding Encyclopedic-like Resources in TEI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>TEI2018</idno>
		<ptr target="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01819505" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-09">Sept. 9, 2018</date>
			<pubPlace>Tokyo, Japan</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>visited on 09/11/2019</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Retrodigitizing and Automatically Structuring a Large Bibliography Collection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lindemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01941534" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Conference. Galway</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-12">Dec. 2018</date>
			<publisher>EADH</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ireland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Curating Object-Oriented Collections Using the TEI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4000/jtei.1680</idno>
		<ptr target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1680" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Number: Issue 9 Publisher: Text Encoding Initiative Consortium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">Sept. 24, 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>visited on 06/01/2021</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">La Mise en ordre : note sur l&apos;histoire du catalogue</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Recht</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Les Cahiers du Musée National d&apos;Art Moderne</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TEI Lex-0: A Target Format for TEI-Encoded Dictionaries and Lexical Resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tasovac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.2613594</idno>
		<ptr target="https://zenodo.org/record/2613594#.YGBGHEgzZPM" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Book of AbstractsThe 18th Annual TEI Conference and Members&apos; Meeting. TEI 2018. Conference Name: TEI 2018: TEI as a Global Language (TEI2018) Publisher: Zenodo</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Tokyo, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>visited on 03/28/2021</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
