<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">ISO LMF 24613-6: A Revised Syntax Semantics Module for the Lexical Markup Framework</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Francesca</forename><surname>Frontini</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">CNR-ILC</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Pisa</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anas</forename><forename type="middle">Fahad</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">CNR-ILC</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Pisa</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
							<email>laurent.romary@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Inria -Scientific Information and Culture Directorate</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">ISO LMF 24613-6: A Revised Syntax Semantics Module for the Lexical Markup Framework</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B82BA468433D7B21BB4F8F6EA3EAC3F5</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-08-24T15:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The Lexical Markup Framework (LMF) is a meta-model for representing data in monolingual and multilingual lexical databases with a view to its use in computer applications. The "new LMF" replaces the old LMF standard, ISO 24613:2008, and is being published as a multi-part standard. This short paper introduces one of these new parts, ISO 24613-6, namely the Syntax and Semantics (SynSem) module. The SynSem module allows for the description of syntactic and semantic properties of lexemes, as well as the complex interactions between them. While the new standard remains faithful to (and backwards compatible with) the syntax and semantics coverage of the previous model, the new standard clarifies and simplifies it in a few places, which will be illustrated.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The Lexical Markup Framework (LMF) is undoubtedly one of the most influential lexical standards of the last two decades. First published in 2008 by the International Standards Organization (ISO) as ISO standard 24613:2008 it was intended as a "standardized framework for the construction of computational lexicons" <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Francopoulo, 2013)</ref>. LMF was developed with a special focus on two different kinds of lexicon, namely, digital born electronic lexicons specifically intended for use by Natural Language Processing applications, so called NLP dictionaries, as well as for electronic versions of print dictionaries, or more generally lexicons primarily intended for human consumption, so called Machine Readable Dictionaries (MRD). The original LMF, ISO 24613:2008, contained, two modules for syntax and semantics, respectively, whose scope, taken together, was to provide means of representing the syntactic and semantic argument structure of individual lexical entries. The approach taken by the original committee tasked with drafting LMF was a theory agnostic one which identified a nucleus of elements that were generic enough to allow for the modelling of syntax, semantics and their interface without any particular theoretical bias. After its publication in 2008, LMF came to be used by a variety of different organisations and in a number of national and international projects<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> . In particular, the syntactic and semantics models were extensively used in projects such as PAROLE and SIMPLE <ref type="bibr">(Ruimy et al.; Lenci et al.)</ref> as well as being the basis for other models of the syntax/semantics interface in lexical resources, such as the W3C OntoLex Syntax and Semantics Module 2 .</p><p>After a detailed review of the original standard, however, the decision was made in 2015 to revise LMF and, what's more, to make it a multi-part standard with each part being published separately (as distinguished from the old LMF standard which was published in a single part but which contained separate modules as sub-parts). This new multipart version of LMF is currently being developed within the standardisation sub-committee ISO TC 37/SC 4/WG 4 (to which the authors of the current article are all contributing), with the first five parts of the new version having already been published, and other parts at an advanced stage of completion. The current paper is dedicated to ISO 24613-6, a soon-to-be published part of the revised LMF standard dealing with Syntax and Semantics (henceforth SynSem), two areas which as we mentioned above were previously covered by separate modules in the old LMF. SynSem stays true to the overall approach of ISO 24613:2008, but some simplifications/modifications were introduced. In what follows, we shall begin by placing SynSem in the context of the new multipart LMF, and providing an update as to its current status. Then we shall describe the constituent parts of the standard: Syntax, Semantics, and SynSem interface. Finally we shall provide some details as to its serialisation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">An Overview of the New Multipart LMF</head><p>Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Romary et al., 2019)</ref> we provide a list of the new LMF parts in the present section along with their current status. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">The New SynSem module</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> gives the SynSem class diagram. The classes in white (Lexical Entry, Sense and SenseRelation) are inherited from the LMF core (Part 1), while the salmon-pink coloured classes are newly defined in Part 6. Notably, Part 6 introduces two important new classes which provide the means to describe both the Syntactic Behaviour of entries and the Predicative Representation of senses as well as allowing for the specification of connections between the two. The main difference with respect to ISO 24613:2008 is the absence of the previously defined Synset class. Indeed the semantic module of the prior version of LMF contained elements that were entirely dedicated to the modelling of WordNet-like lexicons. However, this was not judged to be necessary in the current standard since the Sense and SenseRelation classes can be used instead.</p><p>Another crucial difference with respect to the former version of LMF is the lack of a feat class, formerly used to make up for specific elements which a lexicographer may want to introduce but which were not generic enough to be included in the model. In the old model, class arguments could be specified as pairs of attributes of the specific tag feat: att would contain the name of the attribute, and val the value. In the new model, attributes can be added as needed; in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> for example a SemanticArgument can be specified in terms of type and restriction. Generally speaking -and here guided by the same principle already introduced for other parts -only the core features of the syntax and semantics interface are described in the present UML based standardisation, however the user can extend the model to add other features.</p><p>Regarding the modelling of syntax in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>, a LexicalEntry may have one or more instances of SyntacticBehaviour, associated with separate SubcategorizationFrame instances, each described with SyntacticArgument. As for the modelling of semantics, it applies to senses. The Sense class, which is specified in the core package, is aggregated in the LexicalEntry class. A PredicativeRepresentation serves to connect a Sense with one or more instances of SemanticPredicate, which are described in terms of SemanticArgument instances. Linking between syntax and semantics is done by the SynSemArgMap component, which links a Se-manticArgument with a SyntacticArgument.</p><p>In modelling semantics, allowance is made in Part 6 for drawing from other relevant standards.</p><p>In particular ISO 24617-4:2014 (en) -Language resource management -Semantic annotation framework (SemAF) -Part 4: Semantic roles (SemAF-SR) provides a background terminology and methodology for designing a semantic role scheme in a coherent way, based upon the work carried out in the LIRICS projects ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Petukhova and Bunt, 2008)</ref>. The examples provided in this paper illustrate the use of such roles without providing a normative list thereof.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Examples</head><p>In this section we will illustrate Part 6 in more detail by means of an exhaustive example (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>), drawn from the Parole Simple CLIPS Italian lexicon<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">3</ref> . The example contains two lexical entries, the Italian verb costruire ('to build') and the deverbal noun costruzione ('a building'). For simplicity's sake, in this example each entry has just one sense (though many are possible), each linked to a separate PerdicativeRepresentation, but these are in turn linked to just one SemanticPredicate (PREDcostruire-1). The predicate is described with its two arguments to which are added semantic roles, and restrictions (the latter represented by types in the SIMPLE ontology <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Del Gratta et al., 2015)</ref>). From the syntactic point of view, a Syntac-ticBehaviour element links the LexicalEntry to a SubcategorizationFrame SCFtxa, representing the transitive construction, which is in turn described by its two syntactic arguments (subject and object). A SynSemCorrespondence component (of type ISObivalent) allows for a mapping between each pair of syntactic/semantic arguments. In this rather straightforward case, the subject maps onto the agent and the object onto the patient. Finally a further diagram (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>) illustrates how syntactic alternations can be represented. In the example, which represents the anti-causative syntactic alternation, a SubcategorizationFrameSet has been created to connect two SubcategorizationFrames that can be subject to alternation, as in the case of the transitive and intransitive in verbs such as bollire ('boil') <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">4</ref> . The SynArgMap class can also be used to represent the link between syntactic arguments: in this case the representation tells us that the object in the transitive construction becomes the subject of the intransitive one.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Serialisation</head><p>We designed the serialisation of ISO LMF 24613-6 as an extension of the TEI guidelines<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">5</ref> . In doing so, we wanted to achieve the following objectives:</p><p>• Maintain coherence with the overall serialisation framework for LMF which has already set out a dedicated TEI subset covering parts 1, 2 and 3 within the ISO LMF 24613-4 standard;</p><p>• Benefit from the TEI specification language ODD ("One Document Does it all") which provides a flexible framework compatible with literate programming principles and which allows for the generation of both schemas (DtD, RelaxNG, W3C) and documentation from a single specification document;</p><p>• Integrate the specific development of LMF syntax and semantic descriptions within a broader lexicographic landscape in which the the TEI guidelines have been widely adopted (also within the framework of the TEI Lex 0 initiative<ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">6</ref> ) for maintaining sustainable lexical resources, which are thus FAIR by construction.</p><p>More precisely, we integrated SynSem components at three specific places within the standard structure of a TEI lexical entry:</p><p>• We added a &lt;syntacticBehaviour&gt; element to the possible grammatical descriptions associated with a lemma (within the TEI &lt;gramGrp&gt; element) that points to a sub-categorisation frame (see below);</p><p>• The content of the TEI &lt;sense&gt; element was expanded to contain a &lt;predicativeRepresen-tation&gt; element with references to a semantic predicate and possible syntactic-semantic correspondences;</p><p>• We extended the general intermediate of a TEI document to allow &lt;subcategorization-Frame&gt;, &lt;SemanticPredicate&gt; and &lt;SynSem-Correspondence&gt; elements to occur freely and be referred to from &lt;syntacticBehaviour&gt; and &lt;predicativeRepresentation&gt; within entries.   </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ISO 24613-1:2019 Language resource management -Lexical markup framework (LMF) -Part 1: Core model: This module defines the basic classes required to model a baseline lexicon and is a pre-requisite for the use of the other classes. Status: Published in 2019 it is now being further revised to make it even easier to use. ISO 24613-2:2020 Language resource management -Lexical markup framework (LMF) -Part 2: Machine-readable dictionary (MRD) model: Contains components providing a deeper specification of lexical description encapsulated within the core model. Status: Published in 2020. ISO 24613-3:2021 Language resource management -Lexical markup framework (LMF) -Part 3: Etymological extension: A completely new addition to the LMF meta-model covering etymological and diachronic information. This part makes etymologies, etymological links and etymons first class citizens. See (Khan and Bowers, 2020) for more details. Status: Published in 2021. ISO 24613-4:2021 Language resource management -Lexical markup framework (LMF) -Part 4: TEI serialization: A TEI serialisation of the other parts of the model which aims to make both TEI and LMF fully compatible and which leverages the knowledge and makes use of the established practices of the TEI community in dealing with lexicographic resources. Status: Published in 2021. ISO 24613-5:2022 Language resource management -Lexical markup framework (LMF) -Part 5: Lexical base exchange (LBX) serialization: Another XML serialisation. Status: Published in 2022. ISO/CD 24613-6 Language resource management -Lexical markup framework (LMF) -Part 6: Syntax and Semantics. Status: A candidate for an ISO Draft International Standard (DIS) ballot.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Synsem Module -Class diagram.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,85.04,97.57,425.20,277.46" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: "Bollire" ("boil") syntactic alternation.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,155.91,458.32,283.47,264.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Costuire / costruzione (build/building) in Parole Simple CLIPS.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,147.31,126.52,300.66,566.93" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Searching for "LMF" in the CLARIN Virtual Language Observatory gives a good indication on resources and also tools using the</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2008" xml:id="foot_1"><p>model (https://vlo.clarin.eu/ ?1&amp;q=lmf.2 https://www.w3.org/community/ontolex/ wiki/Syntax_and_Semantics_Module</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>http://hdl.handle.net/20.500.11752/ ILC-88</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_3"><p>This example works in English ("I boil the water/The water boils")</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_4"><p>https://tei-c.org/guidelines/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_5"><p>https://dariah-eric.github.io/ lexicalresources/pages/TEILex0/TEILex0. html</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>All content relating to the serialisation of 24613-6 is available from the DARIAH WG on lexical resources 7 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>The new ISO LMF 24613-6 will soon be available as a published standard. Resources encoded in the previous model are easily converted to the new one, which remains overall backward compatible. Another crucial task will involve developing user-friendly conversion methodologies for other commonly used formats, particularly OntolexLemon, by defining convenient crosswalks. This would, among other things, provide an easy way to go from tree based TEI-XML representations to RDF-based graph-like representations, thus potentially contributing to the extension of the Linguistic Linked Open Data Cloud.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">SIMPLE-LOD. ILC-CNR for CLARIN-IT repository hosted at Institute for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Riccardo</forename><surname>Del Gratta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Francesca</forename><surname>Frontini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anas</forename><surname>Fahad Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Monica</forename><surname>Monachini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<pubPlace>Pisa</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Research Council</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gil</forename><surname>Francopoulo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">LMF lexical markup framework</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Towards a lexical standard for the representation of etymological data. Convegno annuale dell&apos;Associazione per l</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fahad</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jack</forename><surname>Bowers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>Informatica Umanistica e la Cultura Digitale</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">SIM-PLE: A General Framework For The Development Of Multilingual Lexicons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alessandro</forename><surname>Lenci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nuria</forename><surname>Bel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Federica</forename><surname>Busa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicoletta</forename><surname>Calzolari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elisabetta</forename><surname>Gola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Monica</forename><surname>Monachini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Antoine</forename><surname>Ogonowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ivonne</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wim</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nilda</forename><surname>Ruimy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Marta</forename><surname>Villegas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Antonio</forename><surname>Zampolli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ijl/13.4.249</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="263" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LIRICS semantic role annotation: Design and evaluation of a set of data categories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Volha</forename><surname>Petukhova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Harry</forename><surname>Bunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Sixth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC&apos;08)</title>
		<meeting>the Sixth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC&apos;08)<address><addrLine>Marrakech, Morocco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>European Language Resources Association (ELRA</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Khemakhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fahad</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jack</forename><surname>Bowers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicoletta</forename><surname>Calzolari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Monte</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mandy</forename><surname>Pet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Piotr</forename><surname>Bański</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1906.02136.7</idno>
		<ptr target="https://github.com/DARIAH-ERIC/lexicalresources/tree/master/Schemas/LMF%20SynSem%" />
		<title level="m">GitHub project under</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
	<note>Lmf reloaded</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">LE-PAROLE Project: The Italian Syntactic Lexicon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nilda</forename><surname>Ruimy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ornella</forename><surname>Corazzieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elisabetta</forename><surname>Gola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Antonietta</forename><surname>Spanu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicoletta</forename><surname>Calzolari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Antonio</forename><surname>Zampolli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>In EURALEX &apos;98</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
